<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Eurēka, Eurēka the virtuous woman found, her loss bewailed, and character examined in a sermon preached at Felsted in Essex, April 30, 1678, at the funeral of ... Mary, countess dowager of Warwick, the most illustrious pattern of a sincere piety, and solid goodness his age hath produced : with so large additions as may be stiled the life of that noble lady : to which are annexed some of her ladyships pious and useful meditations / by Anthony Walker.</title>
            <author>Walker, Anthony, d. 1692.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1678</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 242 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 118 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66656</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W301</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R233189</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08251488</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08251488</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41197</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66656)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41197)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1243:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Eurēka, Eurēka the virtuous woman found, her loss bewailed, and character examined in a sermon preached at Felsted in Essex, April 30, 1678, at the funeral of ... Mary, countess dowager of Warwick, the most illustrious pattern of a sincere piety, and solid goodness his age hath produced : with so large additions as may be stiled the life of that noble lady : to which are annexed some of her ladyships pious and useful meditations / by Anthony Walker.</title>
                  <author>Walker, Anthony, d. 1692.</author>
                  <author>Warwick, Mary Boyle Rich, Countess of, 1625-1678. Occasional meditations upon sundry subjects.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 213 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Nathanael Ranew,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Occasional meditations upon sundry subjects" by Mary, countess dowager of Warwick, has special t.p.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Warwick, Mary Rich, --  Countess of, 1625-1678.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41197:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41197:1"/>
            <p>ΕΥΡΗΚΑ, ΕΥΡΗΚΑ. THE Virtuous Woman found Her LOSS BEWAILED, AND CHARACTER EXEMPLIFIED IN A SERMON Preached at <hi>Felſted</hi> in <hi>Eſſex, April,</hi> 30, 1678.</p>
            <p>At the Funeral of that moſt Excellent Lady the Right Honourable, and Eminently Religions and Charitable <hi>Mary,</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſs Dowager of <hi>Warwick,</hi> the moſt Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Pattern of Sincere Piety, and Solid Goodneſs this Age hath produced. With ſo Large Additions as may be ſtiled</p>
            <p>THE LIFE OF THAT NOBLE LADY. To which are Annexed ſome of her Ladyſhips Pious and Uſeful Meditations.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Anthony Walker,</hi> D. D. and Rector of <hi>Fyfield</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſame Country.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Nathanael Ranew,</hi> at the <hi>King's Arms</hi> in S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. 1678.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:41197:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Honourable KATHARINE, VICOUNTESS RANALAUGH. AND THE HONOURABLE ROBERT BOYLE, <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Executors of the Laſt Will of the Right Honourable <hi>Mary,</hi> Counteſs Dowa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of <hi>Warwick.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable Madam, and Truly Honourable Sir.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>MY Obedience to the repeated Commands I have received, (for ſo I ſhall always eſteem your Requeſts) from both your</hi> Honours <hi>to publiſh the</hi> Sermon, <hi>I was
<pb facs="tcp:41197:3"/>by the ſame</hi> Authority <hi>engaged to</hi> Preach <hi>at the Funeral of that excellent Lady, the</hi> Genuine <hi>Siſter of your</hi> vertue, <hi>as well as the</hi> Germane <hi>Siſter of your</hi> blood; <hi>had not been guilty of theſe few weeks delays, had not the indiſpoſition which began to ſeize me at ſo near and perplexing a ſtroke, and under which I laboured all the time of my preparations, and in the hour of its delivery, continued upon me many days: After an effect ſo natural to ſo preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing a cauſe, that I know not whether the</hi> health <hi>of my</hi> body <hi>could have conſiſted with the</hi> ſoundneſs <hi>of my</hi> mind, <hi>under ſuch an inexpreſſible loſs to the Church of God, and my poor ſelf in particular.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But what I was conſtrained to defer a while,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ut bonum quo diu fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iti ſumus, etiam caete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris noſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tandumque plenius de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriberem. S. Hier. Ep.</hi> 10 <hi>Epitaphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um mercellae viduae.</hi>
                  </note> I now</hi> multo cum faenore <hi>preſent to you both, with all humble obſervance: and under your favourable protection to the eye of the world. The</hi> Sermon <hi>is ſuch, almoſt</hi> verbatim, <hi>as my</hi> haſty <hi>and</hi> ſickly <hi>preparations would then allow: Her Lady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips Character I confeſs is much enlarged, that I might ſomewhat more fully, than thoſe ſtreights of time would ſuffer me, propound to the</hi> knowledge <hi>and</hi> imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:41197:3"/>
               <hi>of others;
<note place="margin">Grandes materiasin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genia parva non ſuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent. Et in ipſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> conatu ultra vires auſa ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbunt. quantoque magis fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit quod di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendum, eſt tanto magis obruitur qui magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum verbis non poteſt explicare.</note> that good we had the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to enjoy ſo</hi> long, <hi>and yet</hi> too ſhort <hi>a time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I am conſcious to my ſelf of the great diſproportion betwixt my performance and her merit, for which my Apology is that of</hi> St. Jerome, <hi>weak parts cannot ſuſtain great matters, &amp;c. Yea this is a</hi> Fate <hi>muſt have inevitably attended whoever had been her</hi> Orator <hi>in ſome degree. When I may ſay as truly of her as</hi> Greg. Naz. <hi>of his</hi> Gorgonia, her Prudence and Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty no man living was able to ſet forth, with proportionable language. <hi>And again,</hi> It is exceeding difficult to reach the excellencies of her Virtues either by deed or word, by imitation or encomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um. <hi>And though very many might have</hi> praiſed <hi>her more</hi> floridly, <hi>none could have</hi> repreſented <hi>her more truly, no man living having known her ſo long and ſo intimately as my ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And my</hi> weakneſs <hi>and</hi> plainneſs <hi>may attain this double advantage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Render the</hi> Narration <hi>more</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:41197:4"/>credible,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quaedam ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraxero ne incredibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia videan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp;c.</hi> Hier. <hi>ad</hi> Demet.</note> 
               <hi>which if it had been</hi> dreſſed <hi>up with all the ornaments of which 'twas ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable, would have looked in this Age, more like a</hi> Romance <hi>than an</hi> Hiſtory.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>It will better</hi> ſuit <hi>with the</hi> Original <hi>it</hi> copies, <hi>for as is ſaid of</hi> Sue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius, he wrote the lives of the Roman <hi>Caeſars,</hi> with the ſame liberty they led them. <hi>So I have writ this excellent Ladies life, with the</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Age ad ipſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us laudes accedamus neglecta ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monis ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantia et concinnita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate; nam ne haec quidem quam lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dandam ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepimus laſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu delectata eſt.</hi> Naz.</note> ſame undiſguiſed ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city with which ſhe lived it. <hi>And though never any man had a more</hi> conceſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, conſtant, ſincere Friend, <hi>than ſhe vouchſafed to be to me, yet is not the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony</hi> leſs true, <hi>becauſe of a</hi> Friend; <hi>but the more</hi> ſcrupulouſly exact <hi>for fear of</hi> deſecrating <hi>ſo</hi> ſacred <hi>a</hi> name, <hi>and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending the</hi> Genius <hi>of her, who above all things hated falſhood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I am not the</hi> firſt, <hi>nor ſhall be the</hi> laſt, <hi>whom thoſe (whoſe</hi> charity <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd</hi> good opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion <hi>is not only ſo</hi> wiſe <hi>as to</hi> begin <hi>at home; but alſo ſo</hi> kind <hi>as to</hi> dwell <hi>and</hi> end <hi>there too) will deſpiſe or pity, and bleſs themſelves in the conceit, of what mighty matters they could have done; if this</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince <hi>had fallen to their</hi> ſhare. <hi>It may
<pb facs="tcp:41197:4"/>be little thinking, how ſuch ſorrows as mine juſtly are, would have blunted the</hi> edge <hi>of their keener</hi> Eloquence; <hi>and how unmeet a</hi> Theme <hi>ſo calamitous a</hi> loſs <hi>is, on which to ſhew our wit.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Non opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet ex cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitate ipſa oſtendendi ingenii an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam arripere.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But let ſuch,</hi> for me, <hi>enjoy their hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, I'll ſay no more leſt I awake them, and ſo deprive them of their pleaſant dream.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For</hi> my ſelf, <hi>I have endeavoured to approve my</hi> Conſcience to God: Hic murus aheneus eſto. <hi>And I hope I may</hi> appeal <hi>to your</hi> Honourable Atteſtation, <hi>(whoſe</hi> Teſtimony <hi>will be without and beyond exception) in moſt things I have written of</hi> Your, My,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Marcellant tuam into meam, et ut verius lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quar, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtram. S.</hi> Hier. <hi>ep.</hi> 16.</note> Our <hi>incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable Friend.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And I doubt not but</hi> all <hi>who knew her</hi> Ladyſhip <hi>thorowly, will be able to ſay as the</hi> poor <hi>people are reported to have ſaid after the</hi> Funeral Sermon <hi>of another</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>The Lady</hi> Veer.</note> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent Ornament <hi>of this Country.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They <hi>could have</hi> ſaid <hi>a great deal more of</hi> Her, <hi>than the</hi> Miniſter <hi>did: At the hearing of which our good Lady was much
<pb facs="tcp:41197:5"/>pleaſed, and ſaid;</hi> She ſhould value ſuch a Teſtimony above all others. <hi>The</hi> Poor, <hi>like the</hi> Widows, <hi>which ſtood a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the dead body of</hi> Dorcas; ſhewing the Coats and Garments ſhe made for them,
<note place="margin">Acts. 9.39.</note> whilſt ſhe was with them, <hi>being the moſt unexceptionable witneſſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I confeſs it ſeems both</hi> decent <hi>and</hi> neceſſary <hi>to ſuggeſt ſome Arguments of</hi> Comfort <hi>to them whom I know to be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt with ſo bitter and diſtreſſing a</hi> loſs. <hi>And the undertaking would not (in one reſpect at leaſt) be altogether unſuitable to my ſelf. Becauſe,</hi> Great is that Cordial which is adminiſtred by thoſe who are partakers of the ſame ſorrows.
<note place="margin">Magnum Pharmacum illud eſt, quod abillis qui eodem dolore affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti ſunt por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigitur et qui in ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitate ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantur eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolandis ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamitoſis major eſt Authoritas.</note> And their Authority is greateſt in comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the calamitous, who bear a deep ſhare in the ſame calamity, <hi>as one of the Ancients hath well ſaid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Give me</hi> leave <hi>therefore,</hi> much ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured Madam, Sir, <hi>beſides what you will meet with in the following diſcourſe, to remind you of that great</hi> Panpharmacon. It is the Lord who hath done it, <hi>that</hi> Wiſdom <hi>and</hi> Goodneſs <hi>which commits no</hi> errors, <hi>but doth all things</hi> well <hi>and</hi> wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.
<pb facs="tcp:41197:5"/>
               <hi>And our daily prayers for the</hi> fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of whoſe Will, <hi>obliges, at leaſt, to a</hi> ſubmiſs acquieſcence <hi>when 'tis</hi> done.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And as to her,</hi> She hath finiſhed her courſe triumphantly, and ſhe hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the Crown: She reſts from her labours, and her works do follow her. <hi>She is landed in ſafe</hi> harbour, got off <hi>the rough Seas of ſins and ſorrows.</hi> She is taken from the evil to come, <hi>and ſhall neither</hi> feel <hi>nor</hi> ſee <hi>what our ſins may juſtly make us</hi> fear.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Non moere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus quod talem ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimus ſed gratias a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gimus quod talem habai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus imoha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bemus: Deo</hi> enim <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vunt omnia et quicquid revertitur ad Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliae nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mero com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putatur. Epita.</hi> Paul.</note> 
               <hi>She would not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain with us</hi> as well as ſhe loved us, <hi>let us</hi> long <hi>and</hi> haſten <hi>to be with</hi> Her: <hi>We have uſed to account her happineſs our own, therefore her</hi> bleſſedneſs <hi>cannot make us miſerable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>She is not</hi> loſt, <hi>but</hi> gone before; <hi>and She could not</hi> be <hi>where She is, nor</hi> enjoy <hi>what She</hi> doth; <hi>without being parted from us, till we can</hi> overtake <hi>Her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Be pleaſed alſo to remember that of</hi> St. Jerom, We mourn not becauſe we have loſt ſuch an one, but give thanks that we had ſuch an one, yea have ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:41197:6"/>an one: for all ſuch live to God, and whatever returns to the Lord, is to be accounted in the number of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But I muſt repreſs my ſelf, reflecting how needleſs it is to caſt in my</hi> Mite <hi>into ſuch full</hi> Treaſuries.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I am</hi> conſcious <hi>to my ſelf but of one</hi> offence, <hi>which may make me apprehend your</hi> Frown: <hi>Which is, my adventuring to inſert, without your</hi> leave <hi>or</hi> knowledge <hi>ſome ſhort touches of that</hi> Noble Stock <hi>of which her</hi> Ladyſhip <hi>was ſo conſpicuous and</hi> eminent a branch.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But as I have the</hi> Example <hi>of many</hi> Ancients,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Praecepta ſunt Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ut ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jores ejus, qui lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dandus eſt, et eorum ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta altius repetantur: ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>que ad ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum per gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus ſermo perveniat: qno viz. avitis paternisque virtutibus illuſtrior fiat, et non degeneraſſe a bonis ipſe videatur.</hi> Hier. <hi>de Nepotia.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and almoſt all</hi> Moderns, <hi>who write on ſuch occaſions; ſo would it have been a great</hi> Hiatus <hi>and</hi> indecent defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency <hi>to her Story, to have been wholly</hi> ſilent <hi>in it. And I have been ſo</hi> conciſe <hi>and</hi> cautious, <hi>not to offend the</hi> humble modeſty <hi>of thoſe who yet</hi> ſurvive.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:41197:6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>That when the</hi> laws <hi>of</hi> Order <hi>and</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod <hi>have obtained the allowance</hi> Juſtice <hi>may demand; your</hi> Honours kindneſs <hi>will I hope, (at leaſt for her ſake) ſupply what ſhall be farther needful of</hi> Forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thoſe few of her Ladyſhips pious and excellent Papers, which are inſerted in the diſcourſe, or ſubjoyned to it; (as they juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly may, ſo I hope they) will give Ornament and Luſtre to it, in the Judgment of all ſerious Chriſtians: As richer Trimmings of Gold and Silk uſe to do to Garments made of courſer Materials.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I ſhall not</hi> enlarge <hi>your</hi> trouble <hi>by being</hi> importune <hi>in begging your</hi> Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage: <hi>'Tis</hi> Natural <hi>to</hi> all <hi>to defend their</hi> own; <hi>and ſurely beſides the many</hi> Titles <hi>you had to me before.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now by your</hi> Executorſhip, <hi>you have an</hi> Indefeaſable Right <hi>to me: For no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb facs="tcp:41197:7"/>to which her</hi> Ladyſhips Will <hi>enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles you, was more entirely</hi> Hers, <hi>and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently</hi> your Honours, <hi>than</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Much and Truly Honoured Madam, Sir,</salute>
               <signed>Your Honours Moſt Humbly Devoted and Faithful Obedient Servant <hi>Anthony Walker.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>May 27. 1678.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:41197:7"/>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>PROV. 31.29, 30, 31.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <q>
                        <p>Many daughters have done virtuouſly, but thou excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt them all.</p>
                        <p>Favour is deceitful, and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is vain, but a woman that feareth the Lord, ſhe ſhall be praiſed.</p>
                        <p>Give her of the fruit of her own hands, let her own works praiſe her in the gates.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>THat hard queſtion which <hi>Solomon</hi> propounds in the tenth Verſe of this Chapter, <hi>Who can find a virtuous woman?</hi> I could have anſwered with an <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, more <hi>rapturous</hi> and <hi>quick,</hi> and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41197:8"/>
                     <hi>brisk,</hi> than that of <hi>Archimed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>en he had ſolv'd the poſing Problem; had not her ſudden loſs ſurpriſed and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ballanced the joy of finding her, and ſunk it into a gulf of inexpreſſible grief, which might juſtly ſtrike me dumb with aſtoniſhing amazement, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the deepeſt ſilence,
<note place="margin">Prooem. in Eccl.</note> as S. <hi>Jerome</hi> tells his <hi>Paula</hi> and <hi>Euſtochium,</hi> it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to himſelf, upon the unexpected death of the holy <hi>Blaeſilla.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And this might excuſe our meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and wearing out, this ſolemn ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt hour, not by ſliding <hi>Sands,</hi> but as they uſed of old, by diſtilling drops of <hi>Water,</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> our bittereſt and ſalteſt <hi>Tears,</hi> or rather, if our <hi>Blood</hi> can circulate and flow in ſuch a conſternation, and be not chilled and ſtagnant, with Streams of that, both from our Veins and Hearts. But though the Laws of Nature might indulge ſuch gratifying of our paſſions,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lev.</hi> 10.3. <hi>Aaron</hi> held his peace.</note> as we are Men, the Law of Grace will not allow it, as we are Chriſtians: to whom a ſullen ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence is as much forbidden as a ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive holding of our peace is changed on us.</p>
                  <p>For we muſt not ſorrow,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.14.</note> as Men without hope, for them who leep in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:41197:8"/>Jeſus, as without any heſitance, we may conclude ſhe doth, who lived ſo entirely to him; and it would be too rank a ſelfiſhneſs, and unkind a Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, to rob her, but in our wiſhes, of the enjoyment of God, and the inheritance of Saints in Light, that we might a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain enjoy her kind, obliging,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Col.</hi> 1.12</note> holy converſation, in this vale of Baniſhment and Darkneſs.</p>
                  <p>If therefore, ſhe being dead, yet ſpeaketh, as doubtleſs ſhe doth,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.4.</note> and will do to all that had the honour and happineſs to know her, either to our comfort or conviction; let me force a paſſage through my obſtinate and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pifying ſorrows, and partly be her <hi>Eccho,</hi> partly repreſent her in <hi>ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figie,</hi> that by this innocent and uſeful way, ſhe who is gone to live with God in <hi>Heaven,</hi> may ſtill live with us on <hi>Earth,</hi> in our grateful remembrance of her virtuous perfections, in our ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous practice of her wiſe and holy coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, and in a ready imitation of her exemplary Piety.</p>
                  <p>But becauſe the moſt uſual and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful method of inſtructing, is, by giving rules firſt, and then illuſtrating thoſe rules with appoſite and fit examples,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41197:9"/>which prove them practicable, and poſſible at leaſt, if not eaſie alſo, to be obſerved, I ſhall purſue that order, and give you the <hi>rule</hi> and meaſure, from the <hi>wiſeſt</hi> of Men in his Generation, and the <hi>example</hi> from the beſt of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in her own; the firſt from the Pen of the Royal Preacher, the ſecond from the Hearſe of a noble Lady, both Epithetes which carry grandeur in their ſound, and may awaken, yea, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand attention.</p>
                  <p>The whole Chapter contains a Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue betwixt <hi>Bathſheba</hi> and her Son <hi>Solomon,</hi> under the well diſguiſed name of <hi>Lemuel,</hi> wherein ſhe, after her ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous fall (to ſhew the mighty pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Divine Grace and ſincere Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance) now conſecrated to be a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheteſs,
<note n="*" place="margin">The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy which his Mother taught him.</note> by a divine <hi>afflatus,</hi> inſtructs and catechiſes him in things of greateſt importance, and neareſt concernment, which ſhe performs with a ſtrong <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thos,</hi> and moſt winning inſinuation, and hath the honour to have her pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, holy counſels recorded in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred <hi>Canon.</hi> And this fills up the nine firſt Verſes, and from thence he reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procates, and in a lofty ſtrain appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth and applauds his Mother.</p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:41197:9"/>
                  <p>This latter part preſents us with the <hi>Icon</hi> and <hi>Character</hi> of an excellent and Heroick Woman, which is laid down in two and twenty Verſes, according to the number, and in the order of the Letters of the Hebrew Alphabet; every Letter in due ſequence, beginning a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Verſe,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſalm</hi> 25.34.111.119. <hi>Lament.</hi> and divers other.</note> to intimate there's ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſignal in it, which is compoſed with ſo much art, as we find many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eminent portions of the Holy Scriptures are.</p>
                  <p>Some Interpreters <hi>allegorize</hi> theſe words, and make the Virtuous Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man the Figure of the true Church. Others refer them to the Holy and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Bleſſed Virgin-Mother. Others ſuppoſe them to deſcribe an holy and devout Soul, that conſecrates it ſelf en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely to God in the practice of all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and truly ennobling Virtues. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers will have them to be, by a <hi>Proſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>popoeia,</hi> the Idea of Spiritual Wiſdom, and Heroical Virtue in the Abſtract. But the moſt, and I think the beſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitors, eſteem them the Icon, Idea, Character and Picture of a truly <hi>Wiſe, Religious, Godly, Gracious</hi> Woman, drawn by the Holy Ghoſts own Pencil, in the hand of the moſt exquiſite Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and Artiſt, <hi>Solomon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:41197:10"/>
                  <p>He begins with an inqueſt after her, <hi>Who can find a virtuous Woman?</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying, ſhe's a rare creature, and hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly found, but to encourage your ſearch, he aſſures you, ſhe's worth looking for, her value being ineſtimable, for her price is far above <hi>Pearls</hi> and <hi>Rubies,</hi> and all <hi>Precious Stones.</hi> And then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcends to draw her Pourtraicture and Beauty, with comely and due propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, with bright and orient colours, and ſets her in the moſt advantageous Light, in eighteen Verſes. And final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly crowns her with this Wreath of Laurels, with this golden Coronet, with this Diadem of coſtly Jewels, which make my preſent Text.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Many daughters have done virtuouſly, but thou excelleſt them all.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Favour is deceitful, and beauty is vain, but the woman which feareth the Lord, ſhe ſhall be praiſed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Give her of the fruit of her hands: let her own works praiſe her in the gates.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The words are a Royal Garland, ſet on the Temples of the Virtuous Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, by the hands of <hi>Solomon</hi> and God. I may not give the ſcent of every ſingle Flower, the ſenſe of every ſevera word.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41197:10"/>Such ſolemn trifling would look like fulſome Pedantry, and ill become the mournful gravity of this occaſion.</p>
                  <p>The mixed and compound fragrancy reſulting from the whole, wreathed and bound up together, is this; <hi>That ſolid and true praiſe is only and ſuperlatively due to the ſincerely, godly, and gracious wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, who may claim it by the fruits her virtue hath been pregnant with: or Goodneſs in good earneſt, ſubſtantial Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion which hath fruitful hands, deſerves, and ſhall obtain, an honourable teſtimony both of God and Men.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But as too minute a niceneſs is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manly, and obraids the Auditory, ſo too general a procedure is confuſed and cloudy, acts the Dictator, and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrarily impoſeth both on Text and Hearers, rather than deduceth fairly, and convinceth clearly: I ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore uſe that method which is free from both extremes, taking for grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed what is obvious, and rendring ſo, by additional Light, the reſt which needs it.</p>
                  <p>I may call this Text the Porch to the Temple of Honour, and it hath two Doors, one to ſhut out the bold Intruders, and falſe Pretenders: the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41197:11"/>other to admit the true and rightful claimers. Plainly it ſhews;</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Negatively,</hi> who doth not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Poſitively,</hi> who doth deſerve true praiſe.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Negatively,</hi> no Woman deſerves true praiſe.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. For <hi>Favour.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. For <hi>Beauty.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Poſitively,</hi> every Woman de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves true praiſe.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Who feareth the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Who is fruitful in good works.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, <hi>per remotionem,</hi> negatively, becauſe the Gates of this Temple are thronged with Worſhippers, and Praiſe hath many Candidates and Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries, and many run for this prize, but only one obtains it. I ſhall briefly ſhew how <hi>Solomon</hi> thruſts back, and ſhuts the Door againſt, nonſuits the Plea of moſt Pretenders, under two inſtances, of <hi>Favour</hi> and <hi>Beauty,</hi> and by parity of reaſon ſhocks the bold confidence of all others, who can ſhew no better Charter for their claim: as if he had ſaid, whatſoever is <hi>falſe</hi> and <hi>vain</hi> can produce nothing that is <hi>true</hi> and <hi>laſting:</hi>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:41197:11"/>but Favour is <hi>falſe, deceitful, a lye.</hi> And Beauty is a <hi>vaniſhing,</hi> a <hi>fading, fleeting</hi> thing; therefore all the praiſe you affect, or can obtain by theſe, is like the Seed from whence it ſprings: <hi>falſe</hi> and <hi>deceiving, periſhing</hi> and <hi>vain,</hi> and ſhe who ſows ſuch <hi>wind,</hi> may expect nothing but a crop of <hi>Whirlwind,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 8.7. <hi>Vide Cora. a Lapide in locum.</hi>
                     </note> a blaſting and a cold return.</p>
                  <p>By Favour is meant a comely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, a graceful deportment, a win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning carriage, decent geſture, hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome motions, a ready wit, and good expreſſion, and a decorous converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, made up of all theſe and ſuch like Ingredients, which is moſt taking, and renders Women deſirable and accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and procures Favour in the Eyes and Hearts of Men.</p>
                  <p>By Beauty he underſtands a goodly proportion of members, a juſt Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metry, and due ſituation of parts with the fit mixture of the Roſe and Lilly,
<note place="margin">Pulchritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do eſt Gyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chro in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductum, i. phlegma ſanguine commi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tum pulcbre per pellem pellucens. S. Chryſ.</note> the beſt Varniſh of a clear well co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loured skin, and whatever elſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes an harmonious Air. Or, if you pleaſe, Beauty, whether natural or ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificial, whether the mixture of Blood and Flegm ſhining through a good skin, as S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> defines it, or Ceruſs
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41197:12"/>and Vermilion daubed on, to hide a bad one: whether a Gift wherewith God hath bleſſed them, or a Theft for which God will blaſt them; whether the Benefit of the Author of Nature, or the Artifice of him who delights to diſguiſe and deſtroy his Workman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
                  <p>Both theſe are <hi>vain</hi> and <hi>inconſtant, falſe</hi> and <hi>deceitful, adventitious,</hi> or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal, the <hi>beſt</hi> no effect of our choice, as every thing muſt be which is praiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy.</p>
                  <p>The worſt proceeding from a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and ſinful will, therefore blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, and reproachable, not excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Temporis &amp; morbi ludi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brium. G. Naz. Can.</hi> 1.6.</note> much leſs commendable. Not <hi>Ague-proof,</hi> nor <hi>tenable</hi> againſt the firſt aſſaults of age or ſickneſs, nor dare be looked upon by Wind or Sun.</p>
                  <p>And not only <hi>empty, vain,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of good; but <hi>fallacious</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving,</hi> and full of evils, ſnares and bands, and nets, and great temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.
<note place="margin">Faſtus ineſt pulchris, ſiquiturque ſuperbia formam.</note> Firſt, to the Women themſelves, who have them, or who make them; too often rendring them proud, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainful, wanton, laſcivious, deſpiſers of others, waſters of their time, Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizers of their own reflections in a Glaſs,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41197:12"/>and careleſs, or afraid to behold the image of their impurer Souls in the Cryſtal of God's Law, and more afraid of being ſick, or dying, than of a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Sins or Hells.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, deceiving and deſtroying ſilly Men, through whoſe Livers,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Prov.</hi> 7.23.</note> the ſeats of Luſt, thoſe mortal Darts do ſtrike, which an inviſible Bow ſhoots from their wanton Glances, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witching Smiles and Arts.</p>
                  <p>And by parity of reaſon, the like may be ſaid of all the other periſhing, empty, lying vanities: honours, rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, ſtrength, the wiſdom of the fleſh, and learning meerly humane, which are but adventitious Goods at beſt, and ſeldom make Men <hi>better,</hi> often <hi>worſe. What ſhall I ſay, ſhall I praiſe you for theſe? I praiſe you not:</hi> nor will God ever praiſe you, or reward you for them.</p>
                  <p>Nay, I muſt rather drive ſuch falſe Hucſters for true praiſe, out of the Temple of laſting Honour, with ſuch a Scourge as the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> long ſince prepared for that purpoſe; <hi>Let not the wiſe man glory in wiſdom:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.23.</note> nor the witty woman in her wit. <hi>Let not the ſtrong man glory in his ſtrength:</hi>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:41197:13"/>nor the fair woman glory in her Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. <hi>Let not the rich man glory in his riches:</hi> nor the fine woman glory in her dreſs. Let not the honourable Man glory in his Honour, nor the courted Miſtreſs glory in her Favour. Let not the learned Man glory in his being Natures Secretary; nor the wanton woman in being skilled in the depths of Satan. But let him and her that would <hi>glory, and not be aſhamed, or glory in their ſhame, glory in this that they know the Lord,</hi> and love and fear him in ſincerity and truth. Which brings me to the poſitive part, and is the foundation which <hi>Solomon</hi> lays, whereon to build a <hi>Pyramid</hi> of laſting Fame.</p>
                  <p>Not the <hi>graceful,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pulchritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtima animi ornatum non in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, ſed in moribus pulchritudo ſita eſt. Corn. a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pide ex Chryſ.</note> but the <hi>gracious</hi> woman, not ſhe who <hi>glories in her face,</hi> but ſhe who like the <hi>King's Daughter is all glorious within,</hi> even the woman that <hi>feareth the Lord ſhe ſhall be prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In which poſitive part we have the good Womans <hi>Character,</hi> and <hi>Crown.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. Her <hi>Character,</hi> which hath two parts, for the new creature alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts of Soul and Body, an inſide, and an outſide.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:41197:13"/>1. She <hi>fears the Lord,</hi> there's the Soul of her Virtue, the root of the matter within ground, Grace in the Heart.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. She hath <hi>fruitful hands,</hi> there's the Body of her Virtue, the good Tree above ground, works in her life.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Her <hi>Crown, Praiſe</hi> and <hi>Renown.</hi> Which is,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Promiſed</hi> to her: <hi>She ſhall be praiſed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Commanded</hi> for her: <hi>Give her of the fruit of her hands, let her own works praiſe her in the gates.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Performed</hi> concerning her: <hi>Thou excelleſt them all.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As briefly as may be concerning theſe Particulars: and firſt let us view both <hi>Pages</hi> on which her <hi>Character</hi> is written.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. A woman that <hi>feareth the Lord,</hi> that is, who is ſincerely religious, good in good earneſt. Nothing is more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent or obvious in Scripture than ſuch <hi>Synechdoches,</hi> as put one eminent Grace for all the Chain of Graces. So ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the <hi>Love</hi> of God, ſometimes <hi>Truſt</hi> in God, and moſt commonly the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41197:14"/>
                     <hi>Fear</hi> of God is put for being truly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, or is made the Periphraſis of a godly Man. As in that ſignal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of the New Covenant, <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.38, 39, 40. <hi>They ſhall be my people, and I will be their God, and I will give them one heart, and one way, that they may fear me for ever, for the good of them, and their Children after them. And I will make an everlaſting covenant with them, that I will not turn away from them to do them good, and I will put my fear in their hearts, that they ſhall not depart from me.</hi> Job 1.1. <hi>There was a man in the land of Uz, whoſe name was Job, and that man was perfect and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, one that feared God, and eſchew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed evil:</hi> ſo <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. <hi>Haſt thou conſidered my ſervant Job, that there is none like him in the earth, a perfect and an up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right man, one that feareth God, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcheweth evil.</hi> verſ. 9. <hi>Doth Job fear God for nought?</hi> Eccl. 12.13. <hi>Fear. God,</hi> and keep his Commandments, that is the whole of Man: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.4. He ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noureth them that <hi>fear the Lord;</hi> where the godly Man is under this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination of one that <hi>feareth the Lord,</hi> oppoſed to the wicked, called there a vile perſon. 'Tis alſo an infallible ſign
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:41197:14"/>of the preſence of all other Graces, in the exerciſe of which true Godlineſs conſiſts; for as the <hi>Law</hi> is copulative, ſo are the <hi>Graces</hi> by which we obey it, and as where the <hi>Soul</hi> is diſcovering it ſelf by one vital act, all its faculties and powers are; ſo where the <hi>Spirit</hi> of God is working one Grace in truth, the Spirit of all Grace is, for the <hi>Spirit</hi> can no more be without its <hi>Graces,</hi> than the <hi>Soul</hi> without its <hi>Faculties:</hi> yea, the fear of God contains all Graces in it, therefore when <hi>Abraham</hi> offered up his Son <hi>Iſaac,</hi> which was a mighty act of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Love:</hi> God ſaith, <hi>Now I know thou feareſt me,</hi> Gen. 22.12. And as 'tis ſo frequent, it would be <hi>endleſs</hi> to cite all, ſo 'tis ſo obvious, 'tis need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs to cite more.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The other <hi>Page</hi> hath this Inſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Fruitful hands:</hi> the good Woman is like <hi>Dorcas full of good works.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Hands,</hi> two Hands to hold the two Tables of the Law,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Deut.</hi> 9.15.</note> as <hi>Moſes</hi> came down from the Mount with the two Tables in his <hi>two hands,</hi> in each <hi>hand</hi> one, neither empty nor idle.</p>
                  <p>The firſt in the <hi>Right Hand,</hi> there's Religion towards God. The ſecond Table in the <hi>Left Hand,</hi> there's Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41197:15"/>and Charity towards Men.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Theſe Hands bear <hi>Fruit,</hi> good works ſpring, and grow naturally, freely, ſeaſonably, eaſily, maturely as <hi>fruits</hi> from a prolifique Tree, planted in a good ſoil, and by the Waters ſide, as the godly Man is deſcribed in the firſt Pſalm: called <hi>Fruits</hi> of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>Fruits</hi> of the Spirit, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. where S. <hi>Paul</hi> hath a ſignal <hi>Antitheſis</hi> betwixt <hi>Graces</hi> and <hi>Vices,</hi> calling the firſt <hi>Fruits,</hi> the other <hi>Works;</hi> the <hi>Works</hi> of the Fleſh: <hi>verſ.</hi> 19. There's ſervile drudgery in them: <hi>Fruits</hi> of the Spirit: <hi>verſ.</hi> 22. There's a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al eaſineſs in the production of them by the new Nature.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. They are <hi>Fruits,</hi> in the <hi>plural,</hi> for variety of kinds, for number in every kind. Firſt, various acts of Devotion, <hi>Prayers, Prayſes, Reading, Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Meditation, Conference, Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, Communicating,</hi> and all theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iterated, the Morning and the Evening Sacrifice, the weekly Sabbaths, ſolemn Faſts and Feſtivals, ſecret, private, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Devotions, Morning, Evening, and at Noon day:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.</note> yea, at Midnight, ſeven times a day: yea, in a ſober ſenſe, all the day long, nay, all day, and all night
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:41197:15"/>too, as it is teſtified of <hi>Anna,</hi> Luk. 2.37. <hi>That ſhe departed not from the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but ſerved God with faſting and prayers night and day.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ</hi> 5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.12.</note> Pray without ceaſing, continuing inſtant in prayer, giving thanks continually, and in all things.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And the <hi>Left Hand,</hi> though it grow on another <hi>Arm,</hi> draws Sap and Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue from the ſame <hi>Tree</hi> and <hi>Root,</hi> to make it fruitful in variety and multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Acts of <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. Of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> thinking, ſpeaking no evil of any Man, but dealing honeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with all Men, Superiors, Equals, Inferiours, in all <hi>natural, moral, civil</hi> Actions, in all concernments of <hi>Body, Goods</hi> and <hi>Name, wronging no Man, defrauding no Man, but doing to others as they would others ſhould do to them;</hi> and obſerving this rule conſtantly, and in all occaſions and occurrences, and ſo <hi>doing righteouſneſs at all times.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. In <hi>Charity,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.</note> relieving the diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, feeding the hungry, cloathing the naked, viſiting the afflicted by ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, priſon, or any other preſſures, inſtructing the ignorant, comforting the feeble-minded, and ſupporting
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:41197:16"/>them who are caſt down under any temptation,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.6.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> and this not once or twice, or to <hi>one</hi> or <hi>two,</hi> but ſowing this ſeed in the <hi>Morning,</hi> and not withholding in the <hi>Evening, giving this portion to ſeven, and alſo to eight, caſting Bread upon the waters,</hi> yea, <hi>ſcattering by all wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</hi> This briefly of the good Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans character.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Her <hi>Crown, Praiſe:</hi> Praiſe is the ſhadow which attends the Body of Virtue. The <hi>Eccho</hi> which ſounds an honorary Teſtimony.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. From the <hi>Conſciences</hi> of all Men, even thoſe who will not practiſe it themſelves, cannot but approve it and applaud it in them that do; <hi>if there be any virtue, if there be any praiſe,</hi> the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> nay, the <hi>Conſciences</hi> of the very <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> hath annexed them ſo cloſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<note place="margin">Se Judice nemo nocens abſolvitur.</note> they cannot be parted: for as no vicious and guilty perſon can be abſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, though he were to be his own Judge: ſo no virtuous perſon can be condemned,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.</note> though to be judged by his Enemies. <hi>That law written in the heart</hi> cannot but approve the Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript, and Counter-part, and Copy of it ſelf where ere it meets it.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:41197:16"/>2. From the <hi>Mouths</hi> of all good Men, and thoſe eſpecially who have found and felt its beneficial influence.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Beloved, thou doſt faithfully whatever thou doſt to the Brethren,
<note place="margin">3 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.6.</note> and to Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,</hi> which have born witneſs of thy <hi>Charity</hi> before the <hi>Church:</hi> S. <hi>Paul</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven boaſted of the <hi>forward zeal</hi> of them of <hi>Achaia,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.12, 13. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.3</note> and God was <hi>glorified</hi> for their <hi>liberal diſtribution</hi> to all Men. And of the <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>Macedonia</hi> he bears record, <hi>That to their power, yea, and beyond their power</hi> they were willing of themſelves.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Job</hi> 31.20.</note> 
                     <hi>The Loyns of the poor bleſſed</hi> Job <hi>who were warmed by the ſleece of his Sheep: Her children riſe up and call her bleſſed, for</hi> the care of their ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and pious education, and <hi>her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band for</hi> her chaſte converſation and faithful induſtry, of which he is not only a witneſs, but reaps the benefit of it, and for thoſe <hi>he praiſeth her.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. From the whole Chorus of the Heavenly <hi>Hierarchy,</hi> the Angels <hi>Joy</hi> in Heaven, is the moſt <hi>landative accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> to her Virtues.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. From God and Chriſt, whoſe <hi>Euge, Well done, good and faithful ſervants,</hi> whoſe, <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my Father,</hi> whoſe teſtimony, <hi>I was hungry,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.</note>
                        <pb n="20" facs="tcp:41197:17"/>and ye fed me; naked, and ye cloathed me;</hi> is the higheſt praiſe imaginable, or poſſible.</p>
                  <p>Now this praiſe is firſt <hi>promiſed, She ſhall be praiſed:</hi> God leaves us not without encouragements to make us good. Promiſes and Threats, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards and Puniſhments, are the great inſtruments of Government, both with God and Men; and all Rewards include Praiſe, and are the <hi>ſilent,</hi> yet the <hi>loudeſt</hi> commendations.</p>
                  <p>A Crown of Righteouſneſs,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.7, 8.</note> and Life, is provided, and fore-promiſed, to them that fight the good Fight, that keep the Faith, that are faithful unto death. Great and precious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.7.</note> that <hi>God will receive us, be our Father and our God,</hi> to provoke us to <hi>cleanſe our ſelves from all filthineſs of fleſh and ſpirit, and perfect holineſs in the fear of God.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi>
                     </note> An Inheritance <hi>incorruptible, undefiled,</hi> and that <hi>fadeth not away, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in Heaven: Rivers of pleaſure, fulneſs of joy, an eternal Kingdom, and everlaſting life.</hi> And in the Letter, the higheſt praiſe,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.28.</note> for he that is <hi>cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed in heart and ſpirit,</hi> that is a Chriſtian within, <hi>his praiſe ſhall be of God,</hi> and he is approved indeed whom
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:41197:17"/>
                     <hi>God commendeth;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſ.</hi> 11.26.</note> and we have God's word for it, that <hi>the righteous ſhall be in everlaſting remembrance.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. 'Tis commanded and given in charge concerning her to others. <hi>Give her of the fruit of her hands; let her works praiſe her in the Gates.</hi> Let them be ſpoken of and mentioned to her honour in the Aſſemblies of the great Men, and in the concourſe of the people, which uſe to be moſt fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent in the Gates; God gives not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>leave,</hi> but <hi>charge;</hi> and 'tis not only an allowable <hi>courteſie,</hi> but a juſt <hi>debt</hi> and <hi>tribute</hi> due to virtuous perſons, to declare and celebrate their famous Acts. 'Tis an Apoſtolical precept to the <hi>Philippians</hi> concerning <hi>Epaphrodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> who for the work of Chriſt was near unto death; <hi>hold him,</hi> and not him only, but ſuch as he, <hi>in reputation.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.29.</note> Yea, our Lord himſelf concerning <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> who anointed him, and wrought a good work upon him:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.13.</note> 
                     <hi>Praedicendo prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepit, Verily, I ſay unto you, whereſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver this Goſpel ſhall be preached in the whole world, there ſhall alſo this that this woman hath done be told, for a memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial of her.</hi> And God will have the Virtues and the Victories of his Saints
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:41197:18"/>recorded, <hi>to provoke our imitation of them, and encourage our weakneſs to war againſt vice,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Gregory.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. It's <hi>performed</hi> concerning her, <hi>thou excelleſt them all;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.12.</note> we ſhould la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to excel in <hi>Duty. Seek that you may excel. What do you more than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers?</hi> See that ye abound more and more, <hi>ſo run,</hi> out-run others, <hi>that ye may obtain;</hi> and praiſe ſhall be propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable: <hi>Thou excelleſt them all.</hi> We find ſuch Encomiums frequent in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture. Thus of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> 2 King. 18.5. <hi>He truſted in the Lord God of Iſrael, ſo that after him was none like him of all the kings of Iſrael, nor any that was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him,</hi> that is, for ſtrength of Faith. So of <hi>Joſiah,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 23.25. <hi>And like unto him there was no king before him, that turned to the Lord with all his heart, and with all his ſoul, and with all his might, according to the Law of Moſes, neither after him aroſe any like him.</hi> So God's teſtimony of <hi>Job,</hi> Job 1.8. is, <hi>That there was not a Man like him in all the earth.</hi> So S. <hi>Paul</hi> teſtifies of <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,</hi> Phil. 2.20. <hi>I have no man like minded, who will naturally care for your eſtate.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:41197:18"/>
                  <p>Thus have I lightly ſhaken the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Branches of this goodly Tree: and the ripe and pleaſant Fruit which is fallen from them all, I ſhall pick up and ſerve in one Diſh. <hi>To be ſincerely religious, to be a vertuous, gracious, god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly woman is the higheſt accompliſhment, and deſerves the greateſt praiſe:</hi> nay, 'tis the moſt honourable teſtimony can be given to any, to ſay of her in truth, ſhe was <hi>godly, and feared the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There ſeems to be a great agreement and likeneſs betwixt the hundred and forty fourth Pſalm, in point of <hi>happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and this Chapter in matter of <hi>Duty;</hi> and <hi>Praiſe</hi> reſulting from it. And therefore the tranſcribing thoſe words, may give much light and illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration to what lies before us. <hi>David</hi> therefore to ſhew, <hi>populum quae faciunt beatiorem, What will make a people happy,</hi> proceeds thus, <hi>v.</hi> 12. <hi>That our ſons may be as plants grown up in their youth, that our daughters may be as corner ſtones, poliſhed after the ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of a palace.</hi> Verſ. 13. <hi>That our garners may be full, affording all manner of ſtore, that our Sheep may bring forth thouſands and ten thouſands in our
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:41197:19"/>Streets.</hi> Verſ. 14. <hi>That our oxen may be ſtrong to labour, that there be no breaking in, nor going out, that there be no complaining in our Streets.</hi> Verſ. 15. <hi>Happy is that people that is in ſuch a caſe.</hi> Every one will be ready to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and admire the happineſs of ſuch a People. But ſaith <hi>David,</hi> I'll tell you who are infinitely and more truly <hi>happy,</hi> yea, who are only ſo indeed; <hi>yea, happy is that people whoſe God is the Lord.</hi> So <hi>Solomon</hi> in this Chapter, to deſcribe the Woman who deſerveth praiſe, ſhe that is ſo good a <hi>wife, that the heart of her Husband doth ſafely truſt in her, that will do him good, and not evil all the days of his life,</hi> that is a Crown to him, and renders him ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable <hi>in the gates.</hi> She that is ſo good an <hi>Houſwife,</hi> that ſhe <hi>worketh wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly with her hands, ſtays at home, ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth early, is induſtrious, planteth, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſeth, increaſeth her eſtate, ſhe that is ſo good a Mother, as to educate her children well, and ſo good a Miſtreſs as to provide moſt carefully for all her ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, that they are ſo far from wanting cloaths, that their Liveries are Scarlet.</hi> She <hi>that is ſo good a</hi> Neighbour that ſhe <hi>treats</hi> the rich, and <hi>relieves</hi> the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:41197:19"/>poor and needy,
<note place="margin">Super omni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> a vultus ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſere boni.</note> and obliges all by the law of kindneſs in her tongue, ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all by kindeſt words, and kinder looks. This Woman certainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves to be admired; yea, is almoſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dored as a <hi>terreſtrial Goddeſs.</hi> But after all this, ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> yet ſhew I you a more excellent way to obtain true and laſting praiſe; the godly Woman, the Woman that <hi>feareth the Lord, ſhe, ſhe</hi> deſerves to be praiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all others.</p>
                  <p>Moſt Men and Women affect to be praiſed, but 'tis for the moſt part for vain and deceitful things, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve no praiſe at all; and if they at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain any, 'tis a poor and empty praiſe which may ſound and make a noiſe in the world, amongſt the fooliſh <hi>heard,</hi> but ſignifies little with wiſe Men, and nothing at all with God, who deſigns <hi>Glory</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> for none but thoſe who ſeek it by <hi>patient continuance in well doing, and working good,</hi> Rom. 2.7, 10. But to <hi>fear the Lord,</hi> that is, to be godly, this deſerves <hi>praiſe</hi> indeed. A truth ſo evident, and clear by its own light, 'tis hard to add any thing to it for proof or illuſtration, to make it clearer, nature hath printed it in our
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:41197:20"/>hearts, and the <hi>new nature</hi> in a ſecond and fairer edition, as a common prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple. And firſt notions are indemon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrable.</p>
                  <p>To praiſe is to bear witneſs, or give an honourable teſtimony, of a Man or Womans having ſuch a Virtue, Grace, Perfection, Excellency in them, and the very acknowledging and teſtifying that they have them, is a praiſing of them highly: as <hi>Acts</hi> 11.24. <hi>Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas</hi> is abundantly praiſed, in that teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony that he was <hi>a good man, full of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and of <hi>faith,</hi> without adding other encomiaſtick Words. So when God himſelf vouchſafes to write <hi>Job</hi>'s Panegyrick, <hi>Job</hi> 1.1. he calls him his <hi>ſervant, a perfect and an upright man, one that feareth God, and eſcheweth evil.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Acts</hi> 13.22.</note> And S. <hi>Paul</hi> expreſly ſaith, that God gave teſtimony to <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> when he ſaid of him, <hi>I have found David a man after mine own heart, who ſhall fulfil my will.</hi> For as we ſay for <hi>reproach,</hi> call a man ungrateful, and you can ſay no worſe, you have ſtigmatized him with the fouleſt brand. So for <hi>Praiſe,</hi> call a Woman Godly, you need ſay no more, there's praiſe enough in that. So that if you
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:41197:20"/>confine me ſtrictly, I muſt ſtick in the Center, and draw no lines from it, but all will return upon it ſelf, and be the <hi>Epha</hi> never ſo full, it will ſettle upon its own Baſe: I may ſay <hi>aliud,</hi> but not <hi>amplius,</hi> none can be commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed highlyer, than to have this Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter impreſt, <hi>they fear the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Again if I ſhould compare <hi>the fear of the Lord</hi> with other things to give it its due preference, or let my ſelf looſe into an enumeration of its cauſes, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties, effects, ſigns, conſequents, advantages, and unſeaſonably com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-place upon it, I ſhould lanch into an Ocean, in which I ſhould loſe my ſelf and your patience, and deſpair to kenn a ſhore in more than an hours ſail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: I ſhall therefore confine my ſelf, or rather willingly ſubmit to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined by the ſtraits of time, to very narrow meaſures, which ſhall be theſe two:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. To point in general at the objects of <hi>Praiſe,</hi> and ſhew what intereſt <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> or <hi>the Fear of God</hi> hath in them.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. To ſhew what uſually acquires praiſe to men, in reference to <hi>God,</hi> their <hi>Neighbours</hi> and <hi>themſelves,</hi> and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:41197:21"/>declare how being ſincerely religious, will intitle us to it on thoſe Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. As to the Objects of true Praiſe. 'The firſt and grand object of <hi>Praiſe</hi> is <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>divine perfections,</hi> which is ſo evident through all the Scriptures, and to the light of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that I'll not waſte time to prove it; and conſequently, what is next to them, and likeſt to them, is the <hi>next,</hi> and <hi>firſt</hi> in the order of the <hi>ſecondary objects of Praiſe.</hi> Now that is the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God reflected and imprinted on the Soul of Man; and this, Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and the Fear of God produceth: <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.24. <hi>The new man is created after God's image in righteouſneſs and true ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs:</hi> And <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 3.10. <hi>The new man is renewed in knowledge after the image of him that created him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And they that ſincerely embrace the great and precious promiſes of the Goſpel, are thereby made <hi>partakers of the divine nature: A God-like temper and diſpoſition.</hi> For <hi>Godlineſs</hi> is <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likeneſs.</hi> Therefore 'tis enjoyned in ſuch language, <hi>Be ye holy, for I am ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly:</hi> or, <hi>as I am holy,</hi> ſaith the Lord.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:41197:21"/>1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.16. and <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.36. <hi>Be ye merciful as your Father is merciful;</hi> and <hi>be ye perfect as your heavenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is perfect,</hi> Matth. 5.48. They therefore that approach ſo near the moſt praiſe-worthy object, deſerve great praiſe.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The object of <hi>Praiſe</hi> is ſome <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent good,</hi> it muſt be <hi>good,</hi> or it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves reproach; but it muſt be alſo <hi>excellent,</hi> or no notice is taken of it. Now <hi>the fear of God is excellent,</hi> Pſal. 19. The Saints are the <hi>excellent</hi> of the earth; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.3. <hi>The righteous is more excellent than his Neighbour,</hi> Prov. 12.26. <hi>Wiſdom excelleth folly, as light excelleth darkneſs,</hi> Eccleſ. 2.13. <hi>And the things of God's law, wherein good men exerciſe themſelves, are ſaid to be more excellent,</hi> Rom. 2.18. The <hi>godly</hi> therefore are to be praiſed, for they are excellent.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. It muſt be a <hi>choſen good,</hi> for it would be no praiſe for any Man (if that were poſſible) to be good without, or againſt his will. <hi>If I do this thing willingly I have a reward:</hi> 1 Cor. 9.17. Now this good woman <hi>chuſeth. Mary
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:41197:22"/>hath choſen the good part:</hi> Luk. 10.42. (And ſo did our honourable <hi>Mary,</hi> if ever any) and it is implyed in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach caſt upon Sinners: <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.29. <hi>That they did not chuſe the fear of the Lord:</hi> that the Saints do chuſe it: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.30. <hi>I have choſen the way of truth, thy judgments have I laid before me:</hi> and <hi>verſ.</hi> 137. <hi>I have choſen thy precepts.</hi> Iſa. 56.4. <hi>The eunuchs which chuſe the things which pleaſe me.</hi> And it's the high commendation of <hi>Moſes, Heb.</hi> 11.25, 26. <hi>That he choſe to ſuffer affliction with the people of God, rather than to enjoy the pleaſures of ſin for a ſeaſon, and eſteemed the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of Chriſt, greater riches than the treaſures of</hi> Aegypt.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. It muſt be ſome permanent and abiding good, not fading, not <hi>like the morning cloud and early dew:</hi> now the <hi>fear of the Lord endureth for ever:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.9.</note> and where it is in truth it will both <hi>conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue</hi> and <hi>grow. The righteous is an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting foundation:</hi> Prov. 10.25. <hi>The good part they chuſe ſhall not be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>They repent not of their repentance, and Chriſt hath <hi>prayed that their faith fail not.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:41197:22"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They go from ſtrength to ſtrength till they appear before God perfect in Zion, and bring forth more fruit in their age.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The path way of the juſt is as the ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning light:
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pov.</hi> 4.18.</note> which ſhineth more unto the perfect day.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. I ſhall conſider the object of <hi>Praiſe</hi> more ſpecially, and what men are eſteemed to merit praiſe for, with reſpect to <hi>God,</hi> their <hi>Neighbours</hi> and <hi>themſelves.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. Men are <hi>praiſed</hi> for their well performing of their duty to God, as <hi>good ſervants.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. For their <hi>Beneficence</hi> to men in all relations, as uſeful, juſt, kind, chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table amongſt and towards all men.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. For their <hi>wiſdom</hi> to themſelves, as being prudent, diſcreet, and wiſe in their own concerns.</p>
                  <p>Now <hi>Religion,</hi> the <hi>Fear of the Lord,</hi> is productive of all theſe in an eminent degree; and therefore are they greatly to be praiſed in whom it is.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:41197:23"/>1. This <hi>fear</hi> will make <hi>good ſervants to God.</hi> This is a principal part of a ſervants duty. <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.6. <hi>If I be a Maſter where is my fear?</hi> Now this fear is the root of univerſal obedience: he that fears God will not, dare not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend him: <hi>Fear God and keep his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, this is the whole duty of man:</hi> Eccleſ. 12.13. Only <hi>fear the Lord, and ſerve him;</hi> if you fear him, you will not fail to ſerve him. <hi>What doth the Lord require of thee,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.12.</note> but to fear him, and to ſerve the Lord thy God with all thy heart and ſoul: ſerve the Lord with fear,</hi> Pſal. 2. <hi>Let us have grace whereby we may ſerve God accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly with reverence and godly fear:</hi> Heb. 12.28. Yea, the <hi>fear</hi> of God will help to clean from all filthineſs both of fleſh and ſpirit, and to perfect holineſs: 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1. So that if it be praiſe-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be <hi>a dutiful child</hi> and <hi>obedient ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant</hi> to God, as certainly nothing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves it better; the woman that <hi>fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Lord</hi> hath a juſt claim to <hi>Praiſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>The fear of the Lord</hi> will make fruitful in all good offices to our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, humble and obedient to Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, careful of, and tender to Inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:41197:23"/>juſt and kind to all, and muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent and liberal to thoſe that are in want. This good woman in the Text, <hi>who feareth the Lord in her heart, had fruitful hands, and works of her own to praiſe her in the gates.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>'Tis the excellency of Religion to make good in all relations. <hi>Good Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates,</hi> 'tis the firſt qualification of <hi>Jethro</hi>'s Juſtice: <hi>Able men that fear God:</hi> Exod. 18.21.</p>
                  <p>So <hi>Nehemiah</hi> of himſelf, <hi>Neh.</hi> 5.15. <hi>The former Governours which were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me, had been chargeable to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and had taken of them bread, and wine, and forty ſhekels of ſilver, yea, even their ſervants had rule over the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but ſo did not I becauſe of the fear of God,</hi> and good Subjects: <hi>Fear thou the Lord, and the King;</hi> Prov. 24.21. <hi>Fear God, and honour the King:</hi> 1 Pet. 2.17. One will enforce the other, and will make <hi>ſubject for conſcience ſake: Rom.</hi> 13.5.</p>
                  <p>It will make loving and <hi>good Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands,</hi> and it will make <hi>good</hi> and <hi>obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Wives,</hi> like <hi>Sarah;</hi> for <hi>holy women who truſt in God are in ſubjection to their own husbands:</hi> 1 Pet. 3. And this made this Virtuous Woman ſo excellent a
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:41197:24"/>Wife. It will make good Family-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, <hi>who will walk in their houſe with a perfect heart,</hi> and will neither provoke their Children, nor deny what's equal to their ſervants, whilſt they remember themſelves have a <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and <hi>a Maſter in heaven;</hi> Col. 4.1. It will make dutiful children, and faithful ſervants. <hi>Servants obey in all things your Maſters according to the fleſh, not with eye-ſervice, as men pleaſers, but in ſingleneſs of heart, fearing God:</hi> Col. 3.22. In a word, it will make honeſt and righteous in our whole con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation: <hi>S. Peter</hi> puts together <hi>Acts</hi> 10.35. <hi>Fearing God and working righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It renders alſo <hi>charitable</hi> and <hi>bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> to them in need; this good Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>verſ.</hi> 20. <hi>Stretcheth out her hands to the poor; yea, ſhe reacheth out her hands to the needy. The good man is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver merciful, and lendeth; yea, liberal, and giveth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cornelius</hi> is deſcribed, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.1. <hi>A devout man that feared God, and gave much alms to the people;</hi> and S. <hi>James</hi> tells us, that <hi>true Religion and undefiled is to viſit the fatherleſs, and widows in their affliction, that is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:41197:24"/>
                  <p>So that if to be good in all relations, and to be a Benefactor and common good to mankind, deſerves <hi>praiſe,</hi> the <hi>fear of God</hi> deſerves it, which makes men ſuch.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly and laſtly, the fear of the Lord will make a man <hi>wiſe</hi> for himſelf, to do himſelf good: <hi>And men will praiſe thee when thou doſt well to thy ſelf;</hi> Pſal. 49.18. And nothing is more praiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy in <hi>man's</hi> account, than to be <hi>wiſe,</hi> nor in the account of <hi>God,</hi> than to be <hi>wiſe to ſalvation.</hi> Now the <hi>fear of the Lord</hi> not only makes wiſe, but is wiſdom it ſelf.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The fear of the Lord, that is wiſdom, and to depart from evil is underſtanding:</hi> Job 28.28.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Godlineſs</hi> are ſynony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous words in the Holy Ghoſt's Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, the wiſe man is the good man, (<hi>wiſe virgins,</hi> Matth. 25.) and the <hi>wicked</hi> man the <hi>fool.</hi> The <hi>fear of the Lord is the beginning of wiſdom;</hi> the head, the chief of wiſdom; <hi>a good un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding have all they that keep his commandments.</hi> The <hi>praiſe</hi> of every one of them who do ſo <hi>endureth for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver:</hi> Pſal. 111, <hi>ult.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:41197:25"/>
                  <p>I am loth, notwithſtanding the ſtraits of time, to diſmiſs this great truth without ſome ſhort improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, let me therefore take advantage from the deſire of fame and praiſe, which nature hath planted in us all.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. To reprove the blindneſs and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of Men who will not ſee, or ſeeing, not purſue the only true and ſafe, and ſure method of attaining it, by la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring to be <hi>ſoundly</hi> and <hi>ſincerely god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> but build upon the ſand, that hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, ſinking ground, which will not bear this triumphal Arch, this Royal Pillar; their natural, fortuitous, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired accompliſhments, their <hi>ſtrength, beauty, riches, honour, fleſhly wiſdom,</hi> all which are periſhing and vain, falſe and deceiving, and will crown them at laſt but with fading flowers, and wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering garlands, with the praiſe of fooliſh men, like themſelves; never with that praiſe which comes from God: for <hi>the Lord taketh no pleaſure in the legs of a man,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.10.</note> nor in the face of a woman:</hi> in the ſtrength of the one, nor in the beauty of the other; but the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:41197:25"/>Lord taketh pleaſure in them that fear him, and hope in his mercy. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you therefore, and adjure you by all the obligations of <hi>duty</hi> to God, and <hi>wiſdom</hi> for your ſelves, devote your ſelves to the <hi>fear of God</hi> entirely. Reſolve to be <hi>good in very good earneſt;</hi> to be Chriſtians indeed, and Chriſtians within, <hi>circumciſed in heart and ſpirit,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.28.</note> that your praiſe may be of God,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.7.</note> and not of men: and found in the faith, that it may be found to praiſe, and honour, and glory, at the appearance of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>And to encourage you, lift up your eyes, beſtow one ſteddy, wiſhful glance upon the goodly fruit, with which this tree of life is loaden, of which, whoever eats ſhall never die, but live for ever.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. All your ſins ſhall be <hi>pardoned,</hi> you ſhall have peace with <hi>God,</hi> with <hi>conſcience,</hi> and with all the <hi>creatures;</hi> acceptance of your perſons, and of all your ſervices.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. You ſhall be freed from the <hi>pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> the <hi>filth,</hi> and the <hi>deceitfulneſs</hi> of ſin,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:41197:26"/>the vaſſalage of Satan, the ſting of death, and from the pit, and fear of Hell.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Your Souls ſhall be repaired to their original perfections and excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies in the Image of God, and partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of the Divine Life.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. You ſhall be <hi>ingrafted</hi> into Chriſt, adopted into the Family of God, made <hi>temples of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> with all the Bleſſings which are conſequent on theſe.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. You ſhall be <hi>heirs of all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes;</hi> yea, <hi>inherit all things:</hi> have all your wants ſupplied, all juſt deſires ſatisfied, all conditions ſanctified, all providences bleſſed, to promote your everlaſting good.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, you ſhall be crowned with the unwithering Laurels of true, and of eternal praiſes, by Men, by Angels, and by Chriſt, and God; and when you <hi>die</hi> in <hi>nature,</hi> begin to <hi>live</hi> in <hi>glory;</hi> go to God and ſee his face, and be for ever with him, in <hi>whoſe preſence is ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of joy, and at whoſe right hand are pleaſures for ever more.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:41197:26"/>
                  <p>And for further quickening and ſtrengthning you againſt the difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which may ſeem to meet you, and to obſtruct you in this excellent way. Let me ſet before you the examples of the Saints of God, who, though men of like paſſions with your ſelves, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly clogged with the ſame corrupt and ſinful nature, outwardly beſet with the like or ſame temptations, caſt off the weight which hung upon them, broke through the difficulties which did encompaſs them, and ran the race which was ſet before them, and through faith and patience obtained, and now inherit the promiſes, and that ſure reward, that Diadem of Joy, and Praiſe, which God hath provided, and Chriſt hath purchaſed for, and promiſed to them that <hi>love and fear him, and wait for his appearance.</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect on all the Worthies of the Old Teſtament, and New, the holy <hi>Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs, Prophets</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> the noble <hi>Army of Martyrs,</hi> all the primitive Chriſtians, whoſe names are recorded in the Church's Story, all the devout men and women of ſucceeding ages; and follow that <hi>Cloud of Witneſſes,</hi> as <hi>Iſrael</hi> followed that <hi>Pillar of Cloud</hi> and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:41197:27"/>
                     <hi>Fire,</hi> through the wilderneſs till they arriv'd at <hi>Canaan.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And that you may not doubt, or fear that <hi>God's Arm is ſhortened,</hi> or <hi>his hand grown weak,</hi> his Bowels ſtraitned, or the aids of his Grace leſs <hi>powerful, ſufficient,</hi> yea, <hi>exuberant</hi> than they were of old.</p>
                  <p>Let me ſet before you an <hi>illuſtrious,</hi> an <hi>Heroick,</hi> a <hi>recent</hi> inſtance, freſh in your memories, known to you all, a Preſident, as much beyond exception, as example, which may ſilence all your cavils of <hi>difficulty,</hi> and much more of <hi>impoſſibility.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I mean the <hi>thrice honourable, and truly noble, the moſt excellent and incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable Lady,</hi> the ſacred Shrine of whoſe venerable Herſe we are now drenching with the juſt tribute of our floods of tears, and ſtrewing with the ſweeteſt Flowers of Applauſe and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, though they as much too <hi>few,</hi> as theſe too <hi>pale</hi> and <hi>faint</hi> for ſuch an offering.</p>
                  <p>She was a <hi>Woman,</hi> of <hi>the feebler Sex, a ſinful daughter</hi> of firſt ſinning <hi>Eve, a rich woman,</hi> and <hi>how hardly can ſuch be ſaved?</hi> That had as much <hi>buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:41197:27"/>to divert her, and as much <hi>plenty</hi> to entertain her, as much <hi>beauty</hi> to tempt her, and as much <hi>favour</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangle her, as any of you, and lived in the ſame atheiſtical, degenerate age with your ſelves, wherein ſincere and ſerious Religion is made the greateſt <hi>Ridicule,</hi> eſteemed the moſt unmodiſh and unfaſhionable thing.</p>
                  <p>And yet in the midſt of all theſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantages, I may without <hi>Hyperbole</hi> invite you, as the Cryer us'd to call Spectators to the ſecular Plays: Come ſee thoſe Shews, <hi>Quos nemo mortalium vidit, vel viſurus eſt, Come ſee, come hear</hi> ſuch an example of <hi>Heroick Virtue,</hi> of <hi>Generous Piety,</hi> of <hi>ſincere, humble, unaffected, ſerious, fruitful Religion,</hi> as in all reſpects this age hath not produced, as hath had rare, if any Preſidents to follow, and will I fear be followed by few, or none, but with long diſtant in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervals.</p>
                  <p>An <hi>hundred</hi> Mouths and a <hi>thouſand</hi> Tongues,
<note place="margin">Si mihi ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> centum lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guae, ſint oraque cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</note> though they all flowed with <hi>Nectar,</hi> would be too few to praiſe her. O for a <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>'s Mouth, for an <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel</hi>'s Tongue to deſcribe this terreſtrial Seraphim; or a ray of <hi>light</hi> condens'd into a <hi>pencil,</hi> and made <hi>tactile</hi> to give
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:41197:28"/>you this glorious <hi>child of light</hi> in <hi>vive Effigie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But what great Maſters can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in <hi>minature?</hi> what skillful hand <hi>epitomize</hi> ſo great a ſoul, and draw her in <hi>little</hi> (on ſo few remaining Sands) who had nothing <hi>little,</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing <hi>mean,</hi> but a <hi>little eſteem</hi> of her own <hi>perfections,</hi> and being <hi>mean</hi> in her own eyes.</p>
                  <p>For ſhe was truly excellent, and great in all reſpects: <hi>great</hi> in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of her <hi>Birth,</hi> being born a <hi>Lady,</hi> and a <hi>Virtuoſa</hi> both, Seventh Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of that eminently Honourable <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard,</hi> the Firſt Earl of <hi>Cork,</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing born a private <hi>Gentleman,</hi> and younger Brother of a younger Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to no other Heritage than is expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the <hi>Device</hi> and <hi>Motto,</hi> which his humble Gratitude inſcribed on all the Palaces he built,
<q>
                        <hi>God's Providence, mine Inheritance.</hi>
                     </q> By that <hi>Providence,</hi> and his diligent and wiſe <hi>Induſtry,</hi> raiſed ſuch an <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> and <hi>Eſtate,</hi> and left ſuch a <hi>Family</hi> as never any Subject of theſe three Kingdoms did, and that with ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotted
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:41197:28"/>a <hi>reputation</hi> of integrity, that the moſt <hi>invidious ſcrutiny</hi> could find no blot, though it winnowed all the methods of his Riſing moſt ſeverely, which our good Lady hath often told me with great content and ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
                  <p>This Noble Lord by his prudent and pious Conſort, no leſs an Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Honour to their Deſcendants than himſelf, was bleſſed with five Sons, of which he lived to ſee four Lords, and Peers of the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And a Fifth, more than theſe Titles ſpeak, a Sovereign and Peerleſs, in a larger Province, that of univerſal na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſubdued, and made obſequious to his inquiſitive mind.</p>
                  <p>And eight Daughters.</p>
                  <p>And that you may remark how all things were extraordinary in this great Perſonage: it will, I hope, be neither unpleaſant, nor impertinent, to add a ſhort Story, I had from our Lady's own mouth.</p>
                  <p>Maſter <hi>Boyl</hi> (who was then a Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dower) came one Morning to wait up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:41197:29"/>Sir <hi>Jeoffry Fenton,</hi> at that time a great Officer of State in the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland;</hi> who being engaged in bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, and not knowing who it was who deſired to ſpeak with him, a while delayed him acceſs, which time he ſpent pleaſantly with his young Daughter in her Nurſes Arms. But when Sir <hi>Jeoffrey</hi> came, and ſaw whom he had made attend ſomewhat long, he civilly excuſed it. But Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Boyl</hi> replyed, he had been very well entertained, and ſpent his time much to his ſatisfactiou, in courting his Daughter, if he might obtain the Honour to be accepted for his Son-in-law. At which Sir <hi>Jeoffrey</hi> ſmiling, (to hear one who had been formerly married, move for a Wife carried in Arms, and under two years old) asked him, if he would ſtay for her: to which he frankly anſwered him he would, and Sir <hi>Jeoffrey</hi> as generouſly promiſed him, he ſhould then have his full conſent. And they both kept their words honourably. And by this vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Lady he had thirteen Children, ten of which he lived to ſee honourably married, and died a Grandfather by the youngeſt of them.</p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:41197:29"/>
                  <p>Nor did ſhe derive leſs <hi>honour</hi> from the <hi>collateral,</hi> than the <hi>deſcending</hi> Line, being Siſter by <hi>Soul</hi> and <hi>Genius,</hi> as well as <hi>Blood</hi> to theſe great <hi>Perſonages,</hi> whoſe <hi>illuſtrious, unſpotted,</hi> and <hi>reſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Honour,</hi> and <hi>Virtue,</hi> and whoſe <hi>uſeful Learning,</hi> and <hi>accurate Pens</hi> may attone and expiate, as well as ſhame, the ſcandalous Blemiſhes of a <hi>debauched,</hi> and the many <hi>impertinencies</hi> of a ſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Age.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Richard</hi> the truly Right Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, <hi>Loyal, Wiſe,</hi> and <hi>Virtuous</hi> Earl of <hi>Burlington</hi> and <hi>Cork,</hi> whoſe life is his faireſt, and moſt laudable Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Right Honourable <hi>Roger,</hi> Earl of <hi>Orery,</hi> that <hi>great Poet, great States-man, great Soldier,</hi> and great <hi>Every-thing</hi> which merits the name of <hi>Great</hi> or <hi>Good.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Francis, Lord Shannon:</hi> whoſe <hi>Pocket-Piſtol,</hi> as he ſtiles his Book, may make as wide Breaches in the Walls of the <hi>Capital,</hi> as many <hi>Canons.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. And that Honourable, and well known name <hi>R. Boyl,</hi> Eſquire, that <hi>profound Philoſopher, accompliſhed Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſt,</hi> and <hi>excellent Divine,</hi> I had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſaid <hi>Lay-Biſhop.</hi> as one hath ſtiled
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:41197:30"/>Sir <hi>H. Savil,</hi> whoſe Works alone may make a Library.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Female</hi> Branches alſo (if it be lawful ſo to call them. whoſe <hi>Virtues</hi> were ſo <hi>maſculine,</hi> Souls knowing no difference of Sex) by their <hi>Honours</hi> and <hi>Graces</hi> (by mutual reflections) gave, and received luſtre, to, and from her.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Eldeſt</hi> of which, the Lady <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice,</hi> was married to the Lord <hi>Bara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Second,</hi> the Lady <hi>Sarah,</hi> to the Lord <hi>Digby</hi> of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Third,</hi> the Lady <hi>Laetitia,</hi> to the eldeſt Son of the Lord <hi>Goring,</hi> who died Earl of <hi>Norwich.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Fourth,</hi> the Lady <hi>Joan,</hi> to the Earl of <hi>Kildare,</hi> not only <hi>Primier</hi> Earl of <hi>Ireland,</hi> but the <hi>ancienteſt Houſe</hi> in Chriſtendom of that degree, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>Earl</hi> being the ſix and twentieth, or ſeven and twentieth of Lineal Deſcent. And, as I have heard, it was that great <hi>Antiquary,</hi> King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt his obſervation, that the three anienteſt Families in <hi>Europe</hi> for <hi>Nobility,</hi> were the <hi>Veres</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> Earls of <hi>Oxford,</hi> and the <hi>Fitz-Geralds</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> Earls
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:41197:30"/>of <hi>Kildare:</hi> and <hi>Momorancy</hi> in <hi>France.</hi> 'Tis obſervable, that the preſent young Earl of <hi>Kildare</hi> is a mixture of the Blood of <hi>Fitz-Geralds</hi> and <hi>Veres.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Fifth,</hi> the Lady <hi>Katharine,</hi> who was married to the Lord Vicount <hi>Rane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laugh,</hi> and Mother to the preſent gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Earl of <hi>Ranelaugh,</hi> of which Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily I could have added an eminent Remark, I meet with in <hi>Fuller</hi>'s Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>Lady's Character</hi> is ſo ſignalized by her known Merit, among all Perſons of Honour; that as I <hi>need</hi> not, ſo I <hi>dare</hi> not attempt beyond this one word, She was our Lady's Friend-Siſter.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Sixth,</hi> the Lady <hi>Dorothy Lof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Seventh</hi> (the number of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection) which ſhut up and crown'd this noble Train, (for the Eighth, the Lady <hi>Margaret</hi> died unmarried) was our excellent Lady <hi>Mary,</hi> married to <hi>Charles</hi> Earl of <hi>Warwick:</hi> of whom, if I ſhould uſe the Language of my Text, I ſhould neither deſpair their pardon, nor fear the reproach of rudeneſs: <hi>Many Daughters,</hi> all his <hi>Daughters did virtuouſly; but thou</hi>—</p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:41197:31"/>
                  <p>She was <hi>Great</hi> by her Marriage into the Noble Neighbouring Family, which yet received acceſſion to its Grandure, by the luſtre of her Name and Virtues. But ſhe needed neither borrowed Shades, nor reflexive Lights, to ſet her off, being <hi>perſonally great</hi> in all natural Endowments and Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhments of Soul, and Body, Wiſdom, Beauty, Favour, Virtue.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Great</hi> by her <hi>Tongue;</hi> for never Woman uſed one better, ſpeaking ſo <hi>gracefully, promptly, diſcreetly, perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently, holily,</hi> that I have oft admired the edifying words that proceeded from her Mouth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Great</hi> by her <hi>Pen,</hi> as you may <hi>(Ex pede Herculem)</hi> diſcover by that little taſte of it, the world hath been happy in the haſty fruit of one or two inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted hours after Supper, which ſhe profeſſed to me with a little regret, when ſhe was ſurpriſed with it's ſliding into the world, without her know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, or allowance, and wholly beſide her expectation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Great</hi> by being the <hi>greateſt Miſtreſs,</hi> and <hi>Promotreſs,</hi> not to ſay the <hi>Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs,</hi> and <hi>Inventreſs</hi> of a <hi>new Science— The Art of obliging;</hi> in which ſhe at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:41197:31"/>that Sovereign Perfection, that ſhe <hi>reigned</hi> over all their hearts with whom ſhe did converſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Great</hi> in her nobleneſs of Living, and in her free and ſplendid Hoſpita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Great</hi> in the unparallel'd ſincerity of conſtant, faithful, condeſcending Friendſhip; and for that law of kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which dwelt in her Lips and Heart.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Great</hi> in her dexterity of Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Great</hi> in her quickneſs to apprehend the difficulties of her Affairs, and where the <hi>ſtreſs</hi> and <hi>pinch</hi> lay, to untie the Knot, and looſe and eaſe them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Great</hi> in the conqueſt of her ſelf, and maſtery of her paſſions, as I could give ſeveral pregnant inſtances, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in that of the death of her <hi>dear</hi> and <hi>only Son;</hi> wherein her beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour was ſo ſubmiſs, ſerene, and calm, I confeſs I cannot but judge it ſcarce imitable, or attainable by any other.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Great</hi> in a thouſand things beſides, which the world admires as ſuch; but I can be, and here profeſs my ſelf her faithful witneſs, ſhe deſpiſed them all, and <hi>counted them but loſs and dung in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:41197:32"/>of the fear of God, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of the knowledge of Chriſt Jeſus our Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Subſtance</hi> of great <hi>Volumes</hi> uſes to be ſummarily contracted into <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents</hi> and <hi>Titles.</hi> All I have ſaid is but an imperfect <hi>Index,</hi> to this great <hi>Folio of Voluminous Virtue.</hi> You that knew her muſt have the <hi>Book</hi> before you, turn over the <hi>leaves</hi> of your own me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories, and read with pleaſure what thoſe <hi>hints</hi> refer you to.</p>
                  <p>But I promiſed you to preſent her, as an <hi>example</hi> of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s <hi>Rule,</hi> let us therefore bring <hi>her,</hi> and the <hi>Text</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and never two were better met. If ever this Scripture were fulfilled, 'tis this day fulfilled in your ears.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O thou Great, Heroick, Noble, Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Soul,</hi> (and bleſſed be that God, and Grace that made thee ſuch) <hi>Many daughters have done virtuouſly, but thou excelleſt them all.</hi> Though thou wantedſt not Beauty, and didſt exceed in Favour; thou didſt neither prize them, nor catch at praiſes by them, but didſt <hi>fear the Lord with all thy heart,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:41197:32"/>and eſteemedſt that thy only praiſe and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. Thy hands were fruitful, and thy lips too,</hi> and thy Fruits were many, pleaſant, uſeful, ſeaſonable, ripe, ſweet, and fragrant: both to <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thou art now <hi>praiſing God,</hi> and we are <hi>praiſing thee:</hi> with the <hi>Sprigs</hi> of thoſe <hi>Lawrels</hi> will we crown <hi>thee</hi> which thy own <hi>hands</hi> did plant, and <hi>eyes</hi> did wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; that God may be praiſed in thee, and for thee, and others drawn by holy emulation to tranſcribe thy Copy. I ſhall begin with that which always had the firſt place in her care, and heart, <hi>her Religion, and Piety,</hi> which in the language of my Text, is the <hi>fear of the Lord.</hi> And I may, as is ſaid of <hi>Hanna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niah,</hi> Neh. 7.2. truly atteſt, that <hi>ſhe feared the Lord above many;</hi> above <hi>moſt,</hi> not to ſay above <hi>all:</hi> that <hi>ſhe feared the Lord greatly,</hi> as is teſtified of <hi>Obadiah,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 18.3. Or as <hi>David</hi> calls him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <hi>Gods ſervant devoted to his fear:</hi> Pſal. 119.38. So might ſhe moſt truly.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall give you an account of,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Her <hi>Entrance,</hi> or <hi>Beginning.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:41197:33"/>2. <hi>Progreſs,</hi> or <hi>Growth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Practice,</hi> and <hi>Exerciſe</hi> of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as to her ſelf.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Of her <hi>Zeal,</hi> and <hi>holy Induſtry</hi> to promote it, and encourage it in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> as to her <hi>beginning</hi> to be <hi>ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly Religious,</hi> and to make it her bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs in good earneſt, though ſhe had good education, and had been princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled in the Grounds of <hi>Catechiſm</hi> in her youth: yet ſhe would confeſs ſhe underſtood nothing of the <hi>life</hi> and <hi>power</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> upon her heart, had no ſpiritual ſenſe of it, till ſome years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhe was married. She hath told me alſo with what <hi>prejudice</hi> and ſtrange apprehenſions, as to matters of <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> ſhe came into the Family in which ſhe <hi>lived</hi> and <hi>died</hi> with ſo much Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, for ſhe was almoſt frighted with the diſadvantageous account was given of it: but when ſhe came to ſee the regular performance of divine Worſhip, and hear the uſeful, edifying, preaching of the moſt neceſſary, practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, and ſubſtantial truths, and obſerve the order and good Government, and received encouragement from her
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:41197:33"/>Right Honourable Father-in-law, who had always an extraordinary value for her, and affection to her: her <hi>preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice</hi> wore off, and <hi>approbation</hi> followed. Which minds me of a compariſon, uſed by the Learned <hi>P. Martyr,</hi> which occaſioned the Converſion of the Pious <hi>Galeacius Caracciolus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If a Man ſtanding at a great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance ſee a Company dancing, he wonders at their <hi>antick</hi> Geſtures, and ſeemingly ridiculous motions, and thinks them a company of mad men: but if he approaches nearer, and comes within the hearing of the ſweet and harmonious Muſick, which guides and meaſures out thoſe motions, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves how regularly one anſwers to the other, he then admires them, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves their decency and order, and deſires to dance with them. So if a man take up the reports the world gives of ſerious Chriſtians, or ſees them at a diſtance buſily attending all the duties of their holy Calling and Profeſſion, he thinks of them as <hi>Feſtus</hi> did of <hi>Paul:</hi> that <hi>they are beſide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi> or <hi>mad:</hi> but if he acquaint him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf more throughly with them, and hears and underſtands the Word of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:41197:34"/>God, which is as it were the Muſick to which they dance, and takes notice how they meaſure all their motions by its melody, he ſees ſuch an agreeing and beautiful conformity betwixt them; he cannot but approve it, and joyn with them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>God</hi> made uſe of two more <hi>remote</hi> means of her <hi>Converſion, Afflictions,</hi> and <hi>Retirement,</hi> the kind of the <hi>firſt,</hi> and the occaſion of the <hi>ſecond</hi> need not here be named. Only the divine Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Grace is very adorable, for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dapting ſuitable means to bring his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes to paſs: as theſe were in her cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, for ſhe would ſince ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that her great difficulty and <hi>remora,</hi> was her love of the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and vanities of the world, which ſhe neither knew how to reconcile with the ſtrictneſs of Religion, nor yet could be content to part with for that, whoſe ſweets and better pleaſures, ſhe was not then acquainted with: God therefore gradually weaned her, by rendring more inſipid what had too much pleaſed her, and by giving her vacancy and freedom from diſtraction, to acquaint her ſelf more throughly
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:41197:34"/>with the things of God. By which ſhe was enabled to ſet to her ſeal to that teſtimony which God gives to ſpiritual Wiſdom, <hi>That all her ways are pleaſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and all her paths are peace:</hi> and to her Friends would frequently and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do it, aſſuring them That ſhe had no cauſe to repent the change ſhe found, of the ſolid and ſatisfying pleaſures ſhe obtained in Religion, for thoſe unquiet, empty ones, ſhe left in ways of vanity: thereby encouraging them to <hi>try,</hi> not doubting, but upon experience they would become of the ſame mind.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Two</hi> more <hi>immediate</hi> helps which God bleſſed to her, were the <hi>preaching</hi> of the Word <hi>(which God hath ordained for the ſalvation of them that believe:</hi> 1 Cor. 1.21.) and <hi>Chriſtian Conference,</hi> and (becauſe ſuch an hint may do o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers good) the preſſing the neceſſity of <hi>ſpeedy and true repentance,</hi> and ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the danger of <hi>procraſtination,</hi> and puttings off, and ſtifling preſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions by delay: This ſeemed to turn the wavering, trembling balance, and to fix the ſcale of her reſolution.</p>
                  <p>This is about nine and twenty years
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:41197:35"/>ſince, from which time (though be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her converſation was viceleſs, ſweet, and inoffenſive, yet ſhe would confeſs her mind was vain) ſhe <hi>walk'd with God</hi> moſt cloſely, circumſpectly, accurately. And I verily believe few (if any) ever <hi>choſe the better part,</hi> more reſolutely than this our noble <hi>Mary,</hi> or devoted themſelves more unreſervedly <hi>to God's love,</hi> and <hi>fear,</hi> and <hi>ſervice,</hi> learning to be good in very good earneſt, and to encreaſe, <hi>and grow in grace, and in the knowledge of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>To promote this,</hi> like the wiſe man in the Goſpel, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.24. <hi>She dug deep to lay her foundations on a rock.</hi> She made a ſtrict ſcrutiny into the ſtate of her Soul, and weighed the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of her choice, in the balance of the Sanctuary. And with the other Buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in the Goſpel, <hi>ſate down and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered with her ſelf what it might coſt to finiſh her ſpiritual edifice, and whether ſhe were furniſhed to defray that charge.</hi> And alſo whether the grounds of her hope were firm, and ſuch as would not abuſe, and ſhame her, and her evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences for Heaven, ſuch as would
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:41197:35"/>bear the Teſt, and Scripture would approve.</p>
                  <p>And this ſhe drew up at large, with her own hand <hi>judiciouſly, ſoberly, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtly, humbly,</hi> and about twenty years ſince did me the honour with greateſt ſecrecy to read it to me, and obliged me with all freedom and faithfulneſs to give her my judgment of it; which I could not but do with much approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And this, I doubt not, remains amongſt her many excellent Papers.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Having thus put her hand to the plough, ſhe looked not back,</hi> but minded Religion as her buſineſs indeed; and never gave ſuſpicion of <hi>trifling</hi> in ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious a work.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Therefore for her <hi>practice</hi> of it, it was her great deſign <hi>to walk worthy of God in all well-pleaſing, to adorn her pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed ſubjection to the Goſpel, by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation becoming it, and to ſhew forth his virtues and praiſes, who had called her</hi> to his marvellous Light.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt</hi> then ſhe was circumſpectly careful <hi>to abſtain from all appearance of evil;</hi> and in all doubtful caſes 'twas
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:41197:36"/>her rule to take the fureſt ſide; for ſhe would ſay, I am ſure, 'twill do me no hurt, to let them alone. Though therefore none were further from cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring others, or uſurping judgment over their liberties; yet for her ſelf ſhe would never allow her ſelf the addition of artificial handſomneſs, (uſed nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther paint nor patch) and was pleaſed with a ſaying of one of her ſpiritual Friends, upon the reading the Book which apologizes for it: <hi>O Lord, I thank thee, that thou gaveſt me not wit enough to write ſuch a Book, unleſs withal thou hadſt given me Grace enough not to write it.</hi> Neither would ſhe play at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Games, becauſe beſide many other inconveniences, ſhe judged them great waſters of precious time: of which ſhe was always very <hi>thrifty.</hi> And though ſhe was known to be a woman of good underſtanding, yet were there <hi>three</hi> things which were too hard for her, and ſhe would confeſs ſhe could not comprehend them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> How thoſe who profeſſed to believe an Eternal Eſtate, and it's de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance upon the ſhort inch of time, could complain of times lying as a dead
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:41197:36"/>commodity on their hands, which they were troubled how to drive away.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> how Chriſtians, who would ſeem devout at Church, could laugh at others for being ſerious out on't, and burleſque the very Bible, and turn Religion into Ridicule.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> How knowing men could take care of ſouls, and ſeldom come amongſt them, never look after them.</p>
                  <p>And though in the forenamed par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, ſhe was content only to give example of forbearance: yet from the Play-houſe, ſince the Stage hath taken ſo great liberty, ſhe would openly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort her Friends with greateſt earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>She,</hi> very many years ſince, began to keep a <hi>Diary;</hi> and conſulted two, whom ſhe uſed to call her Soul-Friends, and ever eſteemed ſuch her beſt Friends, concerning the beſt manner of performing it. This, at <hi>firſt,</hi> ſhe uſed to perform every <hi>Evening;</hi> but finding that inconvenient, by reaſon of her <hi>Lords</hi> long illneſs, which gave her
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:41197:37"/>many inevitable diverſions and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions at that ſeaſon, ſhe changed it into the quiet, ſilent morning, always riſing early. And therein amongſt other things recorded the dayly <hi>frame of her own heart</hi> towards God, his <hi>ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal providences</hi> to her ſelf, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times towards others, <hi>his gracious ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtations to her Soul, returns of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, temptations reſiſted, or prevailing,</hi> or whatever might be uſeful for <hi>caution</hi> or <hi>encouragement,</hi> afford her matter of <hi>thankfulneſs</hi> or <hi>humiliation.</hi> And by this means ſhe had arrived at ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, that ſhe could conclude, at leaſt make ſtrong conjectures of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents of things ſhe ſpread before the Lord in prayer, by the <hi>frame of her own heart,</hi> in the performance of it, as I could inſtance in particulars, if it were convenient.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>She</hi> uſed to call Prayer Hearts-eaſe, as ſhe often found it; and though her modeſty was ſuch, and ſhe was ſo far from a vain, affected oſtentation of her gifts, I cannot name one perſon with whom ſhe prayed, yet can I ſay ſhe was as well mighty, and fervent in prayer, as conſtant and abundant in it;
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:41197:37"/>for ſhe ſometimes uſing her voice, hath been over-heard, and her <hi>own Lord</hi> (knowing her hours of prayer) once conveyed a grave Miniſter into a ſecret place, within hearing, whom, if I ſhould name, I ſuppoſe would not be denyed to be a competent Judge, who much admired her humble fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vency; for ſhe <hi>praying prayed,</hi> and when ſhe uſed not an audible voice, <hi>her ſighs</hi> and <hi>groans</hi> would eccho from her Cloſet at good diſtance. And the very day before ſhe died, ſhe was ſhut up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove an hour, which ſhe ſpent in <hi>fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, private prayer,</hi> notwithſtanding her indiſpoſition; and indeed <hi>prayer was her very element,</hi> in which ſhe <hi>lived,</hi> and <hi>actually</hi> died; and 'twas as the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal breath of her Soul, and the wing that wafted it immediately to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
                  <p>But if ſhe <hi>exceeded</hi> her ſelf in any thing; as much as ſhe excelled others in moſt things, 'twas in <hi>meditation:</hi> this was her <hi>Maſter-piece;</hi> for ſhe uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally walked two hours dayly in the morning, to meditate alone, in which divine art ſhe was an accompliſhed Miſtreſs, both in ſet and occaſional, in
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:41197:38"/>the firſt chuſing ſome ſelect ſubject, which ſhe would preſs upon her heart, with intenſeſt thoughts, till ſhe had drawn out all its juice and nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and for the ſecond, like a <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Bee,</hi> ſhe would ſuck Honey from all occurrences, whole Volumes of which ſhe hath left behind her.</p>
                  <p>After this <hi>conſecrating</hi> of the day with <hi>reading Scriptures,
<note place="margin">Lectione aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidua &amp; meditatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne diuturna pectus ſuum Biblio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecam ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerat Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti; unde hic fervor, aiſi ex amere Dei? unde legis Chriſti indefeſſa meditatio niſi ex defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derio ejus qui legem dedit?</note> prayer,</hi> and <hi>meditation:</hi> a ſhort dreſſing time, and ordering her domeſtick Affairs, or reading ſome good Book, ſpent the remainder of the morning till <hi>Chappel-prayers,</hi> from which ſhe was never <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,</hi> and at which ſhe was ever <hi>reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend,</hi> and a <hi>devout</hi> example to her whole Family.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>She</hi> was a <hi>ſtrict obſerver of the Lords<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,</hi> which is truly called the <hi>Hedge</hi> and <hi>Fence</hi> of Religion, and though ſome pleaſe themſelves to call this <hi>Judaizing,</hi> to excuſe the liberties they indulge themſelves: I am ſure our Church hath injoyn'd us all to <hi>cry</hi> to God for <hi>mercy,</hi> for the breach of, and for <hi>grace</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline our hearts to keep, the <hi>fourth Commandment,</hi> as well as any of the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:41197:38"/>other <hi>nine:</hi> and 'tis not hard to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that the ſtreams of Religion are deep, or ſhallow, according as theſe Banks are kept up, or neglected.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>She</hi> was a very <hi>devout Communicant;</hi> ſeldom omitting to prepare her Soul with <hi>ſolemn faſting,</hi> to <hi>renew her cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> with God.</p>
                  <p>And in the act of receiving, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not think of her without reflecting on S. <hi>Stephen,</hi> when <hi>he ſaw the Heavens o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, and Jeſus ſtanding at God's right hand, and his face was as the face of an Angel.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And to encourage <hi>others</hi> to ſuch <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious</hi> preparation to that <hi>Sacred Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,</hi> as ſhe us'd before it: I ſhall ſhew what <hi>ſweet advantages</hi> ſhe reaped in it, and by it. And this I ſhall do by tranſcribing word for word out of her <hi>Diary,</hi> what I find written with her own hand, concerning one of the laſt <hi>Sacrament Days,</hi> ſhe ever enjoyed. For the Sacrament which was appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to have been adminiſtred in her La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyſhips <hi>Chappel</hi> upon <hi>Eaſter-day,</hi> was put off by reaſon of her falling ill in <hi>Paſſion</hi> week.</p>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:41197:39"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>November,</hi> 25. <hi>Sacrament Day.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <p>AS ſoon as I awaked, I bleſſed God. When I had read in the <hi>Word,</hi> the Chapters of the Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of my <hi>Bleſſed Saviour,</hi> I ſpent much time in meditating of his <hi>dying love.</hi> By which thoughts I found my <hi>heart</hi> much drawn out to <hi>love</hi> him, and <hi>melted</hi> by his <hi>love:</hi> then with great and awful apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of <hi>God</hi> upon my heart, I went to <hi>pray.</hi> In which <hi>duty</hi> my <hi>heart</hi> was lifted up in the high <hi>praiſes</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> for both ſpiritual and temporal mercies: and my <hi>affections</hi> were much drawn out in the <hi>duty,</hi> in which my <hi>heart</hi> did follow exceeding hard after <hi>God</hi> for a nearer commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with him in the <hi>Sacrament</hi> than ever yet I had. I then renewed my <hi>covenant</hi> with <hi>God:</hi> and made pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, that by his <hi>Grace</hi> enabling me, I would walk more cloſely with him, for the time to come. That which in eſpecial manner I begged of God at this <hi>Sacrament</hi> was more <hi>love</hi> to him,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:41197:39"/>more <hi>holineſs,</hi> more <hi>contempt</hi> of the world, and the Glories of it, that I might be more <hi>uſeful</hi> to the <hi>Souls</hi> and <hi>Bodies</hi> of my Fellow <hi>Chriſtians</hi> than formerly I had been.</p>
                     <p>Thoſe <hi>mercies,</hi> which in eſpecial manner, I was grateful for, were, the <hi>Creation</hi> and <hi>Redemption</hi> of the World, and for the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and the <hi>Covenant</hi> of <hi>Grace,</hi> and for <hi>convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Grace,</hi> and for <hi>Juſtification,</hi> and for ſome meaſure of <hi>Sanctification:</hi> and for ſo much <hi>Patience</hi> exerciſed toward me, <hi>before</hi> my <hi>converſion:</hi> and in order to it, <hi>imbittering Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-comforts,</hi> that I might ſeek for <hi>comforts above:</hi> and for a <hi>ſanctified affliction,</hi> and for ſome degree of <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience</hi> to bear it, and for ſupports under it by the warm and lively <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts</hi> of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt:</hi> and for <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns</hi> of <hi>prayer:</hi> and for ſo many <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities</hi> to ſeek unto God: and for the ſweet <hi>reviving</hi> hours I had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed with <hi>God</hi> in <hi>ſolitude</hi> by Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly <hi>Meditations:</hi> and for the <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Sacraments,</hi> and the <hi>ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifying motions</hi> of <hi>Gods Spirit.</hi> I was in a more than uſual manner <hi>melted</hi> in the <hi>duty,</hi> and <hi>ſhed</hi> a very great
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:41197:40"/>plenty of <hi>tears</hi> in it: which when I came from, I found a <hi>longing</hi> deſire to partake of the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> and a <hi>great joy</hi> that I was going to partake of it. Then I went to hear— the Text was, <hi>I am the way, the truth and the life, no man cometh to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but by me.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I was attentive at that good Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. And by what I heard of the <hi>excellency</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> had my <hi>heart</hi> much warmed with <hi>love</hi> to him.</p>
                     <p>Afterwards, at the <hi>confeſſion</hi> before the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> I found my <hi>heart</hi> in a more than uſual manner <hi>broken</hi> for my ſins, which I <hi>bewailed</hi> with great plenty of <hi>tears,</hi> and from my <hi>heart judged,</hi> and <hi>loathed</hi> my ſelf for them. After I had received, I found my <hi>heart</hi> in an extraordinary manner <hi>warmed</hi> with <hi>love</hi> to <hi>God.</hi> And my <hi>Soul did follow very hard after him,</hi> to be made more <hi>holy,</hi> and for <hi>Grace</hi> to ſerve him better than ever yet I had done. I had very <hi>lively</hi> affections in the <hi>duty;</hi> in which I received much joy, and had ſweet communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with God in it.</p>
                     <p>After I had at the <hi>Table</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> given to the Poor, I came from
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:41197:40"/>the <hi>Sacrament</hi> with my <hi>heart</hi> in a ſweet, grateful, and Heavenly Frame, and then in private <hi>bleſſed God,</hi> for that <hi>bleſſed Feaſt,</hi> and begged ſtrength to keep my promiſes I had made to <hi>God,</hi> of new obedience.</p>
                     <p>In the Afternoon I heard again the ſame perſon, upon the ſame <hi>Text,</hi> I was in an attentive, ſerious, frame at that good Sermon. The Subject of which was to ſhew, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> was the only <hi>way</hi> for poor <hi>peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſinners</hi> to come unto the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                     <p>I <hi>meditated</hi> upon the Sermons, and <hi>prayed</hi> them over. And had alſo <hi>meditations</hi> of the <hi>Joys</hi> of <hi>Heaven,</hi> with the thoughts of being for ever <hi>freed from ſin,</hi> and of being ever with the Lord, where I ſhould <hi>enjoy him</hi> in his <hi>fulleſt love.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I found my <hi>heart</hi> much <hi>revived,</hi> and my <hi>Soul</hi> did then make ſtrong <hi>Sallies</hi> and <hi>Egreſſes</hi> after that bleſſed <hi>Reſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>After Family Duties were over, at which I prayed with fervency, I did before going to Bed commit my ſelf to <hi>God.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="68" facs="tcp:41197:41"/>
                     <p>O <hi>Lord,</hi> I do from my <hi>Soul</hi> bleſs thee for this ſweet day, in which thou wert pleaſed to vouchſafe unto <hi>me,</hi> thy moſt unworthy Servant, more <hi>Soul-joy,</hi> than thou didſt give me for a long time before.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>She</hi> was a very <hi>ferious and artentive hearer of the Word,</hi> and conſtantly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Sermon <hi>recollected</hi> what ſhe heard, ſometimes by <hi>writing,</hi> always by <hi>think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and calling it to mind, that ſhe might make it her own, and turn it into pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, not content to be a <hi>forgetful, fruitleſs hearer</hi> only, <hi>but a doer, that ſhe might be bleſſed in her deed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And ſuch ſhe was for the <hi>external</hi> performances of <hi>Religion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And though this was <hi>beautiful</hi> and <hi>lovely,</hi> yet her <hi>chief glory was within, in the hidden man of the heart, in that which is not corruptible,</hi> in that <hi>dreſs of Graces</hi> which adorned her Soul, this ſtring was all of Orient Pearls, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly matched, not one ill watered, or of unequal ſize. There was not one <hi>dryed</hi> or <hi>withered</hi> Limb, one member <hi>wanting</hi> or <hi>defective</hi> in the new crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:41197:41"/>ſhe was <hi>complete in Chriſt,</hi> all of a piece.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Head</hi> of her Knowledge was <hi>comprehenſive</hi> and <hi>clear.</hi> The <hi>Eye</hi> of her Faith was <hi>piercing</hi> and <hi>ſteddy.</hi> The <hi>Ear</hi> of her obedience was <hi>open</hi> and <hi>light of hearing, and boared at the door poſts of wiſdoms houſe.</hi> Her <hi>Palate</hi> was <hi>ſavory,</hi> and <hi>reliſhing,</hi> to which God's Law was <hi>ſweeter than the honey, and the honey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comb, and more eſteemed than her neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary food.</hi> The <hi>Cheeks</hi> of her Modeſty were <hi>fair</hi> and <hi>ruddy.</hi> The <hi>Arms</hi> of her deſires were <hi>ſtretched out after God,</hi> and <hi>flexible,</hi> to embrace him. The <hi>Hands</hi> of her <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Charity</hi> were <hi>ſtrong</hi> and <hi>open.</hi> The <hi>Breaſts</hi> of her Bounty were <hi>well-faſhioned,</hi> and <hi>full of milk,</hi> and the Bowels of her compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion were <hi>tender</hi> and <hi>fruitful.</hi> Her <hi>hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> and <hi>thirſt after righteouſneſs</hi> was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <hi>greedy</hi> and <hi>inſatiable.</hi> The <hi>heart</hi> of her ſincerity was <hi>ſound</hi> and <hi>lively,</hi> and the <hi>pulſe</hi> of her conſcience <hi>ſmooth</hi> and <hi>equal.</hi> The <hi>feet</hi> of her affections were <hi>ſwifter than the Roes on the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of Bether,</hi> more truly winged than the Poets feign their <hi>Mercuries.</hi> The <hi>natural heat</hi> of her Zeal more <hi>fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent than the coals of Juniper,</hi> and the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:41197:42"/>
                     <hi>radical moiſture</hi> of her repentance more <hi>fluid</hi> than the <hi>ſprings of Piſgah.</hi> Being ſeen with dry eyes, under tear-moving circumſtances, which very nearly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd her ſelf, and being asked, how ſhe could refrain? She replyed, <hi>I deſire to weep for nothing but my ſins.</hi> Her <hi>name was as ointment poured forth,</hi> which made her the delight and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of all good men and women; yea, you may call her a <hi>She Jedidiah,</hi> a <hi>Female Lemuel,</hi> the Lord's delights, ſhe with whom God was.</p>
                  <p>Now the <hi>Soul</hi> of this excellent <hi>Body,</hi> which animated all its goodly parts within, was the <hi>love of God,</hi> and the gorgeous Robe which cloathed it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, was her <hi>deep humility.</hi> Theſe were the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Moon</hi> in this great Firmament, all whoſe <hi>Stars</hi> were of the <hi>firſt magnitude,</hi> and the <hi>leaſt</hi> of which would have made the great Luminary in another Orb. Such was this beauteous Spouſe of Chriſt, ſo like her Heavenly Bridegroom, that for that reſemblance ſake, we may ſay of her ſhe was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding lovely.</p>
                  <p>Nor was ſhe leſs ſolicitous to make others good, than to be ſo her ſelf. She well remembred our Savious charge to
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:41197:42"/>S. <hi>Peter, When thou art converted, ſtrengthen thy Brethren:</hi> She ſet her heart to build God's ſpiritual Temple, and therefore ſhe applyed her ſelf to it with all her might. She had holy Tranſports for the Glory of God, and ſhe was a great Lover of Souls, and thoſe two engaged her to promote Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion with utmoſt induſtry and zeal, which that ſhe might accompliſh more advantageouſly,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>She</hi> avowedly deſigned to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>Religion</hi> as <hi>amiable,</hi> and <hi>taking,</hi> and <hi>free from vulgar prejudice,</hi> as poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſhe might; not ſo as might affright and ſcare men from it: but that it might <hi>allure</hi> them, and <hi>inſinuate</hi> it's ſelf into their love and liking: to this end ſhe was <hi>affable, familiar, pleaſant,</hi> of a <hi>free,</hi> and <hi>agreeable</hi> converſation, <hi>unaffected,</hi> not <hi>ſour, reſerved, moroſe, ſad, dejected, melancholy,</hi> which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents Religion moſt diſadvantageouſly. She was naturally of the ſweeteſt tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in the world: and <hi>Grace</hi> inoculated into ſuch a ſtock, thrives even luxuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antly. Whereas ſome <hi>crabbed, peeviſh, ſullen</hi> natures ſtarve the beſt Cien they are grafted with. As I remember one,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:41197:43"/>of whom 'twas uſually ſaid, he had Grace enough for ſeven other men, yet ſcarce enough for himſelf. And ſhe made <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>nature</hi> both ſubſervient to the good of others.</p>
                  <p>As we ſay of ſome neat, well faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd perſons, what ere they wear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes them, and ſits well: I muſt do her this right, to teſtifie, I never ſaw Religion become any perſon better. And 'twas hard not to approve and love a dreſs ſo decent and adorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>She</hi> kept her ſelf <hi>free</hi> and <hi>diſinte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſed</hi> from all Parties and Factions, that none might ſuſpect a deſign of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Proſelytes to any, but to God.</p>
                  <p>She was neither of <hi>Paul,</hi> nor <hi>Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los,</hi> nor <hi>Cephas,</hi> but only Chriſt. Her name was <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> and her Sirname <hi>Catholick,</hi> ſhe had a large and uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined Soul, not hemm'd in, or pound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up within the Circle of any man's name, or drawing a <hi>Latitudinarian</hi> in the true commendable ſenſe: and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever <hi>feared God, and wrought righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was accepted of her.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>She</hi> very <hi>inoffenſively, regularly, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voutly,</hi> obſerved all the orders of the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:41197:43"/>Church of <hi>England,</hi> in its Liturgy and publick Service, which ſhe failed not to attend twice a day with exemplary Reverence, yet was ſhe very far from placing Religion in Ritual Obſervances. And I may not deny, that ſhe would ſometimes warm her heart <hi>(though never with ſtrange fire)</hi> at private Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, in her own Chamber or Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. She would perfume the company with good diſcourſe, to prevent idle, or worſe communication, not <hi>abruptly, obraidingly,</hi> or <hi>importunely,</hi> which is very <hi>nauſeous</hi> and <hi>fulſome,</hi> and <hi>ſpoils a good game by bad playing.</hi> But ſhe was like a <hi>ſpiritual Stove,</hi> you ſhould <hi>feel</hi> the <hi>heat,</hi> and not <hi>ſee</hi> the <hi>fire,</hi> and find your ſelf in <hi>other company</hi> amongſt the <hi>ſame perſons,</hi> and rather <hi>wonder</hi> than <hi>perceive</hi> how you came there; for ſhe would drop <hi>a wiſe ſentence,</hi> or <hi>moral holy Apothegm</hi> (with which ſhe was admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly furniſhed, of her own making or collection) that ſuited with, at leaſt not far remote from what was talked of, and commending, or improving that, ſhe'd wind about the whole diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe without offence, yea, with much pleaſure.</p>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:41197:44"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>She</hi> kept a Book of ſuch <hi>wiſe, pithy</hi> Sayings, much valuing words, which contain'd great uſe and worth in little compaſs.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall tranſcribe a few of many.</p>
                  <p>THe almoſt Chriſtian is the unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieſt Man, having Religion e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to make the world hate him; and not enough to make God love him.</p>
                  <p>God's Servants ſhould be as bold for him as the Devils are for him.</p>
                  <p>What will make thee happy at any time, may make thee happy at all times.</p>
                  <p>O Lord, what I give thee, doth not pleaſe thee, unleſs I give thee my ſelf. So what thou giveſt me ſhall not ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie me, unleſs thou give me thy ſelf.</p>
                  <p>O Lord, who giveſt Grace to the humble, give me Grace to be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
                  <p>He loves God too little, who loves any thing with him, which he loves not for him.</p>
                  <p>The true meaſure of loving God, is to love him without meaſure.</p>
                  <p>So ſpeak to God, as though men
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:41197:44"/>heard thee, ſo ſpeak to men, as know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God hears thee.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaid, he was better born, than to be a ſlave to his Body.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Luther</hi> ſaid, Chriſt's Croſs is no Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, yet it taught him more than all the Alphabet.</p>
                  <p>We ſhould meditate of Chriſt's Croſs, till we be faſtened as cloſe to him, as he was to his Croſs.</p>
                  <p>By how much the more Chriſt made himſelf vile for us: by ſo much the more precious he ſhould be to us.</p>
                  <p>We need every day blood for our hearts, as water for our hands.</p>
                  <p>Through Chriſt's wounds we may ſee his Bowels.</p>
                  <p>He only can ſatisfie us, who ſatisfied for us.</p>
                  <p>He that takes up Chriſt's Croſs hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomely, ſhall find it ſuch a burden as Wings to a Bird, or Sails to a Ship.</p>
                  <p>'Tis a great honour to be Almoner to the King of Heaven.</p>
                  <p>The Bowels of the poor are the beſt ſoyl, which brings forth an hundred fold.</p>
                  <p>Who would not ſtarve a Luſt to feed a Saint.</p>
                  <p>To give is the greateſt ſenſuality:
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:41197:45"/>How indulgent then is God to annex future rewards, to what is ſo much its own recompenſe.</p>
                  <p>To be libell'd for Chriſt is the beſt Panegyrick.</p>
                  <p>Where affliction is heavy, ſin is light.</p>
                  <p>God chaſtiſes whom he loves, but he loves not to chaſtiſe.</p>
                  <p>Sin brought death into the world, and nothing but death will carry ſin out of the world.</p>
                  <p>If all mens troubles were brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a common ſtore, every one would carry back what he brought, rather than ſtand to a ſhare of an equal divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
                  <p>Though time be not laſting, what depend on it, is everlaſting.</p>
                  <p>The beſt Shield againſt Slanderers, is to live ſo, that none may believe them.</p>
                  <p>He that revenges an injury, acts the part of an Executioner. He that pardons it, acts the part of a Prince.</p>
                  <p>Sanctified afflictions are ſpiritual promotions.</p>
                  <p>Man is a pile of Duſt, and puff of Wind.</p>
                  <p>Why are we ſo fond of that life
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:41197:45"/>which begins with a Cry, and ends with a Groan!</p>
                  <p>But I will not cloy you, knowing it is ſafeſt to riſe with an appetite; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven when we are entertained at a Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Where ſhe had particular <hi>kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> or perſonal <hi>intereſt,</hi> ſhe would improve the authority of her <hi>friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> to gentle, but free correption, and argue, and perſwade ſo ſtrenuouſly, that her <hi>Bow,</hi> like <hi>Jonathan</hi>'s, <hi>ſeldom re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd empty;</hi> and plead the cauſe of God, and their own ſouls, to whom ſhe ſpake with ſo winning and inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſweetneſs, that 'twas hard to reſiſt the <hi>Suada,</hi> ſhall I ſay, or rather the <hi>ſpirit,</hi> by which ſhe ſpake. Let me re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found and eccho from her <hi>lips</hi> (though alas too faintly) how ſhe would with melting charms, and powerful ſtrains, attempt upon the Friends, for whom ſhe had a kindneſs, and whom ſhe longed to reſcue.</p>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:41197:46"/>
                  <p>
                     <q>COme, come, my Friend, you muſt be good, you ſhall be good; I cannot be ſo unkind, nay, ſo unfaithful to the laws of Friendſhip, as to let you periſh, and periſh in a way, you know as well as I, leads down to Hell. It grieves my very ſoul to ſee ſo good a nature enſnared againſt the dictates of its own light, by bad example, cuſtom, or ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what elſe— And if they replyed with excuſes,</q> ſhe would ſtop them thus:
<q>I pray, my Friend, have pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, hear me out, I know, or gueſs at leaſt, what you would ſay, and I would not have you ſay it. 'Tis bad to commit ſin, but 'tis worſe to plead for it, and defend it. <hi>None ſin ſo dangerouſly as thoſe who ſin with excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</hi> The Devil then ties a new ſnare, when he gets into our tongues to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten us to our failings, and raiſes an out-work in our own mouths, to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the Fort he poſſeſſes in our hearts: I take it for granted, all other Holds were ſlighted eaſily, could you conquer ſuch or ſuch a vice, too much by cuſtom prevailing with you.
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:41197:46"/>Unhappy cuſtom that dares preſcribe againſt God's Law—But, <hi>Friend,</hi> uſe no arguments that will not hold water at the day of judgment: <hi>though hand joyn in hand,</hi> you know what follows. And no example, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom, number ſhould allure us, which cannot excuſe us, and ſecure us. But this is the miſchief of ſin liv'd in, it bewitches the heart to love it, that it cannot leave it. Cannot, ſo men love to ſpeak; but 'tis becauſe they will not, that is, will uſe no en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to be rid on't. But you muſt leave it, there's no remedy though it coſt you trouble, ſmart, and ſelf-denial. There's as much as all this comes to, in <hi>cutting off a right hand,</hi> and <hi>digging out a right eye.</hi> I ſpeak to you, as to one in whom I have a party to help me plead. I mean your conſcience, and the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of the Scriptures; for if you were one of thoſe on whom you know I uſe to ſet my mark, I ſhould not give you this trouble, nor eſteem my ſelf under more than the Laws of general charity to wiſh you better, ſhould hardly venture my little skill to make you ſo.</q>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="80" facs="tcp:41197:47"/>
                     <p>But as for you, who ſtill own God's authority, and believe his Word, and attend his Worſhip. Why ſhould I deſpair of making one piece of your ſelf, agree with the other, your practice with your convictions, your converſation with your conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
                     <p>And not to fright you with the Thunder-claps of wrath and venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and God's judging you know who—liſten ſtill to the voice, 'tis your peculiar eminency to be kind and grateful (and becauſe there is a kind of magnetick virtue in thoſe arguments which touch our temper, and a ſtring will move it ſelf when a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother inſtrument is touched that's ſet to the ſame Key, and pitch) I ſhall attack you on that ſide, hoping the ſtrongeſt excellency of your na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, will prove the weakeſt defenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſative for ſin, and to keep out God.</p>
                     <p>You therefore who are ſo good na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured, ſo kind, ſo grateful that you ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver think you have acquit your ſelf ſufficiently to thoſe who have been civil, or as you pleaſe to call't obliging. Oh how can— be ſo unkind, and ſo ungrateful unto God Almighty,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:41197:47"/>the kindeſt Fiend, who is ſo much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand with you, who hath given you ſo much, and is ſo ready to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give you all. Oh, that you, who I dare ſay would take my word for any thing elſe, would do me the honour to take my word for him, who I aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you upon your ſincere repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance will be fully reconciled to you in Chriſt, and never ſo much as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braid your paſt neglects, <hi>but heal your back-ſlidings, and love you freely.</hi> And do not fear that you ſhall have cauſe to repent of your repentance. <hi>No man ever yet was a loſer by God;</hi> and you ſhan't be the firſt: you ſhall not loſe your pleaſures, but exchange them, defiling ones for pure and clean, and raviſhing. And let it not ſeem ſtrange, or incredible to you, that there ſhould be ſuch things, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe perhaps you never felt them. Alas, you have deprived your ſelf unhappily, by being uncapable of them. <hi>New wine muſt be put into new bottles.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To ſay nothing of what the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures ſpeak of a <hi>day being in God's courts being better than a thouſand, and of joys; and unſpeakable, and full of
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:41197:48"/>glory, of the great peace they have who keep God's law, and that nothing ſhall offend them, that wiſdoms ways are plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantneſs.</hi> Let my weakneſs reaſon out the caſe with you. Do you think that God's Angels which excel in all perfections, have no delights, becauſe they have no fleſh, no ſenſe, no bodies, as men and beaſts: or have our Souls (the Angels in theſe houſes of clay) which are God's Images, and the price of his Blood no objects, no employments which may yield them delight and ſatisfaction.</p>
                     <p>Think not ſo unworthily of God, or meanly of your ſelf; have not the ſtroaks of your own fancy, or the intellectual pleaſures of your mind, ſometimes tranſported you beyond all the charms of your ſenſes, when they have chimed all in tune toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                     <p>And cannot God, think you, who is a ſpirit, and ſo fit an object for our ſouls, give them as great pleaſures, as any object of our taſte and ſight.</p>
                     <p>Come, come, my <hi>Friend,</hi> take my word for't, there is more pleaſure in the peace of a good conſcience, and in well grounded hopes our ſins are
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:41197:48"/>pardoned, and in ſerving God, and expectation of eternal life, than in all the pleaſures in the world. Alas, I was once of your mind, but I aſſure you upon my word, I have really found more ſatisfaction in ſerving God, than ever I found in all the good things of the world, of which you know I have had my ſhare.</p>
                     <p>Try therefore, <hi>dare to be good,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to be ſo throughly; and if you do not find it much better than I have told you, never take my word, or truſt me more.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>Thus and much more powerfully would her zeal for their good cauſe her to argue with her Friends, that ſhe might by holy violence attract them, and allure them to be good, and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. <hi>She</hi> was of an <hi>extenſive charity,</hi> and would make people good by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving them to be ſo, and by this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement make them aſhamed to deceive her hopes, and diſappoint her expectation.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <pb n="84" facs="tcp:41197:49"/>6. <hi>She</hi> had a tender, conſcientious care to provide good Miniſters, and to encourage them, would augment their maintenance where 'twas ſmall; <hi>Leez, Braintree,</hi> and <hi>Foulneſs,</hi> &amp;c. may be her witneſſes in this, and indeed ſhe was the heartieſt and trueſt Friend I e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver knew to ſuch, and do deſpair ever to know her like, in this reſpect.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. <hi>She</hi> had a great care of the <hi>Souls</hi> of her Servants, and if ſhe had any ambition in her, 'twas in this, to be the <hi>Miſtreſs</hi> of a <hi>religious</hi> Family. This appeared amongſt others, in theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. In exacting their attendance on God's publick Worſhip, and reverent behaviour there.</p>
                  <p>Her <hi>Eye</hi> ſurveyed her <hi>Chappel,</hi> and none could be abſent, but ſhe would miſs them.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. In <hi>perſonal inſtruction,</hi> and famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar perſwading of them, I appeal to the conſciences of all that ſerv'd her, what one of them hath ſhe not, on ſome oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, dealt with to do them good.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. In preparing them for, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading them to the frequent partiei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:41197:49"/>of the Lord's moſt holy Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. In ſcattering good Books in all the common Rooms and places of atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, that thoſe that waited might not loſe their time, but well employ it, and have a bait laid of ſome practical, uſeful Book, and fitted to their capacity, which might catch and take them.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. In making it the Foot-ſtep to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, for ſhe uſed to make the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dredth and firſt Pſalm the <hi>Rule</hi> of her <hi>Oeconomicks;</hi> and though ſhe treated all her ſervants as Friends, yet they were her Favourites, which moſt ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally feared God.</p>
                  <p>And ſhe was not a firſt Table Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian only, we need not draw her Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture with a ſide-face, to hide the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figurement of either ſide, both her hands wrought in the work of God: ſhe did not <hi>claudicare,</hi> but walk'd in his ways with both her Feet. She had learn'd S. <hi>John</hi>'s Leſſon: <hi>That he who loves God, muſt love his Brother alſo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>She was exactly righteous.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>She was prodigiouſly charitable.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>She was exactly juſt in word and
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:41197:50"/>deed.</hi> She never forfeited her <hi>Title,</hi> to the privilege of <hi>Peerage,</hi> to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved upon the <hi>honour</hi> of her <hi>word;</hi> which was, as <hi>ſacred</hi> as any <hi>oath,</hi> and as <hi>good ſecurity</hi> as <hi>many bonds.</hi> No in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience to her ſelf would make her recoil, or flinch from the obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſhe had brought her ſelf under, by her own mouth: yea, ſhe had ſuch an abhorrence of a diſhonourable receſs, from expreſs, or but intimated promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, that it would render her eſteem of ſuch perſons exceeding cheap and mean, who by little arts and ſhifts would looſe and free themſelves from their engagements, and diſappoint the expectations they had raiſed in others, to ſave their charges, accounting their money ſpared, a very poor and baſe redemption of their reputation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>She abhorred a lye;</hi> and us'd modeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to give this teſtimony of her ſelf, <hi>You know I dare not, I will not lie.</hi> And her Lord knew this ſo well, that though he were <hi>poſitive</hi> enough, yet would never perſiſt, if there happened any conteſt, againſt whatever ſhe affirmed peremptorily.</p>
                  <p>And <hi>a lye</hi> was the fouleſt blemiſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny could ſtain themſelves with, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſing
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:41197:50"/>with her, and the moſt <hi>unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable fault,</hi> a ſervant could contract, to whom ſhe us'd to ſay, <hi>Tell me the truth, and I can forgive you any thing.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I ſhall take liberty on this occaſion to add a paſſage, which may be uſeful on a double account:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. To let her Honourable Friends know ſhe forgot them not, though her purpoſes were prevented.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. How ſhe feared the ſhaddow of a lye.</p>
                  <p>About a Month before ſhe died, ſhe was, (though then in as perfect health, as I have known her) determined to <hi>alter her will.</hi> And whereas ſhe had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore given many <hi>honourable Legacies</hi> in <hi>money</hi> to perſons of great Quality: ſhe ſaid, ſhe would <hi>alter them all,</hi> for this reaſon, becauſe they were <hi>rich, and money they needed not:</hi> but ſhe would give it in ſomething they might keep, as <hi>kind memorials</hi> of her: and when ſhe had ſet down all their names in a Paper, ſhe alſo bethought her ſelf what would be moſt acceptable to every of them: <hi>For,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>that renders a gift moſt agreeable, when it ſuits the fancy of the party to whom it is deſigned.</hi> And then ſurveying her own ſtore, ſhe fixed on
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:41197:51"/>what to give to moſt of them, but not finding her ſelf <hi>actually provided,</hi> of what ſhe might <hi>bequeath</hi> to all, ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to leave all to a <hi>Codicil,</hi> to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to her <hi>Will,</hi> and expreſly ſaid,
<q>I am now, <hi>God willing,</hi> going to <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> when I have finiſhed my <hi>Will,</hi> and then I will by diſcourſe find out, <hi>undiſcerned,</hi> what will be moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to every one of them, and will provide accordingly.</q> Yet when the draught of her <hi>Will</hi> was made, ſhe would put into the <hi>Will its ſelf</hi> for the Right Honourable the Counteſs of <hi>Scarſdale</hi> her beloved Siſter-in-law, (who was one of that number to which in her former Will ſhe had given a Legacy in money) <hi>a ſet of ſilver Sconces,</hi> which adorned her own Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. And when I asked her <hi>Ladyſhip</hi> why ſhe would not leave her to the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicil</hi> among the reſt, ſhe was pleaſed to give this reaſon: <hi>Becauſe,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>ſhe is the only perſon living to whom I e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver intimated being in my will, and I would not die, and have it found other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, and ſo be under the ſuſpicion of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving told a lie, or dying with a lye in my mouth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>She</hi> had learn'd S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Leſſon to
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:41197:51"/>perfection, <hi>To ſpeak evil of no man:</hi> and where ſhe could not ſpeak well, the worſt injury ſhe would do was to be ſilent, and ſay nothing, unleſs it were to ſome ſingle Friend, of whoſe Taciturnity ſhe was ſecure by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
                  <p>Nor would ſhe invidiouſly diminiſh the juſt praiſes of any who deſerved them. Nay, would rather ſtudy to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuate their other failings, by preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the light ſide to hide the dark one. And would commend them for one good quality or action, to cover many bad ones: and would ſay, yet I muſt do them this right, they are ſo, or ſo — for all this.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And ſhe was no leſs accurately juſt in deed than word:</hi> ſhe had learn'd to <hi>do,</hi> as well as to <hi>ſay:</hi> ſhe not only gave <hi>goodly</hi> words, but <hi>good performances.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And becauſe the due diſcharge of the duties of our Relations is one of the moſt ſignal evidences of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the greateſt ornament of our Profeſſion of Religion. I ſhall touch briefly how ſhe uſed to acquit her ſelf in that reſpect: as a <hi>Wife</hi> to her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band <hi>living,</hi> as an <hi>Executrix</hi> to his <hi>Will,</hi> and a <hi>Truſtee</hi> to the <hi>Eſtate,</hi> as a
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:41197:52"/>
                     <hi>Mother,</hi> as a <hi>Daughter,</hi> as a <hi>Siſter,</hi> as a <hi>Friend,</hi> as a <hi>Miſtreſs,</hi> as a <hi>Landlady,</hi> as a <hi>Neighbour.</hi> In all which ſhe was as a <hi>ſingular Bleſſing</hi> to her <hi>Relatives,</hi> ſo an eminent example to others.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, as a <hi>Wife. The heart of her Husband did ſafely truſt in her, and ſhe did him good, and not evil all the days of his life.</hi> Never was <hi>woman</hi> more truly a <hi>crown</hi> or <hi>ornament to man.</hi> She al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways lived with a ſenſe of the <hi>covenant of God,</hi> which was betwixt them up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her heart. She was an equal mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of <hi>affectionate obedience,</hi> and <hi>obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diential affection.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>She</hi> would conceal and hide his infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, deeply ſympathiſed in his long indiſpoſitions, attended, and reliev'd him under them with the greateſt ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, loved his Soul, and would both counſel him with prudent zeal, and pray for him with greateſt ardours, and fervency. And he was not want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>in praiſing her.</hi> He hath with ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement proteſtations ſaid to me: <hi>He had rather have her with five thouſand pounds</hi> (though ſhe brought him much more) <hi>than any woman living with twenty.</hi> Yea, when the very Torrents of his Sorrow were higheſt for the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:41197:52"/>death of his only Son (and Family) he made that the circumflexing Accent of his grief: <hi>'twould kill his Wife, which was he ſaid more to him than an hundred Sons: Sed quid verba audiam, cum facta videam: He gave her his whole eſtate, as an honorary teſtimony of his graceful eſteem of her merits towards him,</hi> and left her <hi>ſole Executrix,</hi> a high teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his confidence in her integrity. Which <hi>truſt,</hi> though it coſt her almoſt <hi>unſpeakable labour</hi> and <hi>difficulties,</hi> ſhe diſcharged with ſuch indefatigable pains, ſuch ſcrupulous exactneſs, and admirable prudence, that as ſhe failed not of one Title of the Will, till all was fulfilled; ſo ſhe never gave, or left occaſion of the leaſt noiſe of any complaining, of any intereſted perſon, but rendred all more than <hi>ſilent, ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,</hi> more than <hi>ſatisfied, applauding,</hi> and <hi>admiring</hi> her prudent, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable conduct of that great Affair. Which ſhe owned to God with much thankfulneſs, as no ſmall Mercy and Bleſſing to her. And for that Noble Eſtate which was to deſcend to others after her, ſhe would not have wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it in the leaſt, to have gained the diſpoſal of the whole; and therefore
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:41197:53"/>was at vaſt expences in repairs, both on the Manſion, and Farms, though her ſelf but a Termer. Yea, though none were more ready to recede from their own right, which determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in her own perſonal intereſts; yet would ſhe be ſtiff, and tenacious, in what may concern her Succeſſors: U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually ſaying, whatever ſhe loſt her ſelf, ſhe would never give occaſion to them that came after her, to ſay, ſhe had damnified the Eſtate, or wronged her truſt, or them. I muſt add one particular, becauſe I believe ſhe was the firſt, and will be the laſt inſtance of it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Her noble, ſplendid</hi> way of living (which in moſt is ſacrificing to their vanity and oſtentation) for ſhe lived very great, as you all are witneſſes) was not an act of <hi>pride</hi> or <hi>ambition,</hi> but <hi>purely,</hi> at leaſt <hi>principally,</hi> of <hi>conſcience;</hi> ſhe would not contract, or abate, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe would not deceive her Lord's truſt, who gave her the Eſtate to keep up the honour of his Name and Family in a place where it had flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and in that kind been famous ſo many years.</p>
                  <p>She was a moſt incomparable Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:41197:53"/>which appeared in the education of one Son of her Body, and three Daughters of her Soul; for ſo I may truly ſpeak. She never bare more than two Children; one Daughter, who died young, and a Son, the gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant, hopeful, young Lord <hi>Rich,</hi> of whom the world hath had an account, by the ſame hand which hath had the unhappy honour to be employed the third time in this mournful Service: <hi>Planctus unigeniti</hi> at the Lord <hi>Rich</hi>'s Funeral: <hi>Leez lachrymans</hi> at the Earl of <hi>Warwick</hi>'s: and this.</p>
                  <p>The pious methods of whoſe educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion might be ſuggeſted with advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, but I ſhould never have done, ſhould I allow my ſelf liberty to enlarge on all was commendable, or exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary; yet one thing I will not conceal; thoſe three <hi>excellent Ladies</hi> to whom ſhe was an <hi>own Mother,</hi> though but an <hi>Aunt-in-law,</hi> and who are by their Couſins death become ſo vaſt fortunes to their Husbands, being left with leſs plentiful portions, ſhe would even du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring her Son's life, never leave preſſing her Lord to make noble proviſions for, and ſettle their <hi>portions</hi> ſuitable to their <hi>Birth</hi> and <hi>Qualities,</hi> which as they well
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:41197:54"/>knew, ſo I doubt not but they will moſt readily atteſt with becoming acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgments, as alſo all the other never to be forgotten obligations, which ſhe ſo nobly ceaſed not, to pleaſe her kind humour, in conferring on them.</p>
                  <p>I never perſonally ſaw her Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Father, nor could remember her dutiful obſervances of him; but this I know, that engagements o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> her own affections would not ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſede her reſpects to him in her mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, till his full conſent and approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was obtained.</p>
                  <p>And no Child could make more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable mention of Parents than I have heard her do of hers, and for the tranſmitting it to poſterity, I cannot ſay ſhe had reſolved to write and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh her Father's Life; but I can, and do affirm, ſhe had it in deliberation, and had conſiderable materials, and Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections, many of which ſhe hath diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed, and read to me, or given me the favour to read my ſelf.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>She</hi> was ſo endearing a Siſter, no language can expreſs it; and therefore it would be inexcuſable boldneſs for me to attempt it.</p>
                  <p>A <hi>Friend</hi> ſo <hi>faithful,</hi> ſo <hi>kind,</hi> ſo <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant,</hi>
                     <pb n="95" facs="tcp:41197:54"/>ſo <hi>condeſcending,</hi> ſo <hi>open,</hi> ſo <hi>free, unreſerved, unſuſpicious,</hi> as I believe is not to be found on earth. I could give inſtance of a Friendſhip, which as ſhe vouchſafed to contract with much condeſcention on her part, continued thirty years, not only without inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, or Eclipſe, but without the leaſt cloud or ſhaddow of miſunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding on either ſide for that long ſpace.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The beſt Miſtreſs in the world,</hi> to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt a Proverb, in a double care, both of the ſpiritual and bodily welfare of her ſervants, whom ſhe as much loved to pleaſe, as other perſons ſervants can do to pleaſe their Maſters, it being her peculiar delight to render the lives of all eaſie and pleaſant, and free from diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content, that they might ſerve God with chearfulneſs. And when ſhe was to leave them, ſhe left not off her kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to them, or care for them, but provided to the uttermoſt of her power, for their comfortable ſubſiſtence, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their degree and time of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, giving Legacies <hi>liberal and noble, four hundred pounds, three hundred pounds, two hundred pounds</hi> a piece, to ſome, one <hi>hundred pound</hi> a piece to
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:41197:55"/>many, to others eighty, to many ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty, to buy them Annuities or their lives; to others fifty, forty, twenty, and a full years wages to every one not ſpecified by name, and three Months Entertainment, with Lodging, Diet, and all accommodations, as in her life; that they might have time to ſeek out, and provide places for themſelves, and not be expoſed to inconveniences, by a ſudden remove.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>She was a moſt noble,</hi> I may ſay, <hi>indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Lanlady,</hi> and would uſually ſay of her Tenants, Alas, poor creatures, they take a great deal of pains, and I love to ſee them <hi>thrive,</hi> and <hi>live com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably,</hi> and I cannot endure to ſee them brought into ſtraits, and therefore would without grudging or difficulty have all things made convenient for them, and if they had ſuſtained any conſiderable loſſes, effectually conſider it. And for her Copy-hold Tenants, would urge with warmth the timely finiſhing the Rolls of her Courts, and delivery of their Copies, profeſſing ſhe could not in conſcience ſuffer it to be neglected, becauſe it was all they had to ſhew for their Eſtates, a piece of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent juſtice, not more honourable
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:41197:55"/>than neceſſary in Lords of Mannors.</p>
                  <p>And laſtly, as a <hi>Neighbour,</hi> ſhe was ſo kind and courteous, it advanced the Rent of adjacent Houſes to be ſo near ſituated to her, not only her Houſe, and Table, but her Countenance and very heart were open to all perſons of Quality in a conſiderable circuit, and for the inferiour ſort, if they were ſick, or tempted, or in any diſtreſs of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy or Mind, whither ſhould they go but to the good Counteſs whoſe Cloſet and Still-houſe was their Shop for Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgery, and Phyſick, and her ſelf, (for ſhe would viſit the meaneſt of them perſonally) and Miniſters whom ſhe would ſend to them, their ſpiritual Phyſicians. But as her love to God was the ſoul of her Religion, ſo the exuberancy of her charity towards thoſe who needed her abundant libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, was the conſpicuous Crown which beautified all her ſweetneſs, and goodneſs towards Men: for in this ſhe was <hi>forward, I bear her record, to her power, yea, and beyond her power;</hi> for ſhe would even anticipate her Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue and Incomes, rather than want wherewith to be liberal. S. <hi>Jerom</hi> pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the higheſt rank of the praiſes
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:41197:56"/>of his admired <hi>Paula,</hi> that ſhe not only made her ſelf poor to relieve, but died in <hi>magno Aere alieno:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">S. Hier. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitaphium</hi> Paulae.</note> And I am ſure it uſed to be ſaid of our excellent: Lady, <hi>That was the Lady that would borrow mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to give away:</hi> She would not <hi>live poor</hi> (in good works) to <hi>dye rich,</hi> yea, though ſhe had choſen Executors, in whom her heart could truſt as ſafely as ever her Husbands did in her, yet ſhe would make her own hands her Executors, and they were very faithful, to her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged heart.</p>
                  <p>But to be more particular; when ſhe had in her Lord and Husbands life time, a ſeparate maintenance or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance, ſettled by Marriage Articles, ſhe was pleaſed to ask me my opinion concerning the <hi>quota pars:</hi> What pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion one is obliged to conſecrate to God of our Eſtates, and when I told her it was hard, if not impoſſible, to fix a Rule which might hold univerſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; but the circumſtances muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in which perſons ſtood, their Qualities, their Incomes, their Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendances, neceſſary and emergent Occaſions, inevitably occurring—But ſhe perſiſting to urge a more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular anſwer as to her ſelf, what would
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:41197:56"/>be fit and becoming her to do, I not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ignorant of her circumſtances, (I muſt bear my own ſhame in acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging the ſtraitneſs of my own heart, told her) I ſuppoſed a ſeventh part: But before I could ſuggeſt the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, ſhe preventingly replied, ſhe would never give leſs than the third part, and ſhe kept her reſolution to the full and with advantage; laying aſide conſtantly the <hi>third part</hi> for charitable uſes, and would ſometimes borrow of that which remained to add to it, but never defaulk from that to ſerve her own occaſions, though ſometimes preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing enough.</p>
                  <p>When ſhe came to the poſſeſſion of ſo large an Eſtate as her Lord bequeath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her for her life, ſhe in good meaſure made it true, what a great Perſon was reported to ſay; that the Earl of <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick</hi> had gave all his Eſtate to pious u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: Meaning thereby, that he had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it to this Noble Lady, who would ſo convert it.</p>
                  <p>And 'tis a great truth, which I have had from her own mouth, that all the ſatisfaction ſhe took in it, was the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity it afforded her of doing good. And I have heard her earneſtly averr,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:41197:57"/>that ſhe would not accept of, or be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbred with the greateſt Eſtate in <hi>England,</hi> if it ſhould be offered her, clog'd with this condition, not to do good to others with it.</p>
                  <p>But ſome may ſay, were her <hi>Eyes</hi> as open as her <hi>Hands,</hi> did ſhe not ſcatter it as <hi>careleſly</hi> as <hi>profuſely?</hi> Nothing leſs, <hi>her liberal Soul deviſed liberal things:</hi> I will point at ſome few of many.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. There are ſome <hi>Objects</hi> of <hi>real Charity,</hi> which are not ſo to <hi>vulgar Eyes</hi> or <hi>Purſes;</hi> on whom ſhe would confer, and whom ſhe would ſurpriſe, with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ſuitable aſſiſtances, this ſtruck deep, drew an whole bag at once, but made no noiſe.</p>
                  <p>Some ſcarcely known to any but my ſelf, and it may be had not been to me, but to ask my judgment, whether it might be reduced to the account of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, to give to ſuch and ſuch, being in ſuch circumſtances: For ſhe was never leſs tender of their modeſty than com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate of their neceſſity, and was more ſollicitous for their pardon, than their thanks, for helping them.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Foreiners</hi> who fled either to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve their Religion, or to embrace what they were convinced of to be the truth.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="101" facs="tcp:41197:57"/>3. A <hi>great many young Scholars</hi> of hopeful promiſing Parts, whom ſhe wholly or in good meaſure educated at the Univerſity, allowing ſome thirty, ſome twenty, ſome ten, ſome eight, many five Pounds <hi>per Annum,</hi> and ſome others who had more aſſiſtance, leſs.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Abundance of young Children which ſhe put to School in the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Towns, I cannot ſay how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, but rather <hi>ſans</hi> number, all that were poor and willing to learn: Nay; that could be perſwaded to it, whoſe Schooling ſhe did not only pay for, but gave them both Books and often Cloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and not only near home but as far as <hi>Wales,</hi> contributing nobly to that pious deſign, of that good old man and indefatigable promoter of it Mr. <hi>Gouge,</hi> ſo <hi>amply atteſted by a Cloud of Witneſſes,</hi> beyond exception, to reſcue <hi>Wales</hi> from its remaining ignorance and demi-Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bariſm.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Many <hi>Miniſters</hi> of both denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, as well <hi>Conformiſts</hi> whoſe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings were ſo ſmall as not to yield them a ſubſiſtance, as thoſe who had none at all.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Many <hi>occaſional Objects of Charity,</hi> which you may ſurely conclude, failed
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:41197:58"/>not to ply at thoſe Stairs where 'twas ſeldom low water: And though ſhe was ſometimes impoſed upon, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by thoſe that neither needed nor deſerved what ſhe gave, yet this did not diſcourage her from giving again: For ſhe ſaid, ſhe had rather relieve ten that only appeared meet objects and were not, than let one go unrelieved who was ſo indeed: For though they deceived her in her giving, God would not deceive her in accepting, what was ſincerely done for his Name ſake.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. <hi>Laſtly, the Poor</hi> which ſhe fed in great number, not only with fragments and broken meat, but with liberal provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion purpoſely made for them. She was a great pitier, yea a great lover of the poor, and ſhe built a convenient houſe on purpoſe for them at her <hi>London</hi>-Seat, (as they had one at <hi>Leez</hi>) to ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them from rain and heat while they received their dole, and when ſhe was at <hi>London</hi> with her Family, had in her abſence, whilſt no houſe was kept at <hi>Leez,</hi> a kind of houſe kept for their ſakes alone: That is, twice a week, good Beef and Bread provided for the poor of four adjacent Pariſhes, and hath
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:41197:58"/>taken order in her Will to have the ſame continued three months after her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe, and by the ſame Will hath given an hundred pounds to be diſtributed to the Poor of <hi>Braintree, Felſted, Little-Leez,</hi> and <hi>Much-Waltham,</hi> at or ſhortly after her Funeral.</p>
                  <p>And though it cannot reaſonably be expected from one who had no Lands of Inheritance, to leave charitable foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations. Yet I may, without <hi>Hyperbole,</hi> ſay, that every year ſhe lived, after ſhe came to be Miſtreſs of the Eſtate, ſhe gave as much in charity as would have purchaſed Lands ſufficient to have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed an Alms-houſe or Free-ſchool. And that pious and liberal foundation of <hi>Rochford</hi> Alms-houſe, which though founded legally by a Patent granted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Broad Seal for its confirmation, by the Anceſtors of that Family, of which ſhe bore the Title; was by the death of the Founder, not endowed, yet as all her predeceſſors had done.</p>
                  <p>She always paid the Alms-people their full deſigned Allowance, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by her laſt Will it ſhould be ſo done for a year after her deceaſe. And I muſt here take leave to add, to their great honour, and the ſatisfaction of all
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:41197:59"/>that relate to that Family, that thoſe Right Honourable and worthy perſons, to whom the eſtate deſcends, have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed to continue the ſame plentiful al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance: And if I were worthy to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe them, I would earneſtly perſwade them to make Legal Settlement, and endow it with Lands to the value of what they reſolve to allow, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they make the diviſion of the Eſtate.</p>
                  <p>But methinks I hear it asked, what! had ſhe no <hi>Spots,</hi> no <hi>Scars,</hi> no <hi>real</hi> nor <hi>imputed Blemiſhes?</hi> how could ſhe live in ſuch an Age and not be <hi>corrupted</hi> or at leaſt <hi>traduced?</hi> neither <hi>ſcorched</hi> by the <hi>fire</hi> of infection, nor <hi>blackned</hi> by the <hi>ſmoak</hi> of <hi>revengeful detraction,</hi> for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braiding the guilty by her innocency? This <hi>overdoing</hi> is <hi>undoing,</hi> if you would make us <hi>believe</hi> ſhe had no <hi>faults,</hi> we ſhall ſooner <hi>believe</hi> you have no <hi>truth:</hi> And that all you have ſaid hath more of <hi>Romance,</hi> and what you <hi>fancy,</hi> than <hi>Narrative</hi> of what ſhe <hi>was</hi> or <hi>did.</hi> I confeſs 'tis next to a miracle to conſider, both how divine Grace enlarged her heart, and eſtabliſhed her goings, and reſtrained the tongues of others from reproaching, or ſhewing diſlike of that
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:41197:59"/>in her, for which they deride and hate, not to ſay perſecute others.</p>
                  <p>But I muſt implore that <hi>candour</hi> while I embalm her memory, with the ſweet <hi>Oyntment</hi> of her own good name, you granted to her <hi>vertues,</hi> which acquired it, and made it ſo fragrant.</p>
                  <p>I therefore ſolemnly proteſt, I have ſpoke the truth <hi>(though the truth in love,</hi> as I am allowed and requir'd <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.15.) and have not knowingly diſguiſed or falſified, nor dipt my pen in flattering colours.</p>
                  <p>But ſince you are ſo inquiſitive, and ſeem to deny me the juſt and civil free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, to draw a veil of ſilence over her imperfections, and your <hi>curioſity</hi> will be <hi>peeping</hi> under that <hi>ſacred Pall,</hi> which ſhould <hi>ſecure</hi> and <hi>ſhroud</hi> the worſt of men from being pryed into; and the <hi>Vault,</hi> and <hi>Grave,</hi> that place of darkneſs and forgetfulneſs, which ſhould bury all defects and render them inviſible, muſt be ranſack'd: <hi>Draw back the Curtains, let in the light,</hi> ſurvey its ſecreteſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes; nor <hi>She,</hi> nor <hi>I</hi> in her behalf, fear the moſt piercing Eagle-eye or Scent: Nor that I deny her to have been a <hi>Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> while I adore that Grace that made her a <hi>Saint,</hi> or that ſhe was a <hi>Woman,</hi>
                     <pb n="106" facs="tcp:41197:60"/>while I proclaim her a <hi>Terreſtrial Angel.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But theſe three things I ſay, and will adhere to.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, That ſhe was not notoriouſly defective in any Grace or Vertue, but as eminent in all as moſt have been for any ſingle one: She was not only <hi>aliquid in omnibus,</hi> but <hi>omnis in ſingulis,</hi> ſhe did abound in every grace. Which St. <hi>Gregory Naz.</hi> admires in <hi>Gorgonia,</hi> and St. <hi>Jerom</hi> in <hi>Nepotian: Ita in ſingulis virtutibus eminebat, quaſi caeteras non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beret.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> She was never <hi>ſtained</hi> with any ſcandalous deformity, another rare mercy: For though ſhe did <hi>humanum pati, ſlip</hi> now and then, or <hi>ſtumble</hi> if you will; ſhe <hi>fell</hi> not, much leſs <hi>lay</hi> or <hi>wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed</hi> to defile her Garments, which I teſtifie not only from my own obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but her own Pen.</p>
                  <p>
                     <q>After God had thus ſavingly (I hope) wrought upon me, I went on conſtantly, comfortably in my Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian courſe, though I had many doubts and fears to contend with: And did truly obey that Precept of working out my Salvation with fear
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:41197:60"/>and trembling, yet God was pleaſed to carry me ſtill onward: And though I too often broke my good reſolutions, I never renounced them, and though I too often tript in my Journey to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, yet I never forſook my purpoſe of going thither.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Her very <hi>defects</hi> and <hi>fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> were ſuch as others might be <hi>proud</hi> of, her <hi>Weeds</hi> would have been <hi>Flowers,</hi> and her <hi>Thiſtles</hi> appeared <hi>Roſes</hi> in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Garden.</p>
                  <p>For I never heard her blamed for more than <hi>two faults,</hi> by the moſt curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous obſervers and inſpectors of her diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition or behaviour.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Exceſs of Charity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Defect of Anger,</hi> or what was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceable to thoſe two, two goodly faults: But even theſe admit Apology more eaſily than they need it.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. What was reputed the culpable exceſs of her <hi>Charity,</hi> was her credulous eaſineſs, to believe moſt people <hi>good,</hi> or at leaſt <hi>better</hi> than they were. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs ſhe did bend a little to this right hand error, but if it were a <hi>bad effect,</hi> it proceeded from a <hi>good cauſe.</hi> For as 'tis obſerved, that as they who are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:41197:61"/>to themſelves of ſome great e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, ſcarce can eſteem any leſs <hi>nocent</hi> than themſelves; ſo they that have clear and <hi>innocent</hi> hearts, are ready to judge the like of others. <hi>Charity think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no evil,</hi> and ſhe uſed this good opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of others, as an inſtrument to make them what ſhe was ſo willing to ſignifie ſhe thought them: And though ſhe would never <hi>deſpair</hi> of any man, while ſhe found them under the <hi>Awe</hi> of <hi>Gods Authority</hi> and <hi>Word,</hi> for even thoſe may receive ſome nouriſhment, who eat againſt Stomach, and the Seive under the Pump may be cleanſed though it hold no water; yet if ſhe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved a perſon to ſcorn or deride the Scriptures, deſpiſe Gods Ordinances, and turn all that was ſacred into ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cule—<hi>She uſed,</hi> as her Phraſe was, <hi>to ſet her mark upon that man:</hi> And I muſt further add, She was neither ſo <hi>often</hi> nor ſo <hi>much</hi> miſtaken in her judgment of perſons, as ſome ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſhe was; they more miſ-interpret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her civility, than ſhe did the others ſanctity.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. For her <hi>Defect of Anger,</hi> which implies, if it be faulty, <hi>want of zeal againſt ſin, and ſinners,</hi> and ſo 'tis an
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:41197:61"/>unjuſt charge; for though I confeſs ſhe could not rage and ſtorm, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover her anger, as ſome perſons do, who verifie the ſaying, <hi>Ira furor brevis, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is a kind of madneſs;</hi> for her <hi>ſedate, compoſed, ſerene mind,</hi> and <hi>ſweet,</hi> and <hi>amicable diſpoſition</hi> was ſcarce forcible to what was ſo contrary to her nature; yet would ſhe make deeper impreſſions of her diſpleaſure for great faults, than thoſe who appeared moſt furious, like a ſtill ſoaking ſhower, which will wet more than a driving ſtorm. And therefore 'twas obſerv'd, that if any ſervant had been faulty, they had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have paſſed the Gantlet thrice of their Lord's moſt furious expreſſions, than have once been ſent for to their <hi>Lady's Cloſet,</hi> whoſe treatment was <hi>ſoft words,</hi> but <hi>hard arguments</hi> againſt their <hi>faults,</hi> and like that ſilent lightning, which without the noiſe of Thunder melts the Blade, and ſindgeth not the Scabbard; neither the <hi>frightful hiſſing,</hi> nor the <hi>venom'd ſting,</hi> but the <hi>penetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting oil of Scorpions.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This little is enough to extenuate her, almoſt commendable faults; and 'tis a great evidence of her goodneſs, that theſe things were imputed as Ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:41197:62"/>for they who would not ſpare her in theſe little errors, ſhewed plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that ſhe was not chargeable with more or greater.</p>
                  <p>I am now arrived at the laſt Stage of this Mournful Journey, to give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of her ſurpriſing, and never e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough lamented death.</p>
                  <p>What preſages ſhe might have of its near approach ſhe never diſcovered, but her preparations for it had been long habitual, it was one of the moſt conſtant ſubjects of her thinking, and ſhe uſed to call her walking to medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate of it, her going to <hi>take a turn with death,</hi> and it could never <hi>ſurpriſe, or take her unprepared, who was always pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring for it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Yet there are ſome paſſages, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of our remarks of the <hi>watchful kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of <hi>Divine Providence</hi> over his <hi>own,</hi> allarming them to trim their Lamps (as the wiſe Virgins did) againſt the coming of the Bridegroom, and allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them fit opportunities to do it, as he ſignally did to her.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall on this conſideration very ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably add another Tranſcript out of her Ladyſhips Diary, which contains an account of the laſt Sunday of her
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:41197:62"/>health, being written but the very day before ſhe was taken ill, and in which <hi>God</hi> did, it ſeems, in a moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable manner, <hi>impreſs</hi> the thoughts of her approaching <hi>diſſolution</hi> on her Soul, though there were no viſible ſymptoms of it then upon her Body.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>March</hi> 24. <hi>Sunday.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <p>AS ſoon as I awaked, I bleſſed God; then I meditated and endeavoured by thinking of ſome of the great mercies of my life, to ſtir up my heart to return Glory to God. And thoſe thoughts had this effect upon me, to melt my heart much by God's love, and to warm it with love to him.</p>
                     <p>Then I prayed, and I was enabled in that duty to pour out my Soul to God, and my heart was in it, carried out to praiſe God, and I was large in recounting of many of God's ſpecial mercies to me. And whilſt I was doing ſo, I found God mighty upon my ſpirit and my heart, in a much more than ordinary manner, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:41197:63"/>out to admire God for his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and to love him. And I found his love make great impreſſions in my Breaſt. And melting me into an unuſual plenty of tears.</p>
                     <p>Thoſe mercies which in an eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al manner I was grateful for, were the Creation and Redemption of the World, and for the Goſpel and the Sacraments, and for free Grace, and the Covenant of Grace, and for the excellent means of it I had enjoyed: and for the great patience God hath exerciſed towards me before and ſince my Converſion. And for checks of Conſcience when I had ſinned, and for repentance when I had done ſo. And for a ſanctified af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, and ſupports under it. And for ſo large a portion of worldly Bleſſings.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <q>After I had begged a Bleſſing upon the publick Ordinances, I went to hear Mr. <hi>Woodroof:</hi> his Text was, <hi>Paſs the time of your ſojourning here in fear</hi>— Then after a ſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry account of the Sermon, follows: In the Afternoon I heard again the ſame Perſon upon the ſame Text.</q> And then follows a conciſe and metho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dical
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:41197:63"/>recapitulation of that Sermon al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. "And after that—
<q>I was in a ſerious and affected frame at both the Sermons, and was by them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of the excellency of fearing God, and of ſpending of the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the term of my life in his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. And did reſolve to endeavour to ſpend the remaining part of my time better.</q>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <p>At both his Prayers I prayed with fervency: afterwards I retired, and meditated upon the Sermons, and prayed them over.</p>
                     <p>And I had alſo this Evening large Meditations of Death, and of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; which thoughts had this effect upon me, to make me in an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary awakened frame, in which the things of another life were much realized to me, and did make very deep impreſſions upon me. And my <hi>Soul</hi> did <hi>follow hard after God,</hi> for Grace to ſerve him better than ever yet I had done.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>O Lord be pleaſed to hear my Prayers, which did not come out of fained Lips: and to hear the voice of my weeping, for more holineſs, and for being more wean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the world, and all things in it.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="114" facs="tcp:41197:64"/>
                     <p>After Supper, I committed my ſelf to God.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>This was written the very laſt day of her health, Monday Morning: in which we ſee how God realized to her, and gave her extraordinary impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Death, Eternity, and the Life to come, when he was about to bring her to it; for the very next day ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be ill of that Sickneſs of which ſhe died.</p>
                  <p>Our <hi>excellent Lady</hi> was far from their humour whoſe <hi>Conſciences</hi> are ſo <hi>bad</hi> and <hi>unquiet</hi> company, that they hate ſolitude, and dare not be alone: For ſhe loved, and even hugged her retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as her greateſt ſatisfactions. And though, when ſhe was called to it, ſhe would deny her ſelf and particular in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination (as in the Univerſe Individuals do, to obey the laws of univerſal Nature) to comply with a duty of a larger ſpread; as is related of the devout Marqueſs of <hi>Renti</hi> in the two years time he ſpent in repairing the ſeat of his Anceſtors, which diverſion he cheerfully ſuffered as a willing mortification, being a duty he owed to the Station in which God had placed him.</p>
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:41197:64"/>
                  <p>So <hi>ſhe</hi> chearfully ſuſtained the <hi>hurry</hi> of buſineſs which was inevitable to the acquitting her ſelf of the truſt repoſed in her, by her Lords laſt Will.</p>
                  <p>But never did Bird take Wing, when diſ-intangled from a Net, with greater cheerfulneſs, nor chirp out the pleaſures of its unconfined freedom, more mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily than ſhe did ſolace her ſelf, when ſhe had eſcaped the noiſe and croud of affairs, which ruffled and turmoyled her quiet, and ſuſpended the enjoyment of her ſelf. And when her deareſt Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter was in the beginning of the laſt winter, about to leave her; her laſt farewel ſhe took was in theſe words: Now I have done my <hi>drudgery</hi> (meaning her buſineſs) I will ſet to the renewing of my preparations for <hi>Eternity,</hi> and ſhe made it the repeated buſineſs of the laſt winter.</p>
                  <p>In the beginning of the laſt <hi>March,</hi> ſhe ſet to the making of her Will anew, and ſigned and ſealed it on the twelfth day of the ſame Month, and on the Tueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day in Paſſion Week, <hi>March</hi> 26. was taken with ſome indiſpoſition, loſs of Appetite, and aguiſh diſtemper, and had four or five Fits, which yet in that ſeaſon were judged both by Phyſicians
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:41197:65"/>and her Friends, more advantageous to her health than dangerous to her life. And in this ſtate ſhe continued freed from her fits in her own apprehenſion, and in our hopes, till Friday the twelfth of <hi>April,</hi> on which day ſhe roſe with good ſtrength, and after ſitting up ſome time, being laid upon her Bed, diſcourſing cheerfully, and piouſly, one of the laſt ſentences ſhe ſpake was this, turning back the Curtain with her hand,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Well, Ladies, if I were one hour in Heaven, I would not be again with you, as well as I love you.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Having then received a kind viſit from a Neighbouring Lady, at her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture ſhe roſe from her Bed to her Chair, in which being ſet, ſhe ſaid ſhe would go into her Bed, but firſt would deſire one of the Miniſters then in the houſe to go to prayer with her, and asking the company which they would have, preſently reſolv'd her ſelf to have him who was going away, becauſe the other would ſtay and pray with her dayly; and immediately he being called, and come, her Ladyſhip
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:41197:65"/>ſitting in her Chair, by reaſon of her weakneſs, for otherwiſe ſhe always kneeled, holding an Orange in her hand, to which ſhe ſmelt, almoſt in the beginning of the Prayer ſhe was heard to fetch a <hi>ſigh,</hi> or <hi>groan,</hi> which was eſteemed <hi>devotional,</hi> as ſhe uſed to do at other times. But a Lady looking up, who kneeled by her, ſaw her look pale, and her hand hang down, at which ſhe ſtarted up, affrighted, and all applyed themſelves to help, and the moſt afflictively diſtreſſed of them all, if I may ſo ſpeak, when all our ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows were ſuperlative, catch'd her right hand, which then had loſt it's pulſe, and never recovered it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</p>
                  <p>Thus lived, thus died this Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Lady, this Heroick Woman, this Bleſſed Saint, <hi>this incomparable pattern of flaming zeal for the glory of God, and burning charity for the good of men;</hi> in the actual <hi>exerciſe of prayer,</hi> by which ſhe ſo often <hi>anticipated Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> by <hi>preguſtation,</hi> and which now <hi>wafted</hi> her longing ſoul into the <hi>Holy of Holies, within the vail:</hi> at the <hi>kiſs of God's mouth,</hi> as <hi>Moſes</hi> did, though not
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:41197:66"/>
                     <hi>full</hi> of years, yet full of mature <hi>fruits,</hi> and <hi>Graces,</hi> when all men judged her worthy of a <hi>longer,</hi> but God, the only unerring Judge, found her full ripened for a <hi>better life.</hi> And in a ſweeter <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſia</hi> than <hi>Auguſtus</hi> could wiſh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, might claim a more triumphant <hi>Plaudite</hi> than he. Yea, might have ſung her <hi>Nunc demittis</hi> with good old <hi>Simeon,</hi> nay, with the holy Apoſtle, that <hi>joyful Epinichion, I have fought a good Fight, I have finiſhed my courſe, I have kept the faith, henceforth there is laid up for me a crown of righteouſneſs, which the Lord the righteous Judge ſhall give me at that day, and not to me only, but unto them alſo that love his appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>You have heard, though too too dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, how ſhe <hi>ſerv'd</hi> and <hi>honoured God,</hi> I ſhould now ſhew to encourage you to do the like, how he <hi>honoured her,</hi> according to his word by <hi>Samuel: Him that honours me, I will honour.</hi> And that of our Saviour, <hi>He that ſerveth me, him will my Father honour.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But I have much prevented my ſelf by what is interwoven through all the preceding diſcourſe: <hi>The greateſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:41197:66"/>God can put upon his creatures, is to vouchſafe to uſe them, and to make them Veſſels of Honour, fitted for their Maſter's ſervice.</hi> And this he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred upon her in eminent and redou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled meaſures. He imprinted on her the <hi>faireſt impreſs</hi> of his moſt <hi>amiable Image,</hi> and rendred her habile, and ready to <hi>every good word and work.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He gave</hi> her <hi>riches, and honour in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance,</hi> as is ſaid of <hi>Jehoſophat,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 17.5, 6.</note> and yet her heart was not puffed up by them, but <hi>lifted up under them in the ways of the Lord,</hi> as it there follows.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He gave</hi> her the <hi>Heaven upon earth,</hi> (after ſome ſhivering ſcruples, and trembling fears) the bleſſed <hi>calm</hi> of a <hi>purified, pacified, ſerene,</hi> and <hi>well-aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured conſcience.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He gave</hi> her the <hi>fragrant</hi> perfume of an odoriferous name, and more than <hi>unſpotted,</hi> a <hi>bright,</hi> and <hi>reſplendent</hi> reputation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He gave</hi> her many endeared Cordial Friends, faithful to her as her own Soul, to aſſiſt, counſel, comfort, help her, and carry her through her great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt difficulties, and entangling affairs, concerning one of whom ſhe us'd of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with much thankfulneſs to ſay, <hi>He
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:41197:67"/>was a Friend of God Almighty's giving;</hi> even beyond her own expectation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He gave</hi> her many merciful delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, one very like to that <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> inſiſts ſo largely on in his Funeral Oration for his Siſter <hi>Gorgonia,</hi> the Mules in whoſe Chariot running away, not only <hi>bruiſed,</hi> but <hi>brake</hi> her Bones, and yet God miraculouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor'd her. So when the Horſes in our Lady's Coach excuſſed the Coach-man, ran furiouſly away, God almoſt mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly hung the Coach againſt a Poſt in the way, ſtopped their fury, reſcued her life from moſt eminent hazard, and healed the bruiſes ſhe received with ſafety. This happened <hi>July,</hi> 23. 1661.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He gave</hi> her the <hi>affectionate eſteem</hi> of all her <hi>Neighbours,</hi> to ſuch a degree, that ſhe was like <hi>Titus, Deliciae humani generis, the delight and darling of her Country,</hi> and with ſo loving a willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs did they delight to ſerve her, that you might ſee fifty freſh, brave and gallant Teams, day after day bringing in her proviſions, without other invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation than the bare knowledge of the time, which themſelves would enquire out; and nothing would grieve them
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:41197:67"/>more, than to be prevented in pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Tribute of Honorary Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He gave</hi> her ſuch an eſteem for her prudent integrity, and diſcreet, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Righteouſneſs, that ſhe began to be (an employ and honour not uſual to her Sex) the <hi>Arbitreſs</hi> and <hi>Umpreſs</hi> of all the controverſies amongſt adja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Neighbours, many of which ſhe reconciled happily, and all which ſhe decided wiſely and juſtly.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He gave her</hi> the univerſal <hi>approbation, love, admiration</hi> of all that knew her, that the Proverb was confuted, which ſaith, <hi>Who hath no Enemies, hath no Friends.</hi> For either ſhe had none, or her <hi>ways ſo pleaſed the Lord, he made her Enemies to be at peace with her.</hi> For <hi>honourable,</hi> and <hi>mean, rich,</hi> and <hi>poor,</hi> of all <hi>degrees,</hi> and which is more, of all <hi>perſwaſions,</hi> paid her moſt kind re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, honoured, and lov'd her.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Finally, he prevented her with the bleſſing of goodneſs, and crown'd her with loving kindneſs, and tender mercy. He made her glad with the light of his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and ſatisfied her as with mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and fatneſs; he granted the requeſts of her lips, and ſhut not out her prayer:</hi>
                     <pb n="122" facs="tcp:41197:68"/>He gave her ability, and time to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge her truſt, and ſettle her world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affairs with honour and ſatisfaction, and he gave her opportunity, ſpace, and an heart to recollect her ſelf, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem what a hurry of buſineſs had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived her of, and renew her evidences for Heaven.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He</hi> took out the <hi>ſting</hi> of <hi>death</hi> before ſhe <hi>died,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Intelligeres illam non e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mori, ſed emigrare, &amp; mutare amicos non relinquene.</hi> Hierom.</note> and the <hi>pains</hi> of <hi>death</hi> when ſhe <hi>died,</hi> and with a kiſs of his mouth ſucked up her Soul to Heaven, to be immerſed in that <hi>fulneſs of joy, and bathed in thoſe rivers of pleaſure, which are at his right hand for evermore.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>May we live like her, may we die like her, that we may live with her, and with our common Lord, for ever.</p>
                  <p>And for your noble Lordſhip, who are now inveſting your ſelf with her large and noble Mantle—<hi>May Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jah's ſpirit reſt upon you, as well as his Mantle:</hi> that you may riſe up an <hi>Eliſha</hi> in her place and ſtead.</p>
                  <p>That <hi>Leez</hi> may be <hi>Leez</hi> ſtill: the <hi>ſeat of Nobleneſs, and Honour, the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpital of Bounty, and Charity, the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary of Religion, and the fear of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:41197:68"/>
                  <p>That ſo you may live, and may <hi>live longer,</hi> and as <hi>much deſired,</hi> and when you die (as die you muſt, for <hi>Leez,</hi> though a Paradiſe, hath no Tree of Life) you may die <hi>later,</hi> and <hi>as much lamented</hi> as your Noble Predeceſſors.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:41197:69"/>
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:41197:69"/>
                  <head>A Copy of that Excellent and Pious Letter, written to the Right Honourable <hi>George</hi> Lord <hi>Berkeley;</hi> by the <hi>Right Honourable</hi> Mary, late Counteſs Dowager of <hi>Warwick,</hi> of which Intimation is given in the <hi>48 page</hi> of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Diſcourſe.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Lord,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>IN obedience to your Commands I have undertaken that which I know I am very unfit to perform; which is, to give your Lordſhip Rules for holy living. Yet becauſe your Lordſhips Friendſhip makes you ſo
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:41197:70"/>kind, as to believe what is ſaid by me, will make a deeper impreſſion than by others who have not ſo great a ſhare in your Lordſhips eſteem; I have ventured upon it, not to inform you, as one I believe ignorant, (for I know your Lordſhip to be very much better able to inſtruct me) but to put your Lordſhip in mind, <hi>That not the knower of the Law, but the doer of it ſhall be juſtified;</hi> and that, <hi>If you know theſe things, happy are you if you do them. For he that knows his maſters will, and doth it not, ſhall be beaten with many ſtripes.</hi> I will begin my firſt Rule of Advice to your Lordſhip, with deſiring you not to turn the day into night, and by ſleeping ſo long in the morning, give your ſelf only time in haſte to put on your clothes, and it may be ſometimes with more haſte ſay a ſhort formal prayer to ſtop the mouth of a natural Conſcience, which for haſte you hardly mind your ſelf, and therefore have little reaſon to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect God ſhould. Therefore I ſhall adviſe your Lordſhip to go to bed in ſo good an hour at night, as that you may wake in ſo good time, as you may not loſe the morning, which certainly
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:41197:70"/>is the beſt time for the Service of God. And I would have you as ſoon as you wake, fix your thoughts upon that God that gives you time to think, and do as Holy <hi>David</hi> did, who ſaid, <hi>As ſoon as I awake, I am with thee.</hi> Conſider how your Bed might have been your Grave, for many every night go down into the place of ſilence, and there take their long and laſt ſleep. Conſider alſo what a mercy ſleep is, and if we miſs but a nights reſt, how burdenſome and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie a man would be to himſelf; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore begin the morning with bleſſing God for it, and then commune with your heart upon your bed, and be ſtill; and conſider what a mercy it is to have another day added to your life, that you may make your peace with God, before you go hence, and be no more ſeen. Think what many a poor dying Creature would give for a day to repent in, and at what a high rate (if it were to be purchaſed) the damn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Spirits would purchaſe a day to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent in. Conſider, a day is a preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous thing, when <hi>Titus</hi> a Heathen could ſay (when he had ſpent a day with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doing good) to his friends with
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:41197:71"/>great regret, <hi>O my friends, I have loſt a day!</hi> And another could ſay, <hi>He was not worthy the name of a man, who ſpent a whole day in worldly pleaſures.</hi> Remember, this little moment of time is all we have given us to provide for Eternity in; and therefore not to be ſpent and thrown away careleſly, as if we had no God to ſerve, nor no Soul to ſave. Therefore have a care, leſt it be ſaid of you, as it was of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſabel, I gave her ſpace to repent, but ſhe repented not.</hi> When your Lordſhip has thus in the morning brought your heart into a ſerious frame, then my ſecond Advice is, to leave your Bed, and as ſoon as you are ready, retire to your Cloſet, and let none of the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of the World be firſt diſpatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, (though the Devil be never ſo buſie to perſwade you to it) but ſay to all your worldly imployments, <hi>Stay here, while I go yonder and worſhip, and I will come to you again.</hi> When you have ſhut your door, and have ſhut out outward Company, then have a care to ſhut out inward, vain and diſtracting thoughts, which will be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry buſie to ſteal away your heart. Then I would adviſe you to begin your pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:41197:71"/>devotions with reading the Word of God, the Holy Scriptures; for <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> ſays, <hi>Wherewithal ſhall a young man cleanſe his ways? even by taking heed thereunto according to thy Word.</hi> And certainly theſe Divine Oracles of God, are a moſt excellent means to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the mending of our lives. Therefore I would have you begin e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very morning with reading ſome por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it, remembring it is that Word by which we muſt one day he judged. When you have done this, I would not adviſe you preſently to clap down up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your knees, but firſt to conſider ſeriouſly what you are going about, <hi>viz.</hi> That you are going about to ſpeak to that God, before whom the Angels and the Cherubins do cover their faces in token of reverence, as not being able, or worthy to behold ſo much glory; and that <hi>Abraham</hi> (the Father of the Faithful) preſented him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf before him with ſo much humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, as that he called himſelf duſt and aſhes. Therefore do you proſtrate your ſelf before him with humility, remembring that he has ſaid, that he will have reſpect unto the lowly; And yet come with confidence as to a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:41197:72"/>Father, who has promiſed, <hi>That whoſoever comes unto him, he will in no wiſe caſt out;</hi> and that <hi>before we call, he will anſwer,</hi> and <hi>whilſt we are yet ſpeaking, he will hear.</hi> Remember that Prayer is the key of Heaven; it is that by which you can pour out all your wants to God, as to a moſt loving Father, with a confidence that he will ſupply them. The Scripture tells you, <hi>That the effectual fervent prayer of a righteour man availeth much;</hi> and it tells you, that though <hi>Elias was a man ſubject to like paſſions with us,</hi> yet God heard him, and granted his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, to encourage us to come with boldneſs to the Throne of Grace. Therefore do not only make conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to pray, but make conſcience al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo how to pray. Pray with zeal and fervency, do not ſatisfie your ſelf with the body of the duty without the Soul; but as pious <hi>Hanna</hi> did, pour out your ſpirit before the Lord in the name of Chriſt, for things what you ſtand in need of. And remember that <hi>David</hi> ſaid, that the Lord had heard the voice of his weeping. And therefore if you can, weep for your ſins, at leaſt mourn, that you cannot mourn
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:41197:72"/>for ſinning againſt ſo gracious a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that ſo the mercies of God may melt into an ingenuous ſorrow: And do not leave your prayers till you have enjoyed ſome Communion with God in them, and then you will be fit to go chearfully about your worldly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments. Forget not, God hath intruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you with Children, and therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member to take care they be bred up in the nurture and admonition of the Lord; and to ſeaſon them in their young and tender years with Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Piety and Honour, that ſo ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them forth in the way wherein they ſhould go, when they are old, they may not depart from it. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member alſo you have a Family to govern, and take up good <hi>Joſuah</hi>'s re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, that you and your houſe will ſerve the Lord; and <hi>David</hi>'s, who ſaid, that his eyes ſhould be on the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in the Land, that they might ſerve him, and he that telleth lyes, ſhould not tarry in his ſight. Therefore have a care not to keep any that is openly profane and ſcandalous, but at leaſt let them be morally civil; and let God be ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly twice a day publickly wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped by your ſelf and Family, and
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:41197:73"/>ſet them good Examples, and ſay unto them as <hi>Gideon</hi> did to his men in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther caſe, <hi>Look on me, and do likewiſe.</hi> When you have thus ſpent your morning, then I am not ſo rigid as to forbid you all Recreations; no, I think them very neceſſary for Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; but I muſt be ſo ſevere as to forbid you ſuch as may put you into any paſſion or diſorder, which may be hurtful both to Soul and Body. Therefore I would abſolutely forbid you Dice and Cards too, unleſs it be ſometimes, when you muſt keep theſe limitations. Firſt, not to play all day long, as if you were made only to eat and drink, and riſe up to play. For certainly, God did not give us time, as we give Children Rattles, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to play withal. Remember what your good Friend Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi> ſays,
<q>That he that ſpends his time in ſports, and calls it Recreation, is as he whoſe garment is nothing but fringes, and and his meat nothing but ſauce.</q> Therefore I ſhall adviſe you, that your Recreations may be as your ſauce, not as your full meat. The ſecond li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation I would adviſe, is, not to play for more than you care whether
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:41197:73"/>you win or loſe; Remember that Mr. <hi>Herbert</hi> in his excellent Poems ſays,
<q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Game is a Civil Gunpowder in Peace,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Blowing up houſes with their whole increaſe.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q> My next Advice to you, is to make a good choice of your friends, and to keep company moſt with thoſe of them, that are civil and religious, and ingenious; for ſuch company will be both pleaſant and advantagious to you; but the ranting Gameſters company ought to be diſpleaſing to you, for I am ſure you may get a great deal of ill by them, but no good; therefore let ſuch Company be rather a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment than a choice. Next I would deſire you to be as chearful as you can, and to that purpoſe I would recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to you that gaity of goodneſs, that will make you moſt pleaſing to your ſelf and others. And now (my Lord) as your Friend, you muſt give me leave to give you not only good
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:41197:74"/>counſel, but my own experiences too (like Nurſes who feed their Children with nothing but what they have firſt themſelves digeſted into milk) and to aſſure you, that however the Devil and wicked men may perſwade you, That Religion will make you melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly; yet I can aſſert from my own experience, that nothing can give you that comfort, ſerenity and compoſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of mind, as a well and orderly led life; This will free you from all thoſe ſad diſquieting remorſes and checks of conſcience which follow an ill action, and give you that peace of God that paſſes all underſtanding, and that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual feaſt of a good conſcience. This will make you rejoyce with joy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable and full of glory: This will calm your deſires, and quiet your wiſhes, ſo as you ſhall find the conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of God are not ſmall. You will find you have made a happy exchange, having Gold for Braſs, and Pearls for Pebles. For truly (my Lord) I am upon tryal convinced, that all the pleaſures of this world are not ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory. We expect a great deal more from them than we find. For pleaſures die in their Birth, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:41197:74"/>as Biſhop <hi>Hall</hi> ſays, are not worthy to come into the Bills of Mortality. I muſt confeſs for my own part, though I had as much as moſt people in this Kingdom to pleaſe me, and ſaw it in all the Glories of the Court, and was both young and vain enough to endeavour, having my ſhare in all the Vanities thereof; yet I never found they ſatisfied me, God having give me a Nature uncapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of ſatisfaction in any thing below the higheſt Excellency. I never in all my life found real and ſatisfying Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts but in the ways of God, and I am very confident your Lordſhip never will neither. Therefore I beſeech you try this, and then I verily believe you will be of my opinion, <hi>That all her ways are pleaſantneſs, and all her paths are peace.</hi> When you have ſpent what time you think fit in your Recreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or viſiting Friends, or receiving Viſits from them, then I would have you every day ſet ſome time apart for reading good Books and Meditation; do not fear that a little time alone ſhould make you melancholy, for the way not to be alone, is to be alone, and you will find your ſelf never leſs alone, than when you are ſo. For
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:41197:75"/>certainly that God that makes all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers good company, muſt needs be beſt himſelf. Be often in the profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble work of ſelf-examination, be not a ſtranger at home; but pray S. <hi>Auſtins</hi> Prayer, <hi>Lord, make me know thee and my ſelf.</hi> You will find the practice of this Rule conduce much to the good of your Soul. This will make you ſee what ſin is moſt predominant, and what grace is moſt weak, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore had need be ſtrengthened. It will keep ſin from growing undiſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by you. Remember (my Lord) the beſt Gardens had need often to be weeded, or elſe they will ſoon be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>run: and the moſt delicate neat Houſe muſt be often ſwept, or elſe there will be much dirt and duſt in it. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation is a moſt profitable Duty. I would therefore have you meditate ſometimes on the tranſitorineſs and diſſatisfyingneſs of all this Worlds glories. Your Lordſhip, your ſelf, has, as young as you are, ſeen ſuch ſtrange Revolutions as are ſufficient to convince you, that there is nothing certain in this life, but that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo; and that all is vanity and vexation of ſpirit. God has in our
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:41197:75"/>Age caſt contempt upon Princes, and ſtained all the glory of humane Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies, to make us ceaſe to put con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in man, <hi>whoſe breath is in his noſtrils;</hi> for wherein is he to be account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of? God hath famiſhed all the gods of the Earth, that he might be God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, and hath imbittered the Stream, that we might come to the Fountain. Therefore often meditate on this, and it will keep you from over-loving any ſublunary thing. Next I would have you meditate ſometimes upon the ſhortneſs of your life, and the uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of the time of your death; On the black Abyſſus of Eternity, and on the great account you muſt give of all you have done in the fleſh, whether it be good or evil. <hi>For we muſt all appear before the Judgement-ſeat of Chriſt, to receive according to what we have doue in the fleſh, whether good or evil.</hi> I would not keep you upon ſuch melancholy thoughts as theſe too long, and therefore I would have you think of the Joys of Heaven, of that Reſt that remains for the People of God, of that better Country that is a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly one, of that City that hath a
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:41197:76"/>foundation, whoſe Maker and Builder is God, and of thoſe Joys which eye hath not ſeen, nor ear heard, nor hath it ever entred into the heart of man to conceive what God hath laid up for them that love him. For Heaven will make us happy, not as Philoſophy pretends to do, by the confining, but by the frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our deſires. There we ſhall be paſt doing, as well as paſt ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ill. There all tears ſhall be wiped from our eyes, and we ſhall obtain joy and gladneſs; and ſorrow and ſighing ſhall fly away. Thoſe are unmixt bleſſings which are reſerved for the other life. We ſhall then enjoy health without ſickneſs, joy without ſorrow, and happineſs to E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity; but that which is above all; we ſhall be ever with the Lord, and ſee him who ſhall be all in all to us, yea we ſhall follow the Lamb whitherſoever he goes. Such Meditations as theſe I would have you frequent in, that whilſt you are muſing, the fire of Heavenly Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may burn and inflame your heart with love to God, that ſo your
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:41197:76"/>Meditation of him may he ſweet. I would alſo recommend to you the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenting of the publick Ordinances, which are excellent helps to Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for Faith comes by hearing, and God has promiſed that thoſe who wait upon him ſhall renew their ſtrength, and that he will make them joyful in his Houſe of Prayer. I know your Lordſhip too well, to ſay much to perſwade you to works of Charity, for I am not ignorant that your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip abounds in good Works; only to encourage you to continue in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe thereof, I would put you mind of ſome promiſes, how that God hath ſaid, <hi>He that giveth to the poor, lendeth unto the Lord,</hi> and that <hi>whoſoever gives unto a Diſciple, in the name of a Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, though but a cup of cold water, ſhall in no wiſe loſe his reward.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And now (my Lord) I fear I have tired you with my too tedious Rules, and therefore I ſhall put an end to them, when I have given you this one, which is to conclude the day always with Prayer, and not to give ſleep to your eyes, nor ſlumber to your eye-lids,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:41197:77"/>till you have called your ſelf to an account what mercies you have received that day, that you may praiſe God for them; and what ſins you have committed that day, that you may be humbled for them. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring what the good Primate of <hi>Armagh</hi> ſaid,
<q>That the beſt man li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving did enough in the day, to bring him upon his knees at night.</q> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore every night make your peace with God, remembring that many have ſhut their eyes in a healthful ſleep, and yet waked in another World. My Lord, I have now done with my Rules, which I ſhould never have ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured upon, had you not aſſured me, that you are confident they would by Gods bleſſing do you good, and alſo faithfully promiſed me, that you would practiſe them. Which promiſe I muſt beg your Lordſhip to perform, and then I ſhall be much ſatisfied; for I aſſure your Lordſhip, I am ſo much your Friend, as I cannot but with great earnſtneſs deſire the Salvation of your Soul; and indeed, all profeſſions of friendſhip that are made, are but empty profeſſions, if they do not aim
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:41197:77"/>and deſign all they can to make their Friends eternally happy; which I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech your Lordſhip to believe, is the earneſt deſire of,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>My Lord,</salute>
                     <signed>Your affectionate Friend and moſt humble Servant.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:41197:78"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:41197:78"/>
                  <head>Occaſional Meditations UPON SUNDRY SUBJECTS: WITH Pious Reflections UPON SEVERAL SCRIPTURES.</head>
                  <p>By the Right Honourable <hi>Mary,</hi> late Counteſs Dowager of <hi>Warwick.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Nathanael Ranew,</hi> at the <hi>King's Arms</hi> in <hi>S. Paul's</hi> Church-Yard. 1678.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:41197:79"/>
                  <pb n="145" facs="tcp:41197:79"/>
                  <head>OCCASIONAL MEDITATIONS.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="meditation">
                     <head>MEDITATION I. <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon a Damm made to ſtop the Water.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THis Damm that is put up purpoſely by this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to keep to himſelf the water, declares him to be no good natured man. Becauſe, though he is ſupplyed by Neighbouring Springs with more water than he needs for his neceſſary uſes; yet ſtops the Current of it from
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:41197:80"/>his Neighbours, who want it, deſiring to keep all for himſelf.</p>
                     <p>Turn this, O my Soul, into an Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſional Meditation, which may be uſeful to thee. By conſidering that this may not very improperly be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to rich perſons, to whom God hath given with a liberal hand great plenty of this worlds wealth, by which he deſigns that they ſhould not only be watered themſelves, but water others alſo. But they inſtead of <hi>diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting to the neceſſitous poor,</hi> incloſe to themſelves all that God hath beſtowed upon them, to beſtow it upon their <hi>exceſſes</hi> in rich Cloaths and Furniture, with which they adorn their perſons and walls, which expences are the <hi>Damm</hi> which ſtops the current of their charity, and keeps it back from the poor and indigent, whoſe wants would be comfortably ſupplied by their ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluities.</p>
                     <p>O Lord, I beſeech thee to humble me exceedingly under the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of my former guiltineſs in this kind: and make me for the future,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:41197:80"/>when thou art pleaſed to pour thy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits upon me, to conſider thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigneſt I ſhould be thy <hi>Almoner</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigh, as through a Conduit-Pipe, thy <hi>Alms</hi> to thy neceſſitous poor, and let me never more dare to ſtop and damm up what I ought with a liberal hand to ſow for the refreſhing of others. O let me willingly <hi>ſtarve</hi> a luſt to <hi>feed</hi> a Saint. And let me remember that he that <hi>ſows ſparingly, ſhall reap ſparingly.</hi> And let me not only now and then drop a little for charity; but make me one of thoſe perſons mentioned in thy word, who being liberal, <hi>deviſe liberal things, and by ſo doing be eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Oh, make me, as it were, an open Flood-gate to water my Neighbours Neceſſities, that ſo I may, as much as in me lies, be an Imitater of thy Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Bounty, <hi>who doſt good to all.</hi> Oh make me to do ſo as far as I am able, but eſpecially make me remember <hi>the hooſhold of faith;</hi> that ſo I may ſhew my love to him that <hi>begetteth by loving him that is begotten.</hi> And ſeeing my goodneſs extendeth not to thee; let it do ſo to thine. Make me to feed hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:41197:81"/>mouths, and cloath naked Backs, that at the laſt day I may be amongſt thoſe to whom thou wilt ſay, <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my father, inherit the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom prepared for you from the foundation of the world. For I was hungry,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="meditation">
                     <pb n="149" facs="tcp:41197:81"/>
                     <head>MEDITAT. II. <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Conſideration of the different manner of the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a Bee and a Spider.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>WHile I am minding this deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable Spider, which for all its being ſo, hath ſome of its kind that have the honour to inhabit the Courts of the moſt glorious Potentates, (for the inſpired Volumes tell us, they are in <hi>Kings Palaces)</hi> It makes me conſider, that the work they are ſo buſily employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in, while they ſpin their Webs, (which is all ſpun out of their own Bowels, without having any help from any thing without them) is when it is finiſhed good for nothing; but is ſoon bruſh'd down and flung away: Whilſt the induſtrious Bees, that are buſily em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in making of their uſeful Combs, do daily fly abroad to enable themſelves to do ſo: And flying from one Flower to another, gather from every of
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:41197:82"/>them, that which both renews their own ſtrength, and yields others ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
                     <p>By the Spiders work I am minded of a Formaliſt or proud Profeſſor, who works all from himſelf and his own ſtrength, and never goes out of himſelf to a Promiſe to get ſtrength for his performances, or to work by: And therefore his thin-ſpun Righteouſneſs is good for nothing, and will be flung away.</p>
                     <p>The Bees going out, minds me of the Real Chriſtian, who is renewed in the Spirit of his mind, and that he may be enabled to work the great work, he he came into the World for, he goes out to an Ordinance, and to Chriſt in a promiſe for ſtrength to work by, and by them obtains it, and this makes his work give hony, and become good for ſomething.</p>
                     <p>O Lord, I do moſt humbly beſeech thee, let me not dare to work from my ſelf, but to go out daily to thee, for ability to work my great and indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable work with: That I may deny my
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:41197:82"/>own Righteouſneſs, and make mention of thine only. And may thereby find ſuch ſweetneſs from every Ordinance and Promiſe, that my Soul may be like a Garden which the Lord hath bleſſed; and may proſper and thrive exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="meditation">
                     <pb n="152" facs="tcp:41197:83"/>
                     <head>MEDITAT. III. <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon feeding the Poor at the Gate with ſome broken meat left at a Feaſt.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>HOw thankful are theſe poor ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitous perſons, for the frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of that Feaſt, which was ſo plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful to thoſe who ſate within at the Table. Improve this, O my Soul, by conſidering the different Eſtate of the Church Triumphant, and that which is yet Militant.</p>
                     <p>That is in poſſeſſion of eternal bliſs, happy in the fruition of God, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joys him in his fulleſt love, and is every day feaſted with the Marriage Supper of the Lamb; when This being <hi>preſent in the body and abſent from the Lord,</hi> as yet without the door of Heaven, is glad of ſome taſts of thoſe Elixirs of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, which are earneſts of the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed poſſeſſion and previous guſts of
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:41197:83"/>it, and as it were ſome crumbs and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of Glory; ſome of the broken meat of thoſe bleſſed Inhabitants of the new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>'s full and delicious eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry days feaſts.</p>
                     <p>O Lord, I moſt humbly beſeech thee; entertain me ſometimes with ſome taſts of thoſe joys, which thoſe partake of who are preſent with thy ſelf. Let me ſee thee through the Lattice, till I can ſee thee as the pure in heart ſhall ſee thee in another world: That ſo I may long to be diſſolved and to be with Chriſt, and believing in thee let me even here rejoyce with joy unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and full of glory.</p>
                     <p>Which may make me thankful to thee for what I here enjoy of thee: Knowing that Chriſt poſſeſſed by Faith is young Heaven, Glory in the bud; and thereby do thou raiſe my deſires to go to thoſe celeſtial manſions where Glory is full blown, and where I ſhall be entertained with Rivers of pleaſures at thy Right Hand for evermore.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="meditation">
                     <pb n="154" facs="tcp:41197:84"/>
                     <head>MEDITAT. II. <hi>Of my Gardeners chuſing fine young thriving Stocks to graft on, and rejecting old and withered ones.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>MY Gardiners care now he is grafting, in chuſing young and flouriſhing Stocks, and paſſing by thoſe which are old or withered; minds me of Gods dealings with his Creatures in grafting his Grace upon their hearts. He ſeldom doing it upon old decrepid withered ſinners, thoſe old Stocks being oft neglected by him, becauſe they wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly forgat their Creator in the days of their youth, (when they had an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired Precept to remember him) and would go on in ways of ſin, and live ſo wholly without God in the world, that he was but ſeldom in their thoughts, they reſolving to indulge themſelves in all forbidden pleaſures, thinking that
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:41197:84"/>at laſt a death bed Repentance and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God mercy, and ſaying <hi>Lord, Lord,</hi> would be enough to fit them for thoſe eternal manſions whereinto no unholy thing ſhall enter: And ſo bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly go on to add ſin to ſin, (upon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of mercy) while death is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to cloſe their eyes, not conſidering that there is not in the God-breathed Oracles, one example (that I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber) of ſick-bed ſaving Repentance. And though there is one of the Thief upon the Croſs kept upon record, to keep real penitents from deſpairing of mercy at the cloſe of their days; yet there is but one to prevent bold impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſinners from preſuming of mercy.</p>
                     <p>And though the mercy of God ought not to be confined to any Age, yet we may obſerve he doth not frequently work ſaving Grace in old and withering Creatures, but chuſes young Diſciples, and loves and delights to graft his Grace on ſuch, that they may go on to bring forth more fruit in their Age, having given God the Spring and May of their lives, by a ſolemn Act of an early ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dedication to him, and chuſing to walk in all his ways. And who by ſetting
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:41197:85"/>forth betimes in their journey to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, have a long time to glorifie God in: and to be examples and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragers to others to come in, to ſerve God, by aſſuring them that <hi>all his ways are pleaſantneſs, and his paths peace.</hi> And that his <hi>yoak is eaſie,</hi> to thoſe who take it on them, though it may gall their Necks that ſtruggle at it, and are unwilling to bear it.</p>
                     <p>O Lord, I do moſt humbly beſeech thee by this occaſional Meditation, let my heart be lifted up in the high prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of thee my great and good God, for not ſuffering me to continue ſo long un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the reigning power of ſin, as to be caſt off as an old and too withered a ſtock to graft Grace upon, but that thou wert pleaſed to ſhew me the Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Holineſs betimes, before the Autumn of my age. Though, Lord, I do confeſs, with S. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> that too late, Lord, too late I knew and lov'd thee, and do heartily grieve that I did not, as I ſhould, devote all the ſpring of my years to thee, but did give ſome of my green time to vanity and folly, being then too conformable to the wicked world, and too little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to thy bleſſed Will.</p>
                     <pb n="157" facs="tcp:41197:85"/>
                     <p>But oh for ever admired be thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy that did pluck me as a Fire-brand out of the Fire, and left me not to be fuel for everlaſting Burnings. Thou mighteſt then Lord, juſtly have ſaid to me; <hi>Thou that art filthy, be filthy ſtill:</hi> and mighteſt have puniſhed my former ſins with leaving me to die in my ſins. But bleſſed be thy name, that thou didſt implant in me ſome of the Graces of thy ſweet and holy Spirit, before my old age, by which thou haſt been plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to give me more time to ſerve thee, and taſte the pleaſures which are to be found in doing ſo. And haſt thereby enabled me to declare to others what I have my ſelf long experimented, that <hi>thou art good to the Soul that ſeeks thee:</hi> and the pureſt, moſt ſatisfying and laſting pleaſures are to be found in an holy and ſtrict walking with thee, and that, <hi>in keeping thy Commandments there is great reward.</hi> And that religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perſons have their joys, though the blind <hi>Sodomites</hi> of the world want eyes to ſee them. O Lord, make me now in my old age bring forth more fruit, that ſo thou mayſt not ſay of me, as
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:41197:86"/>as juſtly thou didſt of the fruitleſs Fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree, <hi>Cut it down, why cumbereſt thou the ground.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="meditation">
                     <pb n="159" facs="tcp:41197:86"/>
                     <head>MEDITAT. V. <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon looking out of my Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow at</hi> Chelſey <hi>upon the</hi> Thames.</head>
                     <p>THis ſweet River which I looked upon with ſo much pleaſure and delight, while it was ſmooth, ſerene and calm, when a ſudden Tempeſt roſe unexpectedly, and made it rough and troubled, proved rather frightful, than delightful to me, and made me ſhut my Window, and ceaſe looking on it.</p>
                     <p>This minds me what an alluring at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractiveneſs there is in perſons calm and patient, free from the boiſterous diſorders of turbulent paſſions, who entertain the eyes of all Beholders de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfully, while they continue ſo. But if that admired Gentleneſs be by a ſudden eruption of their paſſions turn'd
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:41197:87" rendition="simple:additions"/>into fury, the very form of their viſage ſeems to be changed, and looks fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to all Beholders, and very unallu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring.</p>
                     <p>O Lord, I beſeech thee make me more than ever to ſtudy and practiſe thoſe Chriſtian adorning Graces of Meekneſs and Patience, that thereby I may evince to others how great Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty there is in being calm and free from unbeſeeming and violent paſſions, and that I may by Sweetneſs and Gentleneſs adorn my holy Profeſſion, and excite others to be imitaters of thoſe Graces.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="meditation">
                     <pb n="161" facs="tcp:41197:87"/>
                     <head>MEDITAT. VI. <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon ſeeing a fine Carpet ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off a duſty Table.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>WHilſt this fine Carpet was up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Table it appeared ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fine and clean; but when that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorning Cover was removed, how foul and duſty was it found to be.</p>
                     <p>This minds me of a formal Profeſſor, which puts all his Religion in formali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of outward Duties, and Geſtures, which to Beholders make him appear decently. But all this while under that outſide appearance of Devotion his heart is naſty and duſty, his care being only (like a painted Sepulchre) to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear beautiful without, whilſt within there is all uncleanneſs, and ſo thinks by putting on an hypocritical outſide to hide all his faults, and ſerve the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil ſecurely in Chriſt's Livery.</p>
                     <pb n="162" facs="tcp:41197:88"/>
                     <p>O Lord, I humbly beſeech thee ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer me not to ſatisfie my ſelf with the outward formality of Duties, which may ſeem well to my lookers on. But make me mind the inward and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al performance, and how my heart is affected in them. And let me look to heart cleanſing, knowing, that thou my great God lookeſt to the heart. And that though I may by covering over a duſty heart with a fine outward for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality, deceive men, I cannot deceive thee the great heart-ſearcher, before whom all things are naked and open.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="meditation">
                     <pb n="163" facs="tcp:41197:88"/>
                     <head>MEDITAT. VII. <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon childrens playing in the ſtreets, and falling to fight,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
                     <p>THeſe Children by the delight they take in their play not only forget the time allotted for their recreation, and ſlip the hour preſcribed for their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, to learn their Leſſons in, and have not only thereby ventured a whipping, but have fallen out amongſt themſelves, tearing one anothers fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: which one of their offended Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſeeing, ſnatched up his Son, and ſeverely corrected him, which other perſons in the ſtreet beholding, though they knew neither the Child, nor the perſon that ended the Fray, by taking away the Fighter, concluded by the correction that he gave, that he was the careful Father of the Child, who had us'd his Rod to prevent, perhaps, the loſs of an eye</p>
                     <pb n="164" facs="tcp:41197:89"/>
                     <p>This may be uſeful to mind me of the great Father of all the Families of the Earth's wiſe proceeding with his Children, when he ſees them waſting of their time about things of no concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which ought to be employed in learning what is of everlaſting concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and are quarrelling and fighting not againſt their luſts, but one againſt another. He doth, to prevent the miſchief they might do each other, correct them ſeaſonably, by which he ſhews his fatherly care of them.</p>
                     <p>O Lord, I do moſt humbly beſeech thee, ſanctifie this Meditation to me, that I may remember, that though there is no knowledge either of love or hatred by all that is before us; and that though thy out ward diſpenſations are often in the dark to us; yet it is a ſign of Sonſhip that thou corrects a diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient careleſs Child.</p>
                     <p>And therefore let me not in an afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed condition (if thou by thy provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ſhalt again bring me into it) think that thou hateſt me, but that thou art a moſt Gracious Father, who
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:41197:89"/>correcteſt me in faithfulneſs to prevent what thou foreſeeſt, and I did not, would miſchief me.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="meditation">
                     <pb n="166" facs="tcp:41197:90"/>
                     <head>MEDITAT. VIII. <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the lighting many Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles at one.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THis Candle that hath lighted ſo many, ſtill gives as much light as it did before, and hath loſt nothing by what it hath imparted unto them.</p>
                     <p>Improve this, oh my Soul, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering, that ſome excellent Chriſtians (who as the inſpired Volumes tell us of that admirable perſon S. <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> who was a burning and a ſhining Light) are ſo conſpicuous, that all Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders take notice of their well order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed converſation, their Light ſo ſhining before men, that others ſeeing their good works are thereby excited to glorifie God, and are alſo ſo communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cative of that light wherewith God hath vouchſafed to enlighten their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings, that they are in a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſenſe, what <hi>Job</hi> ſaid he was in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother,
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:41197:90"/>eyes to the blind: and are ſtill teaching young Diſciples what they who are old have been taught of God; and ſo train them up in the School of Chriſtianity. And yet by imparting their knowledge of God, know him not the leſs themſelves, but many times the more, and by inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them of the pleaſures of Religion, bring them into the holy path which leads to eternal life, yet hinder not their own progreſs toward Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
                     <p>O Lord, I moſt humbly beſeech thee, let this Meditation provoke me, more than ever yet I have done, to impart to my Fellow Chriſtians, (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially my Family, under my autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity) what I know of thee, that by my declaring how good a God thou art, I may bring many others to know thee, not only with a general, but an expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimental knowledge; which will make them ſay as I do, <hi>That thou art good, and doſt good.</hi> O let me by declaring what thou haſt done for my Soul, cauſe others to joyn with me in adoring thee for thy greatneſs, and loving thee for
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:41197:91"/>thy goodneſs; that ſo we may magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie thy name together. And I may be inſtrumental to impart light to others, and be made a burning and a ſhining Light my ſelf.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="meditation">
                     <pb n="169" facs="tcp:41197:91"/>
                     <head>MEDITAT. IX. <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the drawing of the Window-curtains to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the Suns putting out the Fire.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>AS ſoon as I perceived that the ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Sun into the Room, would put out the Fire, I inſtantly drew the Window-curtains to prevent it.</p>
                     <p>Which minds me of the neceſſity there is, that God ſhould ſometimes, (when he ſees the Fire of Celeſtial Love, in the hearts of his People, in danger of being put out by other flames) take that away from us which would take us away from him. And if he doth it not by death, yet to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent our cooling in our affections, doth, as it were, by ſome dark providence, draw a Curtain between us and what we doat upon.</p>
                     <pb n="170" facs="tcp:41197:92"/>
                     <p>O Lord, I beſeech thee: when thou ſeeſt the Fire of thy Love in my heart, ready to be put out by any thing, be ſo merciful as to draw what obſcuring Curtain thou pleaſeſt, to hinder it, that my love to thy Divine Majeſty, may be like the Fire upon the Altar that never went out. O let it never be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh'd by any earthly object. But let my love to thee drown and ſwallow up all creature-loves. O blot our every name from my corrupted heart, that hinders the deeper engraving of thy name there; and remove me from what, and whom thou wilt; ſo thou wilt thereby bring me nearer to thy ſelf. Oh, though I have ſparks for Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, yet let my greateſt blaze, blaze towards Heaven. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="meditation">
                     <pb n="171" facs="tcp:41197:92"/>
                     <head>MEDITAT. X. <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon a perſon who had great knowledge, and very quick, but unſanctified parts.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THis perſon, who is in this very prophane Age celebrated for a great <hi>Wit,</hi> and is very acceptable to all his companions upon that account, does yet make ſo very ill uſe of thoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute parts God hath been pleaſed to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow upon him, that he improves them only to make <hi>jeſts,</hi> and to <hi>laugh</hi> at all that is either <hi>ſerious</hi> or <hi>ſacred,</hi> endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring as much as in him lies, to make all Devotion be turn'd into <hi>Ridicule:</hi> and ſo abuſes all the knowledge that God hath beſtowed upon him, ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the <hi>deſign</hi> for which 'twas gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him, of <hi>glorifying his great Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor;</hi> that he only turns it againſt <hi>him,</hi> to his own final deſtruction without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, uſing it as a Torch to light himſelf to Hell thereby.</p>
                     <pb n="172" facs="tcp:41197:93"/>
                     <p>O Lord, I moſt humbly beſeech thee let this Meditation make me chuſe to have a little ſanctified knowledge, rather than the moſt raiſed and quick parts unſanctified, and help me to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove thoſe parts thou haſt beſtowed upon me, to thy <hi>Honour,</hi> that I may never fight againſt thee with thy own weapons, but may bring ſome Glory to thee by them. O be pleaſed to give me <hi>Light</hi> in my <hi>Head,</hi> and <hi>Fire</hi> in my <hi>Heart,</hi> even that <hi>Fire from Heaven,</hi> by which I may inflame others with true <hi>zeal</hi> for thy Glory, that uſing thoſe weak parts for thee thou haſt vouchſafed to me, I may by the little knowledge I have be lighted to the Regions of Bliſs, whilſt otheres with their greater knowledge, devoid of Grace, go down to utter darkneſs.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="meditation">
                     <pb n="173" facs="tcp:41197:93"/>
                     <head>MEDITAT XI. <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon ſeeing a Silk-worm ſpin.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THis Silk-worm hath for a long time entertained my Eyes with obſerving how buſily it was employed in ſpinning its curious Threads of Silk: and that when it had made it's purſe of Silk, into which it has confin'd it ſelf, if the Looker to it does not wind off what it has ſpun, rather than it will keep that weight of Silk upon its Back, it will make a way to get from under it by eating a hole at the top of it, and ſo flings it off.</p>
                     <p>Which minds me of thoſe very vain perſons that are puffed up with their being adorned with fine Cloaths, which is being proud of putting on of that which the Silk-worm puts off.</p>
                     <p>This may be uſeful to caution me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:41197:94"/>loving and delighting in fine Silks. When I do conſider that all the fineſt and beſt mingled ones that can be put on to adorn me with, are all ſpun by a <hi>poor Worm:</hi> and that to be <hi>proud</hi> of <hi>Fine Cloaths,</hi> is to be ſo of that, which is the <hi>monument of our Sin:</hi> for if <hi>Adam</hi> had not ſinned, we ſhould have had no need of cloathing to have hid our ſhame. And that even Pearls which are by many purchaſed at ſo dear a rate, that they may adorn themſelves with them, are but the <hi>ſickneſs</hi> of the <hi>Fiſh;</hi> and that <hi>Crimſon,</hi> with which <hi>crown'd Heads</hi> are often cloathed, is dyed with the <hi>blood of a Fiſh:</hi> and that even <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Silver</hi> for which many perſons venture their <hi>immortal part,</hi> is digged out of the entrails of the earth. And 'tis in the inſpired Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume told us, that <hi>He that loves Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhall not be ſatisfied with Silver:</hi> Nor is all the <hi>Gold</hi> that is in all the Mines in the whole world worth one immortal Soul.</p>
                     <p>O Lord, I do moſt humbly implore, that thou wouldſt by theſe conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the inconſiderableneſs that is
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:41197:94"/>in all theſe glittering adornments, which poor, deluded, proud perſons look on with eyes of admiration. Humble me exceedingly for having in my youth been too guilty of this ſin of too much loving, and delighting in fine Cloaths, being then too much taken up with the adorning of my <hi>vile body,</hi> and too little ſo, with adorning of my better part.</p>
                     <p>O Lord, make me for the time to come to watch againſt this ſin, which did ſo eaſily beſet me, and let me never more lift up my Soul to this tinſel and pagentery vanity: but make me ſtudy to be like the King's Daughter, all <hi>glorious within.</hi> And though thou my God has told us, that thoſe that wear <hi>gay Apparel</hi> are in <hi>King's Houſes,</hi> and that in thy inſpired Volume the Virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Woman is ſaid to have all her Houſhold <hi>cloathed</hi> with <hi>ſcarlet,</hi> and that her own <hi>cloathing</hi> is <hi>Silk</hi> and <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> which ſeems to intimate that it is not unlawful to wear <hi>Silk, Scarlet,</hi> and <hi>Purple,</hi> and that the <hi>Silk-worm</hi> was not made only to ſpin for the <hi>proud.</hi> Yet, O Lord, I do beſeech thee, let me
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:41197:95"/>never more yield to that pityful tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation of being drawn to eſteem either others, or my ſelf upon the account of being ſet out with much bravery: but let me value more, others my Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Chriſtians, and prize more in my ſelf, the adorning of a ſweet, meek, quiet, contented ſpirit, which is in thy ſight of great value. And if I be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orned with the Graces of thy Holy Spirit, help me to conſider they will make me beautiful to all eternity, where as all my bodily adornments are pull'd of at night when I go to reſt, and muſt be all for ever parted with at the night of death by me.</p>
                     <p>O Lord, therefore be pleaſed to make me often call to my remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance the very great and ſenſible plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, I have often experienced in cloathing naked Backs, when thou haſt let me have the honour of being thy Almoner, and diſpenſedſt thy charity through my hands to thy neceſſitous poor; and let that make me rather to chuſe to cloath naked Backs, than to pleaſe idle eyes, and rather to chuſe to ſee many of my Fellow Creatures kept
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:41197:95"/>warm, being covered with my Charity, in plain, but warm Apparel, than to ſtarve my Charity, by putting upon my ſelf one rich laced Gown, which would, if ſold, and diſtributed unto the Poor, make many decent, and convenient Gowns for ſeveral indigent perſons.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="meditation">
                     <pb n="178" facs="tcp:41197:96"/>
                     <head>MEDITAT. XII. <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon deſiring a friend to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve ſafe for me ſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious things, which were kept for me, till I needed them, and then ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably produced to help me.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>HOw earneſtly did I deſire my Friend to lay up ſafe for me theſe things, and how faithfully hath he preſerved them, and how ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably hath he produced them for me at my need?</p>
                     <p>This may be uſeful to excite me, to practice gratitude, to my beſt and higheſt Friend, to whom I have oft ſent up the reſpirations of Soul, that he would keep for me both thoſe Truths I have learnt out of his Sacred
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:41197:96"/>Word, and thoſe experiences I have had of his Goodneſs, and ſupports vouchfafed me under afflicting provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences, not daring to truſt to my me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory only, theſe engaging mercies I have received, leſt his Word and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits ſhould ſlip out of my mind; and I have petitioned him alſo, that he would bring afreſh into my mind thoſe Truths, when I moſt needed them.</p>
                     <p>O Lord, I adore thee for bringing again afreſh to my Memory, thoſe ſupporting promiſes, to ſtrengthen my weak Faith, when I moſt needed them, which thou did preſerve for me, till the times of my greateſt exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies, and didſt then comfort me by them.</p>
                     <p>And, O Lord, I do alſo thankfully acknowledge, that when thou didſt as a gracious Father, chaſtiſe me by afflictions for my enormities, and I was even ready to faint in taking that wholeſome Soul Phyſick, of thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing, that thou wert then pleaſed, by my conſidering the benefits which had formerly accrued to my better part, by ſanctified afflictions, to make me not only in ſome good meaſure patient under them; but didſt alſo
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:41197:97"/>make me to believe, they would be for my ſpiritual good. And thus thou madeſt my Memory a Cabinet, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve my own experiences, that they might be ſeaſonably produc'd to keep me from doing as <hi>Iſſachar</hi> did, crouch down under my burdens.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="meditation">
                     <pb n="181" facs="tcp:41197:97"/>
                     <head>MEDITAT. XIII. <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon my often waking in the night, and preſently falling aſleep again.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>HOw often have I awaked this Night, and inſtantly fallen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep again? being ſo drowſie, that I could not long keep my ſelf from ſlumbring.</p>
                     <p>This may be uſeful to mind me of my Spiritual Condition, having oft been in an awakened frame, in which I have been put upon ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after the great things of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Concernment, which have then been ſo realiſed unto me, as to take deep impreſſions upon my heart, and hath made my Soul to follow hard after God for Mercy, and for power to ſerve him better; but alas!
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:41197:98"/>how ſoon have I by carnal ſecurity been drowſie and fallen aſleep again; and though in the Divine Records of Gods revealed Will unto us: he hath bid us, that we ſhould not ſleep as do others, but that we ſhould be watchful; yet I have been apt to forget that Precept; and to ſay to my ſelf, in a ſpiritual ſenſe, what was ſaid of natural reſt (which is a ſhutting up of the Senſes) concerning <hi>Lazarus; that if he ſlept he ſhould do well,</hi> (though I ſlept, it ſhould be well with me.)</p>
                     <p>But, O Lord, I do moſt humbly beſeech thee, do unto me, as thou ſaidſt thou wouldſt do unto him, come and awaken me out of my ſleep.</p>
                     <p>O let me no longer be ſo unequal in my Devotions, as to have my Goodneſs like a Morning Dew, which ſoon paſſes away; and ſo be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times awake, and ſometimes aſleep. But let me be kept watchful, by the ſerious ſenſe of, my mortality; and of the ſtrict account I muſt give to thee, of all that I have done in the
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:41197:98"/>fleſh, whether it be good or evil: And when thou ſeeſt me falling again into my Spiritual Lethargy, do thou ſay unto me, as the Mariners in the ſtorm did unto <hi>Jonah; Ariſe thou ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard and call upon thy God.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:41197:99"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:41197:99"/>
                  <p>PIOUS REFLECTIONS UPON SEVERAL SCRIPTURES.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:41197:100"/>
                  <pb n="187" facs="tcp:41197:100"/>
                  <head>Pious Reflections On Several SCRIPTURES.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="reflection">
                     <head>REFLECTION 1.</head>
                     <p>LOrd when I read in thy Word, of the man after thine own heart, ſaying, <hi>Rivers of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters run down mine eyes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe men keep not thy commandments;</hi> and yet conſider that I am ſo far from imitating him, that I can many times <hi>ſuffer ſin to be upon my brother,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſo much as giving him reproof for it, or adviſing him, ſo much as to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider <hi>whom he offends by it:</hi> Nay, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times I am ready <hi>to make a mock of ſin,</hi>
                        <pb n="188" facs="tcp:41197:101"/>and to <hi>laugh</hi> at that which is a <hi>grief</hi> to thy <hi>Holy Spirit.</hi> O Lord, I beſeech thee humble me under this conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and make me for the time to come to imitate holy <hi>David,</hi> in my cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity towards my offending Brother. And with thy ſervant <hi>Lot</hi> to have my <hi>ſoul vexed in hearing and ſeeing the fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy communication of the wicked.</hi> O let me be ſo charitable as to weep over the Soul of my offending Brother, and let me, as much as in me lies, help him out of the ſnare of ſin, and by my Prayers, and holy Example, help him towards Heaven.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="reflection">
                     <pb n="189" facs="tcp:41197:101"/>
                     <head>REFLECT. II. Jonah 4.9. <hi>Then ſaid the Lord, doſt thou well to be angry for the gourd? and he ſaid,</hi> I <hi>do well to be angry even unto death.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>LOrd, when I read of this <hi>peeviſh Prophet Jonah,</hi> who becauſe thou waſt merciful unto the repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Ninevites,</hi> and <hi>didſt not deſtroy them in forty days,</hi> according to what he had proclaimed, was ſo diſcontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that when thou <hi>expoſtulatedſt</hi> with him, and askedſt him, whether <hi>he did well to be angry;</hi> he was ſo far from <hi>confeſſing</hi> his fault, as that he ſeemed to <hi>dare</hi> to approve it even to thy very <hi>face,</hi> by theſe words, <hi>I do well to be angry even unto death.</hi> O Lord, how doth this ſhew me the madneſs of this paſſion of anger, and diſcontent, which doth for the preſent ſo far di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract us, that we are ready to juſtifie
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:41197:102"/>a fault in ſtead of begging pardon for it? O Lord, I do therefore moſt humbly beſeech thee, to inable me, to be <hi>ſlow to anger,</hi> remembring that thou haſt told me; that <hi>he that is ſlow to anger, is better than the mighty;</hi> and <hi>he that governs his Sipirit, than he that takes a City; and he that hath no rule over his ſpirit, is as a City that hath no wall.</hi> O bring all my <hi>paſſions</hi> into ſubjection to my <hi>reaſon,</hi> and my <hi>reaſon</hi> to my <hi>Religion.</hi> Let <hi>me not fret my ſelf in any wiſe to do evil,</hi> nor to be <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry,</hi> and ſin in my Anger, but give me a <hi>meek, quiet, contented ſpirit, which is in thy ſight of great value.</hi> Let me <hi>learn of thee to be meek and lowly, that I may find reſt unto my ſoul.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="reflection">
                     <pb n="191" facs="tcp:41197:102"/>
                     <head>REFLECT. III. Mark 9.5. <hi>And Peter anſwered and ſaid to Jeſus, maſter it is good for us to be here.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>LOrd, when I peruſe theſe words of <hi>Peter</hi>'s, that it is <hi>good to be here:</hi> this makes me reflect upon my ſelf, in relation to this preſent World; who, am often times, when I am de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted with any thing here below, which doth pleaſe my ſenſual appetite, ready to ſay 'tis <hi>good to be here.</hi> But, <hi>O Lord,</hi> I beſeech thee do thou then ſay to me, <hi>up and be going, for here is not your reſt.</hi> Look beyond things <hi>temporal</hi> to <hi>thoſe</hi> which are <hi>eternal:</hi> theſe worldly pleaſures dye in the birth, and therefore are not worthy to come into the Bill of Mortality: make me to conſider theſe things can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſatisfie me for a <hi>moment,</hi> much leſs for <hi>eternity;</hi> and that though the world ſeems to <hi>kiſs</hi> me, 'tis but to <hi>ſtab</hi> me, though it makes me <hi>ſport,</hi> 'tis but to
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:41197:103"/>
                        <hi>put out my eyes;</hi> it promiſes <hi>much,</hi> but performs <hi>nothing;</hi> and therefore let me not ſay, <hi>'tis good to be here;</hi> but let me ſeek after that <hi>city that hath founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, whoſe maker and builder is God, after that better country, that is an heavenly.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="reflection">
                     <pb n="193" facs="tcp:41197:103"/>
                     <head>REFLECT. IV. John 4.28. <hi>The woman left her waterpot.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>LOrd! when I read that after thou wert pleaſed to inſtruct the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritan</hi> woman, that thou wert the <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Saviour of the world;</hi> ſhe preſently left her <hi>water-pot,</hi> and went into the City to inform others, that they alſo might come and be bleſſed with a ſight of him, who is the <hi>deſire of all Nations.</hi> O Lord, this doth indeed convince me, that the <hi>Soul</hi> that once findeth <hi>thee,</hi> is preſently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to part with <hi>all:</hi> For this wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, before thy revealing thy ſelf to her, was buſied about her <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-pot,</hi> and her worldly imployments: but after ſhe had found the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> ſhe could (as it were for joy) forget her <hi>water-pot,</hi> and willingly part with it, to inform her Neighbours what ſhe had found, that they alſo might have a part with her. O Lord, that thou
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:41197:104"/>wouldſt inable me alſo, to leave all to follow thee; and that I may like <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Peter,</hi> who when thou calledſt him from his fiſhing, <hi>left his nets ſtraight-way, and followed thee;</hi> leave all my worldly wealth and follow thee, and <hi>count all things dung and droſs to gain thee,</hi> and with the man ſpoken of in the Goſpel, <hi>ſell all to obtain the pearl of greateſt price,</hi> that having found <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> I may willingly part with all for thee; and having thee, may <hi>ſay I have enough.</hi> Lord I am willing, if thou call'ſt me to it, to leave my <hi>water-pot,</hi> and my <hi>nets,</hi> and all for thee.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="reflection">
                     <pb n="195" facs="tcp:41197:104"/>
                     <head>REFLECT. V. Acts 24.25. <hi>And as he reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of righteouſneſs, tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and judgement to come, Felix trembled, and anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Go thy way for this time, when</hi> I <hi>have a convenient ſeaſon</hi> I <hi>will hear thee.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>LOrd, when I peruſe this Verſe, and ſee that thy choſen Veſſel, though a Priſoner, as he reaſoned of Righteouſneſs, Temperance and Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to come, could make <hi>Felix</hi> tremble; and yet he could put him off to another ſeaſon. This makes me to reflect upon my ſelf, in regard of the good motions, that the <hi>holy Spirit</hi> many times comes to me with, as it were, in the <hi>cool of the day,</hi> when the <hi>heat</hi> of <hi>temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> is over, ſaying, <hi>Doſt thou well to be angry? doſt thou well to love this
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:41197:105"/>world? Doſt thou not remember God hath bid the not to love this world, nor to conſume thy days in vanity, nor to be vain in thy imaginations? But God has bid thee work out thy ſalvation with fear and trembling, and give all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence to make thy calling and election ſure. Remember thou haſt a great work to do, and thou haſt but a little moment to do it in; thy body is but duſt, and muſt ſoon return to duſt; but thy ſoul is made for eternity; it muſt laſt for ever, its more worth than an whole world, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeek reſt for that, therefore look beyond things temporal to thoſe that are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal. Lay up for thy ſelf treaſure in heaven, and let thy heart be there alſo.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>O Lord, how often hath thy <hi>bleſſed Spirit</hi> thus, as it were, <hi>whiſpered</hi> into my <hi>Soul;</hi> and though upon ſuch ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conſiderations, I have with <hi>Felix</hi> trembled, for the preſent; yet I have with him alſo ſaid, <hi>Go thy way for this time, when I have a convenient ſeaſon I will hear thee.</hi> But, <hi>O Lord,</hi> I beſeech thee pardon this <hi>procraſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> and putting off good reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:41197:105"/>for the time paſt, and now in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able me to <hi>make haſte,</hi> and <hi>not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay to keep thy commandments,</hi> and to follow the example of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digal, who ſaid, <hi>he would ariſe and go to his Father, and he ſtraight-way aroſe and went,</hi> according to his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution and promiſe. Make me, Lord, to remember that it is <hi>to day, if I will hear thy voice, that I muſt not harden my heart,</hi> and that <hi>now</hi> is <hi>the accepted</hi> time; <hi>now is the day of ſalvation.</hi> Let me therefore now <hi>work the work of God whilſt it is day, for the night cometh wherein no man can work.</hi> Lord, make me to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that if it be <hi>hard</hi> to repent <hi>to day,</hi> it will be much <hi>harder to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row;</hi> and that I have no aſſurance that I ſhall live till to morrow. Make me therefore to <hi>remember thee my Creator in the days of my youth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the evil days come, wherein I ſhall ſay, I have no pleaſure in them;</hi> and with the wiſe Virgins to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare <hi>to meet the Bridegroom of my ſoul,</hi> with <hi>my lamp ready and well fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with oyl,</hi> that when thy <hi>bleſsed Spirit,</hi> next knocks at the door of my heart, by any good motion,
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:41197:106"/>I may preſently entertain it with <hi>careſſes</hi> and <hi>ſatisfaction,</hi> and not ſay with <hi>Felix, Go thy way for this time, when I have a more conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſeaſon I will hear thee.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="reflection">
                     <pb n="199" facs="tcp:41197:106"/>
                     <head>REFLFCT. VI. 2 Sam. 12.5. <hi>And Davids an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger was greatly kindled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the man, and he ſaid to Nathan, As the Lord liveth, the man that hath done this thing ſhall ſurely dye.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>LOrd, when I read of <hi>Nathans</hi> coming to <hi>David,</hi> and by a <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable</hi> ſhewing him his own fault, and hear him preſently ſay, <hi>As the Lord liveth, the man that hath done this thing ſhall ſurely dye.</hi> This diſcovers to me my own iniquity, who am many times ready with <hi>David</hi> to condemn my own actions in an other perſon, and to be a ſevere cenſurer of the faults of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but to paſs a very ſlight one upon my own, and can eaſily diſcern the <hi>mote in my brothers eye, but cannot perceive the beam that is in my own eye.</hi> O Lord, I beſeech thee, when I would cenſure, make me to begin
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:41197:107"/>at home, and to judge my ſelf; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring that I have moſt reaſon to do ſo; for I can ſee in my <hi>brother</hi> but a <hi>a life full of ſin,</hi> but I can ſee in <hi>my ſelf an heart full of ſin;</hi> let me therefore in lowlineſs of mind eſteem others better than my ſelf, and <hi>not judge ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but judge my ſelf, that I may not be judged of the Lord.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="reflection">
                     <pb n="201" facs="tcp:41197:107"/>
                     <head>REFLECT. VII. Joſ. 23.15. <hi>But as for me and my houſe, we will ſerve the Lord.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>LOrd, when I read of thy ſervant <hi>Joſhuah</hi> before his death, reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up all the great engagements that the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> had to ſerve thee, to provoke them to renew their Covenant with thee, and to keep cloſe to thy ſervice; and hear him taking his moſt happy reſolution, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they did, <hi>He and his houſe would ſerve the Lord.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>How deſirous, O Lord, am I to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low this holy man's Example, and to reſolve that whatever the reſt of the World doth, I and my Family will ſerve the Lord; let me not think it enough to ſerve thee my own ſelf; but make me to do, as thou ſaidſt thou knewſt thy ſervant <hi>Abraham</hi> would, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand my Children, and my Houſhold
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:41197:108"/>after me, that they may keep thy Commandments, to do Judgement and Juſtice. And as holy <hi>David</hi> did, let me ſay, <hi>He that walketh uprightly, he ſhall ſerve me, mine eye ſhall be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the faithful of the land, that they may dwell with me: He that telleth lies ſhall not tarry in my ſight,</hi> that it may be ſaid of me, as it was of <hi>Cornelius, That I fear God and all my houſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="reflection">
                     <pb n="203" facs="tcp:41197:108"/>
                     <head>REFLECT. VIII. Luke 16.25. <hi>And Abraham ſaid, Son, remember that thou in thy life time receivedſt thy good things, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Lazarus evil things: but now he is comforted, and thou art tormented.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>LOrd, when I read this ſad anſwer of <hi>Abraham,</hi> to the Rich-mans requeſt: <hi>Son, remember that thou in thy life time receivedſt thy good things:</hi> How ſad a remembrance do I believe this muſt needs be to him, to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his former proſperity; and to think that he was cleathed in Purple and ſine Linnen, and ſared ſumptuouſly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day; and now wanted a drop of water to cool his tongue. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of his former proſperity, was now but an aggravation of his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery.</p>
                     <pb n="204" facs="tcp:41197:109"/>
                     <p>For what good did it do him to conſider that in his life time, he had it may be a great Retinue, and many to wait upon him: when in Hell his Attendance were only Divels and damned Spirits.</p>
                     <p>O Lord, I beſeech thee therefore, let it never be ſaid to me, as it was to this miſerable great one; <hi>thou haſt in thy life time had thy good things;</hi> thou haſt had thy conſolation.</p>
                     <p>O Lord, I beſeech thee, give me not my Portion in this Life, nor let me have a ſhort Heaven here upon Earth, and an eternal Hell hereafter.</p>
                     <p>Let me not be ſatisfied with the bleſſings of thy Foot-ſtool, without thoſe of thy Throne; nor with the fatneſs of the Earth, without the dew of Heaven.</p>
                     <p>Let me not <hi>ſay to gold thou art my hope, or to the fine gold thou art my confidence.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Let me not count theſe lower things my good things, becauſe theſe may ſtand with Reprobation, and a <hi>Dives</hi> may have them, and go to Hell. But let me account thoſe things my good things, which cannot ſtand with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation.</p>
                     <pb n="205" facs="tcp:41197:109"/>
                     <p>O viſit me with the favour of thy choſen: O let me not ſo much co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet to <hi>be cloathed with purple, and fine linnen,</hi> as to be <hi>like the kings daughter all glorious within;</hi> and be cloathed with the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, and help me to put on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and to make no proviſion for the fleſh, to fulfil the luſts thereof.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="reflection">
                     <pb n="206" facs="tcp:41197:110"/>
                     <head>REFLECT IX. Mark 8.36. <hi>VVhat ſhall it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit a man to gain the whole world, and loſe his own ſoul?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>LOrd, when I read theſe words, and ſee, as it were, my bleſſed Saviour, putting the whole world in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one Scale of a Ballance, and the Soul of a poor Creature into the other, and the Soul out-weighing all the World: How really doth this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince me, that whoſoever ſhall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change his immortal Soul to gain the whole World, would make a ſad bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</p>
                     <p>O Lord, I beſeech thee therefore, let me not ſell the Devil mine, for a little ſcrap of it; but remembering the preciouſneſs of it, by the price it coſt; <hi>For we were not redeemed with corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble things, as ſilver or gold, but with the precious blood of Chriſt.</hi> Therefore if the Devil ſhould come to me, as he
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:41197:110"/>did once to my Saviour, and ſhew me all the Kingdoms of the World, and all the glories of them, and ſay, <hi>all theſe will I give thee for thy ſoul.</hi> I may ſay to him, <hi>Get thee behind me Satan:</hi> I'll never make ſuch a fools bargain.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="reflection">
                     <pb n="208" facs="tcp:41197:111"/>
                     <head>REFLECT. X. 1 Sam. 30.6. <hi>And David en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged himſelf in the Lord his God.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>LOrd, when I read this Chapter, and conſider the ſad condition of <hi>David</hi> who, when he returned, found <hi>Ziglag</hi> burnt, and his two Wives car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried Captives by the <hi>Amalekites;</hi> and the people that were with him talking of ſtoning him, that he was in ſo ſad an out-ſide condition, that he was ſorely diſtreſſed, yet the Text ſaith that <hi>David,</hi> (even then) <hi>encouraged himſelf in the Lord his God.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>O Lord, how doth this make me cry out and ſay, <hi>bleſſed are the people which are in ſuch a caſe, yea bleſſed are the people, whoſe God is the Lord;</hi> yea bleſſed are they, who in their great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt tryals and diſtreſſes can encourage themſelves in God, that can truſt in God at all times. <hi>Lord, thoſe that
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:41197:111"/>know thy name will put their truſt in thee,</hi> and thou wilt keep them in perfect peace, whoſe mind is ſtaid on thee, becauſe they truſt in thee.</p>
                     <p>O Lord, I beſeech thee, let this make me follow holy <hi>David</hi>'s Example, in all my diſtreſſes to encourage my ſelf in thee, knowing it is better to put confidence in God, than to put confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in Princes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="reflection">
                     <pb n="210" facs="tcp:41197:112"/>
                     <head>REFLECT. XI.</head>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>Gen. 22.9.</bibl> 
                        <hi>Abraham bound I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaac his ſon, and laid him on the altar, on the wood.</hi>
                     </q>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>V. 12.</bibl> 
                        <hi>Lay not thy hand upon the lad, neither do thou any thing unto him.</hi>
                     </q>
                     <p>LOrd, when I read with what ready obedience faithful <hi>Abraham</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed with that command, which not only ran croſs to his natural affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, but eemingly would diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point the Promiſe he ſo long waited for, and at length received, with ſo much joy and ſatisfaction, that he named his Son, <hi>Iſaac</hi> (Laughter) as a Witneſs and Memorial of it. And alſo, how when he had ſtretched out his hand, and took the Knife to ſlay his Son, thou calledſt from Heaven to him, <hi>Lay not thy hand upon the lad.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This greatly ſhames me to think how
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:41197:112"/>ſlow and backward I was to yield to thy gracious commands and calls, to devote my ſelf intirely to thee, in a courſe of ſtrict Religion, and to preſent my Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy as a living Sacrifice, holy, accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to thee, for fear of ſlaying my <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaac,</hi> looſing all my joy and delight, as if I might never have been merry af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter my ſo doing.</p>
                     <p>But, O Lord, I muſt acknowledge I was afraid where no fear was: For I find by bleſt experience, Religion (the being laid on thine Altar) neither kills, nor burns up our delights, only confines and tames them: For as I read in the Parable of the prodigal, though he had had much mad jollity before, he never knew what true joy was <hi>till he came to himſelf,</hi> and return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to his Father, for 'twas then, and not till then, that he and his began to be (truly) merry,</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="reflection">
                     <pb n="212" facs="tcp:41197:113"/>
                     <head>REFLECT. XII.</head>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>Mart. 7.21.</bibl> 
                        <hi>Not every one that ſaith unto me, Lord, Lord, ſhall enter into the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of heaven, but he that doth the will of my Father which is in heaven.</hi>
                     </q>
                     <p>O Lord, when I read that 'tis not calling upon thee, <hi>Lord, Lord,</hi> but the obeying thee as ſuch by doing of thy Will, that will give entrance into thy Kingdom. O Lord, how deſirous am I, to live my Prayers. And as I eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day pray as thou haſt taught me, that thy Will may be done: So Lord inable me to do thy Will, even when 'tis moſt croſs to my own.</p>
                     <p>Let thy Will commanding be my will obeying. O help me to reſign my will wholly to thine, make me
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:41197:113"/>chearfully to do, and patiently to ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r thy Will.</p>
                     <p>Lord, let they holy Will be done by me, and upon me.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="imprimatur">
                  <p>Imprimatur,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Geo. Thorp, R<hi rend="sup">mo</hi>. in Chriſto P. &amp; D. Domino Guliel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo Archiep. Cant. A Sacris Domeſticis.</signed>
                     <date>May 31. 1678.</date>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:41197:114"/>
            <head>A CATALOGUE OF Some Books Printed for, and Sold by <hi>Nathanael Ranew,</hi> at the Kings Arms in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Folio's.</head>
               <p>THe Works of <hi>Joſephus,</hi> with great diligence Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed and Amended, according to the excellent French Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation of Monſieur <hi>Arnauld d' Andilly.</hi> Alſo the Embaſſy of
<pb facs="tcp:41197:114"/>
                  <hi>Philo Judeus</hi> to the Emperor <hi>Caius Caligula,</hi> never tranſlated before; with the References of the Scripture. A new Map of the Holy Land, and divers Copper Plates ſerving to illuſtrate the Hiſtory.</p>
               <p>The Principles of Chriſtian Religion; with a large Body of Divinity, methodically and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarly handled, by way of Queſtion and Anſwer, for the uſe of Families. Together with Immanuel, or the Myſtery of the Incarnation of the Son of God: by the moſt Reverend <hi>James <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> late Archbiſhop of <hi>Armagh:</hi> To which is added in this ſeventh Edition, twenty Sermons preached at <hi>Oxford</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Majeſty, and elſewhere: Peruſed and publiſhed by his Lordſhips Chaplains; with the
<pb facs="tcp:41197:115"/>Life of the Author, containing many remarkable Paſſages, and an Alphabetical Table never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore extent.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Quarto's.</head>
               <p>The Harmony of the Divine Attributes, in the Contrivance and Accompliſhment of Man's Redemption by the Lord Jeſus Chriſt: or Diſcourſes wherein is ſhewed, how the Wiſdom, Mercy, Juſtice, Holineſs, Power, and Truth of God, are Glorified in that great and bleſſed Work: by <hi>William Bates</hi> D. D. in <hi>quarto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of Wiſdom, three Books writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in French, by <hi>Peter Charron,</hi> Doctor of Law in <hi>Paris:</hi> Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flated by <hi>Sampſon Lennard</hi> in <hi>quarto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Sermon preached at <hi>High-Wickham,</hi> in the County of
<pb facs="tcp:41197:115"/>
                  <hi>Bucks,</hi> wherein the Miniſters Duty is remembred, their Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty aſſerted, Man's Reconciliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with God urged; by <hi>Samuel Gardner,</hi> Chaplain to his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, in <hi>quarto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Norfolk</hi> Feaſt, A Sermon preached at St. <hi>Dunſtans,</hi> being the day of the Anniverſary Feaſt for that County; by <hi>VVil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Smythes</hi> Miniſter in that County, in <hi>quarto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Speech of Sr. <hi>Audley Mervyn</hi> Knight, His Majeſties prime Serjeant of Law, and Speaker of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in <hi>Ireland;</hi> delivered to his Grace Duke of <hi>Ormond,</hi> Lord Lieutenant of <hi>Ireland,</hi> the 13th. <hi>Febr.</hi> 1662. in the Preſence Chamber in the Caſtle in <hi>Dublin.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Octavo's.</head>
               <p>"EYPHKA, "EYPHKA. The Virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb facs="tcp:41197:116"/>Woman found. Her Loſs Bewailed, and Character Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plified in a Sermon preached at <hi>Felſted</hi> in <hi>Eſſex, April</hi> 30. 1678. At the Funeral of that moſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Lady, the Right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and Eminently Religious and Charitable <hi>Mary,</hi> Counteſs Dowager of <hi>VVarwick,</hi> the moſt Illuſtrious Pattern of Sincere Piety, and ſolid Goodneſs this Age hath produced. With ſo large Additions as may be ſtiled The Life of that Noble Lady: By <hi>Anthony VValker,</hi> D. D. and Rector of <hi>Fyfield</hi> in the ſame County. To which are An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed ſome of her Ladiſhips Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Uſeful Meditations.</p>
               <p>A worthy Communicant; or a Treatiſe ſhewing the due or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Receiving the Sacrament of the Lord's Supper: By <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah Dyke,</hi> in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:41197:116"/>
               <p>The Way to Salvation, or the Doctrine of Life Eternal; laid down from ſeveral Texts of Scripture, opened and applied; fitted to the capacity of the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Chirſtian, and uſeful for all Families, by <hi>John Hieron,</hi> in <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctavo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Solitude improved by Divine Meditation, or a Treatiſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Duty, Demonſtrating the Neceſſity, Excellency, Uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, Nature, Kinds, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſites of Divine Meditation: Firſt, intended for a Perſon of Honour, and now Publiſhed for general uſe, by <hi>Nathanael Ranew</hi> ſometime Miniſter of <hi>Felſted</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> in <hi>octavo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moral Vertues Baptized Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, or the Neceſſity of Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity among Chriſtians, by <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Shelton</hi> of <hi>Burſted Magna</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:41197:117"/>
               <p>The Burning of <hi>London</hi> in the Year 1666. Commemorated and Improved in a hundred and ten Meditations and Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, by <hi>Samuel Rolle</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel, and ſometime Fellow of <hi>Trinity Colledge</hi> in <hi>Cambridge:</hi> in <hi>octavo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Natural Theology, or the Knowledge of God from the Works of Creation; Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated and Improved to the Service of Chriſtianity, by <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew Barker:</hi> in <hi>octavo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Chriſt and the Covenant, the Work and way of Meditation; God's Return to the Soul or Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, together with his prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Mercy; Delivered in Ten Sermons by <hi>VVilliam Bridge,</hi> ſometime Miniſter of <hi>Yar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Sinfulneſs of Sin, and the
<pb facs="tcp:41197:117"/>Fulneſs of Chriſt; delivered in two Sermons by the ſame Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor.</p>
               <p>The Vanity of the World by <hi>Ezekiel Hopkins:</hi> in <hi>octavo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Souls Aſcenſion in the ſtate of Separation, by <hi>Iſaac Loeffs:</hi> in <hi>octavo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>An Explication of the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies leſſer Catechiſm, by <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel VVinney:</hi> in <hi>octavo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iter Boreale,</hi> with other ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect Poems; being an exact Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of all hitherto extant, and ſome added, never before Printed, by <hi>Robert VVild</hi> D. D. in <hi>octavo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Synopſis of Quakeriſm, or a Collection of the Fundamental Errors of the Quakers, by <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Danſon:</hi> in <hi>octavo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Poetical Meditation, wherein the Uſefulneſs, Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency,
<pb facs="tcp:41197:118"/>and ſeveral perfections of Holy Scriptures are briefly hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, by <hi>John Clark:</hi> in <hi>octavo.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Twelves.</head>
               <p>Correction, Inſtruction, or a Treatiſe of Affliction, firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by way of private Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, afterwards digeſted into certain Sermons, and now publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed for the help and comfort of humble ſuffering Chriſtians: by <hi>Tho: Caſe,</hi> in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Poor doubting Chriſtian, drawn to Chriſt, by <hi>Thomas Hooker</hi> of <hi>New-England,</hi> in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ovids Metamorphoſis</hi> in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh verſe, by <hi>George Sandy's</hi> in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aeſop's</hi> Fables, in Proſe with Cuts, in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Principles of Chriſtian Religion, with a brief Method of
<pb facs="tcp:41197:118"/>the Doctrine thereof, Correct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Enlarged by the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend <hi>James <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Armagh,</hi> in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A plain Diſcourſe of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of having Godly Parents, with the Duties of ildren that have ſuch Parents, by <hi>M. Goddard,</hi> in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Novum Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum; huic editioni omnia Difficiliorum vocabulorum The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mata, quae in</hi> Georgii Paſſoris <hi>Lex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ico Grammatice reſolvuntur in Margine appoſuit</hi> Carolus Hoole; <hi>in eorum ſcilicet gratiam qui pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi Graecae Linguae Tyrocinia fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciunt:</hi> in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
